Amadeus.Directors.Cut.1984.DVDRip.XviD-UnSeeN
Mozart.
Forgive your assassin.
I confess, I killed you.
Si, I killed you, Mozart.
Mozart, pieta.
Forgive your assassin.
Forgive me, Mozart.
Signore Salieri,
open the door, be good now.
Signore,
we have something special for you.
Something you're going to love.
Is that good.
Signore, believe me,
this is the most delicious thing
I ever ate in my life.
Really, you don't know
what you're miss...
All right, that's enough Signore.
Open the door.
Signore, if you don't open this door...
we`re gonna eat everything and
we're gonna leave nothing for you.
And I'm never gonna come
see you again.
Good morning, Father.
Herr Salieri?
Leave me alone.
I cannot leave alone a soul in pain.
Do you know who I`am?
That makes no difference.
All men are equal in God's eyes.
Are they?
Offer me your confession.
I can offer you God's forgiveness.
How well are you trained in music?
I know a little.
I studied it in my youth.
- Where?
- Here in Vienna.
Then you must know this.
I can't say that I do.
What is it?
It was a very popular tune in its day.
I wrote it.
Here, how about this?
This one brought down the house
when we played the first.
Well?
I regret it is not too familiar.
Can you recall no melody of mine?
I was the most famous composer
in Europe.
I wrote 40 operas alone.
Here.
What about this one?
Yes, I know that.
That's charming.
I'm sorry, I didn't know you wrote that.
I didn't.
That was Mozart.
Wolfgang...
Amadeus Mozart.
The man you accuse yourself of killing.
You've heard that?
Is it true?
For God's sake, my son...
if you have something to confess,
do it now.
Give yourself some peace.
He...
was my idol.
Mozart.
I can't think of a time
when I didn't know his name.
I was playing childish games,
when he was playing music
for kings and emperors.
Even the pope in Rome.
I admit, I was jealous,
when I heard the tales they told about him.
None of the brilliant little prodigy,
but of his father,
who had taught him everything.
My father, he did not care for music.
When I told him,
how I wished I could be like Mozart,
he would say,
"Why? Do you want to be a trained monkey?
You'd like me to drag you around Europe,
doing tricks like a circus freak?".
How could I tell him
what music meant to me?
While my father prayed earnestly to God,
to protect commerce,
I would offer up,
secretly...
the proudest prayer a boy could think of.
"Lord, make me a great composer.
Let me celebrate your glory through music,
and be celebrated myself.
Make me famous through the world,
dear God.
Make me immortal.
After I die...
let people speak my name forever
with love for what I wrote.
In return...
I will give you my chastity...
my industry...
my deepest humility,
every hour of my life.
Amen".
And do you know what happened?
A miracle.
My life changed forever.
Of course I knew God had arranged it all.
That was obvious.
One minute I was a frustrated boy
in an obscure little town.
The next I was here...
in Vienna, city of musicians...
and Emperor Joseph, the musical king.
In a few years, I was his court composer.
Isn't that incredible?
Night after night I sat right next
to the emperor of Austria
playing duets with him,
correcting the royal sight-reading.
Actually, the man had no ear at all.
But what did it matter?
He adored my music.
Tell me.
If you had been me,
wouldn't you have thought
God had accepted your vow?
And believe me, I honored it.
I was a model of virtue.
I kept my hands off women.
I worked hours every day teaching students,
many of them for free.
Sitting on endless committees
to help poor musicians.
Work and work and work,
that was all my life.
And it was wonderful.
Everybody liked me.
I liked myself.
Until he came.
He came to Vienna to play
some of his music,
at the residence of his employer,
the Prince Archbishop of Salzburg.
Eagerly, I went there to seek him out.
That night...
changed my life.
As I wandered through the salon,
I played a little game with myself.
This man had written
his first concerto at the age of 4,
his first symphony at 7,
a full-scale opera at 12.
Did it show?
Is talent like that
written on the face?
Which one of them
could he be?
Mozart is not here.
- Stop it.
- I`am.
- I`am stopping it.
I`am. I'm stopping it. Slowly.
There. You see? I've stopped.
- Now we're going back.
- No.
Yes, yes.
Listen, you don't know where you are.
Here, everything goes backwards.
People walk backwards, and dance backwards,
and sing backwards and even talk backwards.
- That's stupid.
- Why? People fart backwards.
Ssa-ym-ssik.
Yes, you are. You are very sick.
No. Say it backwards, shitwit.
Ssa-ym-ssik.
Ssik, kiss.
Ym, my. Ssa.
Kiss my ass.
Em-yrram.
- No, I'm not playing this game.
- Say it, it's serious.
It's very serious.
Yrram.
Marry me.
No... I'm not gonna marry you.
You're a fiend.
Uoy-evol-I-tub.
Tub.
But I...
love...
But I love you?
- Tihs-ym-tae.
- What?
- Eat.
- Ym, my.
- My.
Tihs. Eat my shit.
You filthy fiend.
You filthy...
My music.
They've started without me.
That was Mozart.
That giggling, dirty creature
I'd just seen crawling on the floor.
- I think that went off remarkably well, don't you?
- Indeed.
The Viennese certainly know good music
when they hear it, don't you think?
Certainly.
Your Grace.
Ah, Mozart.
- Why?
- Why what, sir?
Why do I have to be humiliated
in front of my guests,
by one of my own servants?
The more license I allow you,
the more you take.
If His Grace is not satisfied with me,
he can dismiss me.
I wish you to return immediately
to Salzburg.
- Your father is waiting for you there, patiently.
- No, Your Grace.
I mean, with all humility,
I would prefer you dismissed me.
It's obvious I don't satisfy.
I have no intention of dismissing you.
You will remain in my service
and learn your place.
On the page it looked...
Nothing.
The beginning was simple, almost comic.
Just a pulse.
Bassoons, basset horns...
like a rusty squeezebox.
And then, suddenly,
high above it...
an oboe.
A single note, hanging there, unwavering.
Until...
a clarinet took it over...
sweetened it into a phrase of such delight.
This was no composition
by a performing monkey.
This was a music I had never heard.
Filled with such longing,
such unfulfillable longing.
It seemed to me I was hearing
the voice of God.
Excuse me.
But why?
Why would God choose an obscene child
to be his instrument?
It was not to be believed.
This piece had to be an accident.
It had to be.
It better be.
How good is he, this Mozart?
He's remarkable, Majesty.
I heard an extraordinary serious opera of his last month.
- Idomeneo, King of Crete.
- That?
A most tiresome piece. I heard it too.
Tiresome?
A young man trying to impress
beyond his abilities.
Too much spice.
Too many notes.
Majesty...
I thought it was
the most promising work
I've heard in years.
Well then, we should make some effort
to acquire him.
We could use a good German composer
in Vienna, surely?
I'm sure he could be tempted
with the right offer. Say...
an opera in German
for our National Theater.
Excellent, sire.
But not German. I beg, Your Majesty.
Italian is the proper language for opera.
All educated people agree on that.
What do you think, Chamberlain?
In my opinion, sire,
it's time we had a piece in our own language.
Plain German for plain people.
Kapellmeister?
Majesty...
I must agree with Herr Direttore.
German is...
too brute for singing.
Court composer...
what do you think?
I think it's an interesting notion
to keep Mozart in Vienna, Majesty.
It should really infuriate the archbishop
beyond measure,
if that is Your Majesty's intention.
You are cattivo, court composer.
I want to meet this young man.
Chamberlain, arrange a pleasant welcome for him.
Well, there it is.
This is a beautiful wig for you.
It looks so marvelous and I love it.
The other one.
Here is the other one.
I think you will love it.
Here's the third one.
So? Here we go.
- How do you like it?
- They're all so beautiful.
Why don't I have three heads?
This is funny.
Three heads.
Gentlemen.
- Good morning.
- Morning, Your Majesty.
What do you have for me today?
- Your Majesty, Herr Mozart.
- Yes, what about him?
He's here.
Well, there it is. Good.
Your Majesty, I hope you won't find it improper,
but I've written a little march of welcome in his honor.
What a charming idea, court composer.
May I see?
Just a...
Just a trifle, of course.
- May I try it?
- Majesty!
Let's have some fun.
Delightful, court composer.
May I play it when he comes in?
- You do me too much honor, sire.
- Bring in Herr Mozart, please.
But... slowly, slowly.
I need a minute to practice.
Good, continue.
G, Majesty.
Excellent.
Good, Majesty.
Continue. Very good.
Very good, Majesty.
Tempo. Up.
Lightly, then strongly.
It's a march, Majesty.
Again.
Bravo, Majesty.
Gentlemen, please.
A little less enthusiasm, I beg you.
No, please, please.
It's not a holy relic.
You know, we have met before.
In this very room.
Perhaps you don't remember it, you were only 6 years old.
He was giving the most delightful concert here.
As he got off the stool,
he slip and fell.
My own sister Antoinette helped him up.
And you know what he did?
He jumped into her arms and said,
"Will you marry me?
Yes or no?".
You know all these gentlemen, I`m sure.
The Baron Van Swieten.
- I'm a great admirer of yours, young men.
- Thank you.
Kapellmeister Bonno.
My pleasure.
The Director of Opera,
Count Orsini-Rosenberg.
Sir, yes.
The honor is mine, absolutely.
Here is our illustrious court composer,
Maestro Salieri.
At last, such immense joy.
I know your work well, signore.
Do you know,
I actually composed some variations
on a melody of yours.
- Really? Which one?
- "Mio Caro Adone".
I'm flattered.
A funny little tune,
but it yielded good things.
And now he has returned the compliment.
Herr Salieri composed
this little march of welcome for you.
Really?
Well, there it is.
Now...
Down to business.
Young man, we're going to commission
an opera from you.
What do you say?
Did we vote in the end for German
or Italian?
Well actually sire, if you remember,
we did finally incline to Italian.
Did we?
I don't think it was really decided,
Your Majesty.
German.
Please let it be German.
Why so?
Because I've already found
the most wonderful libretto.
Have I seen it?
I don't think you have, Herr Direktor,
not yet. It's quite new.
- I'll show it to you immediately, of course.
- I think you'd better.
Well tell us about it.
Tell us the story.
Well, it's quite amusing, Majesty.
It's set...
The whole thing is set in a...
Yes? Where?
In a harem, Majesty. In a seraglio.
- You mean in Turkey?
- Yes, exactly.
Then why especially
does it have to be in German?
It doesn't, especially.
It could be in Turkish if you really want.
No, my dear fellow,
the language is not finally the point.
Do you really think that subject is quite appropriate
for a national theater?
Why not? It's charming.
I mean, I won't actually show concubines
exposing their...
It's not indecent.
It's highly moral, Majesty.
It's full of proper German virtues.
Excuse me, Majesty,
but what do you think these could be?
Being a foreigner, I'd love to learn.
Well, tell him, Mozart.
Name us a German virtue.
- Love, sire.
- Oh, love.
Of course,
in Italy we know nothing about love.
No, I don't think you do.
Watching Italian opera,
all those male sopranos screeching,
stupid fat couples rolling their eyes about.
That's not love. It's just rubbish.
Majesty, you choose the language.
I'll be my task to set it to the finest music
ever offered a monarch.
Well, there it is.
Let it be German.
This is yours.
Keep it.
It's already here in my head.
What? On one hearing only?
I think so, sire. Yes.
Show us.
The rest is just the same, isn't it?
That doesn't really work, does it?
Did you try...?
Shouldn't it be a bit more...?
Or this?
This. Yes.
Better? What do you think?
Grazie, Signore.
All I ever wanted was to sing to God.
He gave me that longing...
and then made me mute.
Why?
Tell me that.
If he didn't want me
to praise him with music,
why implant the desire...
like a lust in my body?
And then deny me the talent?
Madame Cavalieri is here
for her lesson, sir.
Maestro.
Well...?
How do you like it?
It's Turkish.
My hairdresser said everything this year's
is going to be Turkish.
Does he?
What else did he tell you today?
Come, come.
Give me some gossip.
Well, I heard you met Herr Mozart.
News travels fast in Vienna.
And he's been commissioned to write an opera.
Is it true?
- Yes.
- Is there a part in it for me?
- No.
- How do you know?
Do you know where it's set, my dear?
Where?
In a harem.
- What's that?
- A brothel.
Come.
Let's begin.
- What does he look like?
- Mozart?
- You might be disappointed.
- Why?
Looks and talent
don't always go together, Katerina.
Looks don't concern me, maestro.
Only talent interests a woman of taste.
Shall we continue?
There she was.
I don't know where they met or how.
There she stood.
On stage, for all to see.
Showing off like the greedy songbird she was.
Ten minutes of ghastly scales.
Arpeggios.
Whizzing up and down
like fireworks at a fairground.
Understand, I was in love with the girl.
Or at least in lust.
And I swear to you,
I never laid a finger on her.
All the same, I couldn't bear
to think of anyone else touching her.
Least of all, "the creature".
Brava, madame.
You are an ornament to our stage.
Your Majesty.
Well, Herr Mozart. A good effort.
Well, decidedly that.
An excellent effort.
You have shown us something quite new tonight.
It is new.
- It is, isn't it, sire?
- Yes, indeed.
So then, you liked it?
You really liked it, sire?
Well, of course I did. It's very good.
Of course, now and then,
just now and then,
it seemed a touch...
What do you mean, sire?
Well, I mean, occasionally,
it seems to have...
How shall one say...?
How shall one say, direktor?
- Too many notes, Your Majesty?
- Exactly. Very well put.
- Too many notes.
- I don't understand.
There are just as many notes, Majesty,
as I required, neither more nor less.
My dear fellow, there are in fact
only so many notes the ear can hear
in a course of an evening.
I think I'm right in saying that,
aren't I, court composer?
Yes. On the whole, yes, Majesty.
This is absurd.
Young man, don't take it too hard.
Your work is ingenious.
It's quality work.
And there are simply too many notes,
that`s all.
Just cut a few and it'll be perfect.
Which few did you have in mind, Majesty?
Wolfgang.
Wolfgang, my dear.
- Wolfgang.
- Majesty, this is Frau Weber.
She's my landlady.
- Enchanted, madame.
- Sire, such an honor.
This is my dear daughter, Constanze.
- She's the fiancée of Herr Mozart.
- Really?
How charming. Please.
Well...
When do you marry?
We haven't exactly received
my father's consent yet.
Not entirely. Not altogether.
- Excuse me, but how old are you?
- 26.
Well, my advice is for you to marry
this charming young lady
- and stay with us in Vienna.
- You see?
I told him that, Your Majesty.
but he won't listen to me.
Your Majesty,
you give such wonderful...
such royal advice.
May I...?
Well, there it is.
Wolfie, will you get some water?
Will you get some water, please?
Wolfie, get some water.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
Did you know?
- What?
- The marriage.
What does it matter to you?
Nothing.
He can marry who he pleases,
I don't give a damn.
How was I?
You were sublime.
And what did you think of the music?
Extremely clever.
Katerina, I...
Excuse me.
Is that woman still lying
on the floor?
- No, she's fine.
- Oh, I'm so relieved.
Dear Mozart,
my sincere congratulations.
- Did you like it then?
- How could I not?
It really is the best music one can hear in Vienna today,
don't you agree?
She must be dazzling in bed.
I assume she's the virtuoso
in that department.
There can`t be any other reason
why you'd marry someone like that.
Come in.
Excuse me.
Wolfie, Mom isn't feeling very well.
- Can we go home, now?
- Yes.
No, no, no.
You can't take him away now.
This is his night.
Won't you introduce us, Wolfgang?
Excuse us, Fraulein.
Good night, signore.
At that moment I knew,
beyond any doubt,
he'd had her.
The creature had had my darling girl.
It was incomprehensible.
What was God up to?
Was it possible I was being tested?
Was God expecting me to offer forgivenes,
in the face of every offense?
No matter how painful?
It's very possible.
But why him?
Why choose Mozart
to teach me lessons in humility?
My heart was filling up
with such hatred for that little man.
For the first time in my life,
I began to know
really...
violent thoughts.
Every day, sometimes for hours,
I would pray.
Lord...
please...
send him away,
back to Salzburg.
For his sake...
as well as mine.
- No. I won't have him back.
- But, Your Grace...
Your son is an unprincipled,
spoiled, conceited brat.
Yes, sir,
that is the truth.
But don't blame him.
The fault is mine, entirely.
I was too indulgent with him.
Please, Your Grace?
Give him one more chance?
You have leave to try.
God bless, Your Grace.
I thank Your Grace.
I thank you.
I write to you with urgent news.
I'm coming to Vienna.
Take no further steps towards marriage
until we meet.
As you honor the father
who has devoted his entire life to yours,
do as I bid and await my coming.
I now join you
in the holy bonds of matrimony.
Those whom God hath joined together,
let no man put asunder.
Most beloved father:
Remember how you always told me Vienna is the city of musicians.
To conquer here is to conquer Europe.
With my wife I can do it.
One day soon, when I'm wealthy man,
you'll come and live with us,
and we'll be so happy.
Good morning court composer.
This is my niece, the Princess Elizabeth.
Your Highness.
She's asked me to advise her
in a suitable musical instructor.
- I think I've come up with an excellent idea.
- Your Majesty.
It would be such a tremendous honor.
I was thinking of Herr Mozart.
What is your view?
It's an interesting idea,
Majesty, but...
Yes?
My concern is to protect you
from any hint of favoritism.
Favoritism.
- What is this, Herr Chamberlain?
- What is what?
Why must I submit samples of my work
to some stupid committee
just to teach a thirteen-year-old girl?
Because His Majesty wishes it.
Is the emperor angry with me?
Quite the contrary.
Then why doesn`t he simply appoint me
to the post?
Mozart, you are not
the only composer in Vienna.
No. But I'm the best.
Mozart.
A little modesty might suit you better.
Who is on this committee?
Kapellmeister Bonno, Count Orsini-Rosenberg
and, of course, court composer Salieri.
Naturally, the Italians.
Of course, always the Italians.
They're all musical idiots.
And you want them to judge my music?
Young man,
the issue is quite simple.
If you want this position,
you must submit your stuff,
along with all your colleagues.
Must I?
Well, I won't.
How are we supposed to live, Wolfie?
Do you want me to go
in the streets and beg?
Don't be stupid.
- All they want to see is your work.
- Shit.
- What's wrong with that?
- Shut up. Just shut up.
One royal pupil,
and all of Vienna will come flocking.
They'll come anyway.
- No, they won't.
- They love me here.
- I know how things work in this city.
- You always know everything, don't you?
- Yes?
- Excuse me, sir.
- There is a lady who insists on talking to you.
- Who is she?
She didn't say,
but she says it's urgent.
Excuse me, my dear.
Your Excellency.
How can I help you?
Frau Mozart?
I've come on behalf of my husband.
I brought you some samples of his work,
so he can be considered
for the royal appointment.
How charming,
but why did he not come himself?
Well, he's terribly busy, sir.
I understand.
I will look at them of course,
the moment I can.
It will be an honor.
Please give him my warmest regards.
Would it be too much trouble, sir,
to ask you to look at them now?
- While I wait.
- I'm afraid I'm not at leisure
this precise moment.
Just leave them with me.
I assure you, they will be quite safe.
I really cannot do that, sir.
You see, he doesn't know I'm here.
Then he didn't send you?
No, sir. This was my own idea.
- I see.
- Sir, we're desperate.
We really need this job.
My husband spends far more
than he can ever earn.
I don't mean that he's lazy because he`s not at all,
he works all day long.
It's just that he's not practical.
Money simply slips through his fingers.
It's ridiculous.
Let me offer you some refreshment.
Do you know what these are?
Capezzoli di Venere.
Nipples of Venus.
They're Roman chestnuts in brandied sugar.
Try one. Go on, try one.
They're quite surprising.
They're wonderful.
Thank you very much,
Your Excellency.
Don't keep calling me that.
Keeps me at such a distance.
I wasn't born a court composer,
you know.
I'm from a small town.
Just like your husband.
Are you sure you can't leave this
and come back again?
It's very tempting, sir.
But it's impossible, I'm afraid.
Wolfgang would be frantic
if he found those were missing.
You see, they're all originals.
- Originals?
- Yes, sir. He doesn't make copies.
These...
are originals?
Astounding.
It was actually... It was beyond belief.
These were first and only
drafts of music.
But they showed no corrections of any kind.
Not one.
He had simply written down music,
already finished in his head.
Page after page of it.
As if he were just taking dictation.
And music...
finished as no music is ever finished.
Displace one note,
and there would be diminishment.
Displace one phrase,
and the structure would fall.
It was clear to me.
That sound I had heard
in the archbishop's palace
had been no accident.
Here again was the very voice of God.
I was staring through the cage
of those meticulous ink strokes,
at an absolute beauty.
Is it not good?
It is miraculous.
Yes, he's very proud of his work.
So you will help us?
I dine with the emperor
tomorrow evening.
One word from me and the post is his.
Thank you, Your Excellency.
Thank you.
Come back tonight.
- Tonight?
- Alone.
What for?
Some service deserves service in return.
No?
- What do you mean?
- Isn't it obvious?
It's a post all Vienna seeks.
If you wish it for your husband,
come tonight.
I'm a married woman, sir.
Then don't.
It's up to you.
And not to be vague,
that is the price.
There is no God of mercy, Father.
Just a God of torture.
Evening came.
I sat there,
not knowing whether she would return or not.
I prayed as I had never prayed before.
Dear God...
enter me now.
Fill me with one piece of true music.
One piece with your breath in it,
so I know that you love me.
Show me one sign of your favor,
and I will show mine to Mozart.
I will get him the royal position.
Enter me.
Please.
Yes?
That lady is back, sir.
Show her in.
Well?
I'm here.
My husband has gone to a concert.
He didn't think I would enjoy it.
Well, where shall we go?
Should we stay here?
Well...
Do you still want to look at these?
Or don't we need to bother anymore?
Suppose we don't, really.
Show this woman out.
Stanzi.
What is it?
What's the matter?
Tell me.
I love you.
From now on, we are enemies.
You and I.
Because you choose for your instrument
a boastful, lustful, smutty,
infantile boy,
and give me for reward only the ability
to recognize the incarnation.
Because you are unjust...
unfair...
unkind...
I will block you.
I swear it.
I will hinder and harm
your creature on earth,
as far as I`am able.
Majesty, I don't like to talk
against a fellow musician.
Of course not.
I have to tell you.
Mozart is not entirely to be trusted alone
with young ladies.
Really?
As a matter of fact, one of my own pupils,
a very young singer,
Maria Theresa Paradis,
told me she was...
Well...
Well, what?
Molested, Majesty.
Twice, in the course of the same lesson.
Sir, there is a Herr Mozart
waiting for you in the salon.
- Whom did they choose?
- Herr Zummer.
Herr Zummer?
But the man's a fool.
He's a total mediocrity.
No, no.
He has yet to achieve mediocrity.
I can't lose this post.
I simply can't.
Excellency, please.
Let's go to the palace.
And you can talk to the emperor
and tell him that Herr Zummer
is an awful choice.
He could actually do musical harm
to the Princess Elizabeth.
Between you and me,
no one in the world
could do musical harm
to the Princess Elizabeth.
Look...
I must have pupils.
Without pupils, I can't manage.
You don't mean to tell me
that you're living in poverty?
No, but I'm broke.
Well, how is this possible?
You give concerts, don`t you?
I hear they`re quite successful.
They're stupendously successful.
You can't get a seat.
The only trouble is no one will hire me.
They want to hear me play,
but they won't let me teach their daughters,
as if I was some kind of a fiend.
Seriously,
is there any chance
you could manage a loan?
Only for six months.
Eight, at the most.
You expect your fortunes to change
in six or eight months?
As a matter of fact, I do.
I`am working on something that is
going to explode like a bomb shell
all over Europe.
After that I'll be the richest man in Vienna.
I'll pay you back double. Anything.
You name the terms.
Well, how exciting.
Tell me more.
I better not,
it's a bit of a secret.
Come, come, Mozart,
I'm interested.
This is delicious. What is it?
It's cream cheese mixed with
granulated sugar,
suffused with rum.
Crema Mascarpone Speciale.
Italian.
Forgive me.
We all have patriotic feelings of some kind.
Two thou...
Two hundred florins.
That's all I need.
A hundred.
Fifty.
What exactly are you working on?
Really, I can't say.
I don't think you should become known
in Vienna as a debtor, Mozart.
However...
However, I know a very
distinguished gentleman
I can recommend to you.
And he has a daughter.
Quiet. Quiet.
Herr Mozart.
Welcome. Pay no attention, they're impossible.
Just ignore them.
I treat them just like my own children.
Which of them do you wish me to teach?
That's funny.
You're a funny fellow.
This is the instrument, Herr Mozart,
I hope it's to your satisfaction.
Of course it'll be to his satisfaction.
Come, we're going to listen to some music.
Come.
Good boy.
Now.
Please play me something,
just to give me an idea.
Anything will do.
Just go ahead.
Just as if we weren't here.
Part of music, getting used to an audience.
Am I right, Herr Mozart?
Perhaps it would be better
if we were left alone.
I think we're both a little shy.
Play.
- I said play.
- Michael, please.
Perhaps if I would play something first,
it might encourage the Fraulein.
Why don't you let me try the instrument?
Stop it. Stop.
He always howls when he hears music.
We've got to break him of that habit.
We've got to break them of their habit.
Play. Please.
Herr Mozart, play. Please, I beg you.
That's it. That's it.
Keep playing.
Keep playing. That's it.
Mozart, that's wonderful.
Wonderful.
Well, next time you wish me
to instruct another one of your dogs,
please let me know.
Goodbye, Fraulein.
Goodbye, madam.
Goodbye, sir.
Papa?
Papa.
Why are you here?
Am I not welcome?
Of course, welcome.
Papa, welcome. Welcome.
You're very thin.
Doesn't she feed you, that wife of yours?
Feed? Of course she feeds me.
She stuffs me like a goose all day long.
- Is she not here?
- No, she had to help her mother.
Yes, she's like that.
Her mother's a very sweet woman,
you'Il...
I didn't know you were home.
Stanzi, this is my father.
We'll wait. We'll wait.
Why don't you get up now,
my darling?
She's very tired, poor creature.
You know me. I'm such a pig.
It's not easy cleaning up after me.
Don't you have a maid?
Oh. No. We could if we wanted,
but Stanzi wouldn`t hear it,
she insists on doing everything herself.
How is your...
financial situation?
Couldn't be better.
That's not what I hear.
What do you mean?
It's wonderful.
Really, it's marvelous.
People love me here.
They say you have debts.
Who?
Who says that?
That's a malicious lie.
Do you have pupils?
I don't want pupils.
They get in the way.
I have to have time for composition.
Composition doesn't pay.
You know that.
That one will.
What's that?
It's a secret.
Secret?
You don't have secrets from me.
No. Please. I don't want you to see it.
I don't want anyone to see it.
But you are going to be
so proud of me, Papa.
It`s going to be the best thing that I've ever done.
The best thing anyone...
There she is.
Look at her. Isn't she beautiful?
Come on now, Papa, confess it.
- Could you want a prettier girl for a daughter?
- Stop it, Wolfie.
I look dreadful.
Are you...
expecting?
Yes, I`am.
Isn't it marvelous?
We're delighted.
- May I offer you some tea, Herr Mozart?
- Who wants tea? Let's go out.
This calls for a feast.
You don't want tea, do you Papa?
I know. Let's go dancing.
Papa loves parties, don't you?
How can you be so boring? Tea.
Come on, Papa. Hurry.
Here we go. Good day.
Now.
I name the penalty.
And the penalty is...
- Give her a good one.
- Show us your legs.
Come on, come on.
It's just a game, Papa.
Thank you.
Herr Mozart, why don't you name
your son's penalty?
Yes, Papa. Name it.
Name it.
I'll do anything you say. Anything.
I want you to come back
to Salzburg with me, my son.
The rule is you can only give me a penalty
that can be performed in the room.
I'm tired of this game.
I don`t wanna play anymore.
But my penalty.
I've got to have a penalty.
I name a penalty.
The penalty is,
you shall play our little tune
in the manner of
Johann Sebastian Bach.
- Turn him over.
- Over?
Now you play it backwards.
- Another one. Give me another one.
- Play it like Gluck.
- Boring. Another.
- Handel.
I don't like him. Another one.
Play Salieri.
Now that is a challenge.
That is a challenge.
Please. Please.
Go on. Mock me. Laugh.
That was not Mozart laughing, Father.
That was God.
That was God laughing at me
through that obscene giggle.
Go on, Signore. Laugh.
Show my mediocrity for all to see.
One day I will laugh at you.
Before I leave this earth...
I will laugh at you.
- Wolfie?
- What?
There's a young girl here to see you.
What does she want?
She won't talk to me.
She says she has to speak to you.
Damn.
Yes?
- Are you Herr Mozart?
- That's right.
My name is Lorl, sir.
I'm a maidservant.
I was asked to come here
and offer my services to you.
They'll be paid for, by a great admirer of yours
who wishes to remain...
anonymous.
Is this your idea, Papa?
Mine?
- Are you playing a trick on me?
- I've never seen this girl in my life.
- Is this some kind of joke?
- Not at all, sir.
Young woman, this won't do at all.
My son cannot possibly accept such an offer,
no matter how generous,
- unless he knows who's behind it.
- But I really can't tell you that, sir.
- This is ridiculous.
- What is ridiculous?
Wolfie has many admirers in Vienna.
They love him here.
People send us gifts all the time.
You cannot possibly accept her
without references.
Well, this is none of your business.
- Whoever sent you is going to pay?
- That's right, ma'am.
Splendid. Now we're going
to let a perfect stranger into our house.
Who is we? Who is letting who...?
- Could you please wait outside?
- Yes, ma'am.
Look, old man.
We spend a fortune on you,
and all you can do is criticize from morning to night.
- And now...
- Stanzi.
No. It's right that he should hear.
I'm sick to death of it.
We can't do anything right for you,
can we?
You won't have to do anything for me
ever again.
I'm leaving.
- No, Papa.
- Don`t worry, I won't stay here to be a burden to anyone.
No one calls you that.
She does. She says I sleep all day.
And so you do.
The only time you come out is to eat.
Well, what do you expect?
Do you expect anyone to walk out
into a mess like this every day?
- So now I'm a bad housekeeper.
- So you are. This place is like a pigsty all day.
When can you start?
- Right away, ma'am.
- Good.
They're out every night, sir.
Thank you, sir.
Do any pupils come to the house?
Not that I've seen.
Then how does he pay for all this?
Does he work at all?
Yes, sir. All day long.
He never leaves the house till evening.
He just sits there,
writing and writing.
Really?
What is it he's writing?
I wouldn't know that, sir.
Of course not.
You're a good girl.
You're very kind to do this.
The next time you're sure
they'll be out of the house, let me know.
Thank you, sir.
I think I found out about the money, sir.
Yes? What?
He kept seven snuffboxes in here.
I could swear they were all gold.
And now look.
There's only one left.
Where does he work?
In there, sir.
Gentlemen, I've just heard some news
that may be of interest you.
What?
Mozart is writing a new opera.
An Italian opera.
Italian?
That's not all.
He has chosen for his subject, Figaro.
The Marriage of Figaro.
He's setting that play to music?
Yes.
What is this Marriage of Figaro?
It's a French play, Kapellmeister.
It has been banned by the emperor.
You're absolutely sure?
Herr Mozart.
Gentlemen, sit down.
Mozart.
Are you aware that I have declared
the French play of Figaro
unsuitable for our theater?
Yes, sire.
Yet we hear you're making an opera from it.
Is this true?
Who told you this, Majesty?
It is not your place to ask questions.
Is it true?
Yes, I...
I admit it is.
Would you tell me why?
Majesty, it is only a comedy.
What you think, Herr Mozart,
is scarcely the point.
It's what His Majesty thinks that counts.
But, Your Majesty...
Mozart...
I`am a tolerant man.
I do not censor things lightly.
When I do, I have good reason.
Figaro is a bad play.
It stirs up hatred between the classes.
In France, it has caused nothing but bitterness.
My own dear sister, Antoinette, writes me that
she is beginning to be frightened of her own people.
Sire, I swear to Your Majesty,
there's nothing like that in the piece.
I've taken out everything that could give offense.
I hate politics.
I'm afraid you're rather innocent, my friend.
In these dangerous times I cannot afford
to provoke our nobles or our people,
simply over a theater piece.
Majesty, this is just a frolic.
Is a piece about love.
"Love". Again.
And it's new.
It's entirely new.
So new, the people will go mad for it.
I have scenes...
The end of the second act, for example.
It starts out as a simple duet.
Just a husband and a wife quarreling.
Suddenly, the wife scheming little maid comes in.
It's a very funny situation.
Duet turns into trio.
Then the husband's valet comes in.
He`s plotting with the maid.
Trio turns into quartet.
Then a stupid old gardener comes in.
Quartet becomes quintet.
And so on, on and on.
Sextet, septet, octet.
How long do you think I can sustain that, Majesty?
I have no idea.
Guess.
Guess, Your Majesty.
Imagine the longest time such a thing could be sustained,
and then double it.
Well...
Six...
seven minutes?
- Eight minutes?
- Twenty, sire. Twenty minutes.
Twenty minutes of continuous music.
No recitatives.
Sire, only opera can do this.
In a play, if more than one person
speaks at the same time it´s...
just noise,
no one can`t understand a word.
But with opera, with music...
with music, you can have 20 individuals,
all talking at the same time.
And it's not noise.
It's a perfect harmony.
Mozart, music is not the issue here.
No one doubts your talent.
It's your judgment of literature that's in question.
Even with the politics taken out,
this thing it would still remain a vulgar farce.
Why waste your spirit on such rubbish?
Surely you can choose
more elevated themes.
Elevated.
What does that mean, elevated?
I`am fed to the teeth
with all these elevated things.
Old dead legends.
Why must we go on forever
writing only about gods and legends?
Because they do.
They go on forever.
At least what they represent:
The eternal in us.
Opera is here to ennoble us, Mozart.
You and me,
just the same as His Majesty.
"Bello, bello, bello".
Come on now, be honest.
Which one of you would rather listen to your hairdresser
than Hercules, or Horatius or Orpheus.
People so lofty,
they sound as if they shit marble.
What?
Govern your tongue, Mozart.
How dare you.
Forgive me, Majesty.
I'm a vulgar man.
But I assure you, my music is not.
You are passionate, Mozart.
But you do not persuade.
Sire, the whole opera is finished.
Do you know how much work
went into it?
His Majesty has been
more than patient, Signore.
How can I persuade Your Majesty
if you won´t let me show it?
That will do, Herr Mozart.
Just let me tell you how it begins.
May I just do that, Majesty?
Show you how it begins?
Just that?
Please.
Look...
There's a servant down on his knees.
And do you know why?
Not from any oppression, no,
because he's measuring a space.
And do you know what for?
His bed. His wedding bed.
To see if it will fit.
Late.
On the beat.
Good.
Yes.
Early.
Well, Mozart is already rehearsing.
In that case, gentlemen, I think...
I think we should help Mozart all we can.
And do our best to protect him
against the emperor's anger.
What anger?
About the ballet.
What ballet?
Excuse me but,
didn't His Majesty specifically forbid
the ballet in his opera?
- Herr Mozart.
- Yes?
- A word with you, please.
- Certainly, Herr Direktor.
Now, Herr Mozart.
Five minutes, please.
Five minutes.
Yes?
Do you not know that His Majesty
has expressly forbidden ballet in his operas?
- Yes but this is not a ballet, this is a dance of Figaro`s wedding.
- Exactly, a dance.
Surely, His Majesty didn't mean prohibit a dance
when it's part of the story, Herr Direktor.
It's dangerous to interpret His Majesty edicts.
Give me your score, please.
Thank you.
What are you doing, Herr Direktor?
Taking out what you should
never have put in.
Please. Please.
I have no one else to turn to.
- What is it?
- It's unbelievable.
The direktor has actually torn up
a huge section of my music.
They say I have to rewrite the opera.
But it's perfect as it is.
I can't...
rewrite what's perfect.
Please.
Can't you talk to him?
Why bother with Rosenberg?
He's obviously no friend of yours.
I could kill him.
I mean, really. Kill him.
I actually threw the entire score into the fire,
he made me so angry.
- You burned the score?
- No, my wife took it out in time.
Thank God.
It's not fair that a man like that
should have power over our work.
But there are those
who have power over him.
I think I'll take this up
with the emperor.
Excellency...
would you?
With all my heart, Mozart.
Thank you.
Please, Herr Mozart.
"Please, it's not a holy relic".
I don't need to tell you I said nothing,
whatever, to the emperor.
I went to the theater ready
to tell Mozart something, anything.
When suddenly,
in the middle of the third act
to my astonishment, the emperor,
who never attended rehearsals,
suddenly appeared.
What is this?
I don't understand.
Is it modern?
Majesty...
the Herr Direktor,
he has removed un balletto
that would have occurred at this place.
Why?
It is your regulation, sire.
No ballet in your opera.
Salieri.
Do you like this?
It's not a question of liking, Majesty.
Your own law decrees it, I'm afraid.
Well, look at them.
No. This is nonsense.
Let me see the scene with the music.
But, sire.
Oblige me.
Yes, Majesty.
Can we see the scene with the music back, please?
Certainly. Certainly, Herr Direktor.
Bring the palace set back in, please.
The restored third act
was bold, brilliant.
The fourth...
was astounding.
I saw a woman,
disguised in her maid's clothes,
hear her husband speak the first
tender words he has offered her in years.
Simply because he thinks
she is someone else.
I heard the music of true forgiveness
filling the theater,
conferring on all who sat there,
perfect absolution.
God was singing through this little man,
to all the world.
Unstoppable.
Making my defeat more bitter
with every passing bar.
And then, do you know what happened?
A miracle.
With that yawn,
I saw my defeat turn into a victory.
And Mozart was lucky
the emperor yawned only once.
Three yawns...
and the opera would fail the same night.
Two yawns, within a week at most.
With one yawn,
the composer could still get...
Nine performances. Nine.
That's all it's had. And withdrawn.
I know, I know.
It's outrageous.
Still, if the public doesn't like one's work,
one has to accept the fact gracefully.
But what is it that they don't like?
I can speak for the emperor.
You make too many demands
on the royal ear.
The poor man can't concentrate
for more than an hour.
You gave him four.
What did you think of it yourself?
Did you like it at all?
I thought it was marvelous.
Of course.
It's the best opera yet written.
I know it.
Why didn't they come?
I think you overestimate
our dear Viennese, my friend.
Do you know you didn't even give them
a good bang at the end of songs,
to let them know when to clap.
I know, I know.
Maybe you should give me some lessons in that.
I wouldn't presume.
Nevertheless, at the risk of imposing...
I'd like you to see my new piece.
It would be a tremendous honor for me.
No, the honor would be all mine.
I believe...
I believe
it is the best opera yet written,
my friends.
Salieri.
You are the brightest star
in the musical firmament.
You do honor to Vienna and to me.
Herr Mozart.
- It was good of you to come.
- How could I not?
Bravo, maestro.
Did my work please you?
I never knew that music like that
was possible.
- You flatter me.
- No.
One hears such sounds...
and what can one say but:
Salieri.
Everybody's here and we've got guests.
Bravo.
Well, I've got some more.
Stanzi, you remember my excellent friend Schikaneder.
Come in.
Don't be shy.
- This is a very nice girl, and this...
- Wolfie?
Yes, my love?
These gentlemen are from Salzburg.
Salzburg?
We were just talking about Salzburg.
Your father is dead.
So rose the dreadful ghost,
from his next and blackest opera.
There on the stage,
stood the figure of a dead commander.
I knew.
Only I understood,
that the horrifying apparition
was Leopold,
raised from the dead.
Wolfgang had actually summoned up
his own father,
to accuse his son before all the world.
It was...
terrifying and wonderful to watch.
And now...
the madness began in me.
The madness of a man splitting in half.
Through my influence, I saw to it.
Don Giovanni was played
only five times in Vienna.
But, in secret,
I went to every one of those five.
Worshiping sound I alone seemed to hear.
And as I stood there,
understanding how
that bitter old man
was still possessing his poor son,
even from beyond the grave,
I began to see a way,
a terrible way,
I could finally triumph
over God.
Herr Mozart?
I have come to commission
work from you.
- What work?
- A Mass for the dead.
What dead?
Who is dead?
A man who deserved a Requiem Mass
and never got one.
- Who are you?
- I`am only a messenger.
Do you accept?
You will be well paid.
Work fast.
And be sure tell no one what you do.
You will see me again soon.
Wolfie?
My plan was so simple...
that it terrified me.
First, I must get the death Mass,
and then...
I must achieve his death.
What?
His funeral.
Imagine it.
The cathedral,
all Vienna sitting there.
His coffin.
Mozart's little coffin in the middle.
And then...
in that silence...
music.
A divine music,
bursts out over them all.
A great Mass of death.
Requiem Mass for Wolfgang Mozart.
Composed by his devoted friend,
Antonio Salieri.
What sublimity.
What depth.
What passion in the music.
Salieri has been touched by God at last,
and God forced to listen.
Powerless to stop it.
I, for once, in the end,
laughing at him.
The only thing that worried me
was the actual killing.
How does one do that?
How does one kill a man?
It's one thing
to dream about it.
Very different when you...
When you have to do it...
with your own hands.
Come in.
Don Giovanni,
I've come to dinner.
Dinner. Are you mad?
I'm a nobleman.
I only ever dine with people
of my own height.
Stop it.
Be careful. Be careful.
Hold tight.
I'm a famous
horseman.
And we're a famous horsy.
Give me a hoof, my darling.
And I'll give you my heart.
Take me to your stable.
And never more we'll part.
Kill me. Kill me.
We're going to make a soprano stew.
And when you make a soprano stew.
Shut up.
I'm sick to death of that tune.
Give me some hay, my darling.
And I'll give you my heart.
Leporello. Some hay.
We hope
you're contented.
With what
we've presented.
And love our dove of peace...
- What did you think of that?
- It was wonderful.
- He liked the little people. Didn`t you?
- It's all in good fun.
I liked the horse.
I tell you,
if you played Don Giovanni here,
you would've had a wonderful success.
You belong here.
Not at the snobby court.
You could do anything you like.
The more fantastic, the better.
That's what people want: Fantasy.
You write a proper part for me,
a couple of catchy songs.
I guarantee you a triumph deluxe.
- What do you say?
- How much will you pay him?
Well. I see you brought
your manager with you.
Well, madame,
how about half the receipts?
Half the receipts.
- Stanzi.
- I'm talking about now.
How much will you pay him now?
Down payment.
Down payment?
Who do you think I`am,
the emperor?
I have to go.
Stay here, you'll enjoy this next one.
You not going to do this.
- Why not? Half the house.
- When?
We need money now.
Either he pays you now, or you don't do it.
I don't trust that man.
And I don't like what he did with your opera.
It was common.
Wll, you liked it. Didn`you?
Monkey, punky, flunky.
Half the house.
You'll never see a penny.
I want it here in my hand.
- I'll put it here in your hand.
- Shut up.
You won't put a thing in my hand
until I see some money.
It's embarrassing.
Can't you think of anyone
who could do something for him?
I'm afraid Mozart is a lost cause, baron.
He has succeeded in alienating practically
the whole of Vienna.
He never pays his debts.
I can't think of anyone
to whom I'd dare recommend him.
Herr Mozart. What a surprise.
What can I do for you?
Is my pupil still interested
in learning the art of music?
Your pupil is married
and living in Mannheim, young man.
Really?
Perhaps your dear wife might care
to profit from my instruction.
What is it, Mozart?
What's the matter with you?
Well,
since it appears no one is eager
to hire my services...
could you favor me
with a little money instead?
What for?
If a man cannot earn,
he must borrow.
That's hardly the way to go about it.
You are right, sir. You are right.
But you see, I`am endowed with talent,
and you with money.
If I offer mine...
you should offer yours.
I'm sorry, no.
Please.
My answer is no, Mozart.
Please!
Don't answer it.
Why?
Tell him...
Tell him I'm not here.
Tell him I'm working on it.
Come back later.
Am I interrupting something?
No.
Good. Where's our friend?
He's not here.
But he's working on it,
he told me to tell you.
Is that it?
Is he happy with it?
What's this?
A Requiem Mass?
You think I'm in the funeral business?
Leave that alone.
- Put it down. It's nothing for you.
- I'm sorry.
What have you got for me?
Finished?
- What?
- The vaudeville, what do you think?
Yes.
- Can I see it?
- No.
Why not?
Because there's nothing to see.
Look...
I asked you if we could start rehearsals next week
and you said yes.
- Well, we can.
- So let me see it. Where is it?
Here.
It's all right here in my noodle.
The rest is just scribbling.
Scribbling and bibbling.
Bibbling and scribbling.
- Do you like a drink?
- Look, you little cunt!
Do you know how many people I've hired?
- Leave him alone!
- I'm paying this people! Do you realize that?
- He's doing his best.
- I`m paying this people to wait. For you it's ridiculous!
You know what's ridiculous?
Your libretto, that what's ridiculous!
Only an idiot would ask Wolfie
to work on that stuff!
Twelve-foot snakes, magic flutes?
What's so intelligent about writing a Requiem?
Money. Money.
You're mad.
She's mad Wolfie.
- Oh, yes?
- Wolfie, write it down.
Just write it down.
On paper.
It's no use to anybody in your head.
To hell with your death mass!
Calm yourself.
What's the matter with you?
- I won't work there anymore.
- Why, what has happened?
You don't know what it's like.
Herr Mozart frightens me.
He drinks all day,
then takes all that medicine
and it makes him worse.
Is he working?
Oh, I`am frightened, sir, really.
- When he speaks, he doesn`t make any sense.
- Is he working?
I suppose so.
He sits there all the time,
doing some silly opera.
- Opera?
- Please, don't ask me to go back again.
I'm frightened.
I'm very, very frightened!
Are you sure it's an opera?
I don't have it yet.
Are you neglecting my request?
No. No, I...
I promise you...
I'll give you a wonderful piece,
the best I ever...
This is my wife, Stanzi.
I've been sick,
but I'm all right now, aren't I?
Yes, sir. He's all right.
And he's working on it very hard.
Give me two more weeks. Please.
The sooner you finish,
the greater your reward.
Work.
Wolfie.
I think you really are going mad.
You work like a slave for that idiot actor
who won't give you a penny.
And here, this is not a ghost.
This is a real man,
who puts down real money.
Why on earth won't you finish it?
Can you give me one reason
I can understand?
It's killing me.
You're drunk, aren't you?
Be honest, tell me.
You've been drinking.
It's not fair.
I worry about you all the time.
I do everything I can to help you.
And all you do is drink
and talk nonsense, and frighten me.
Go back to bed.
Please.
Let me...
Let me sit here.
Let me stay here with you.
I did it.
And I was proud to do it.
"Leave." I said.
"Right away. Clear out and take the child with you.
Here is the money and go to the spa
and get your health back." I was shocked.
Shocked to my foundation when I saw her.
I couldn't believe my eyes,
poor little thing.
You monster.
No one exists but you, do they?
You and your music. I warned her.
"Choose a man, not a baby" I said.
"You marry him, you won't have a pot
to piss in."
You selfish thing.
Selfish, that's what you are.
Simply selfish.
Do you hear me?
Pick him up.
Be careful. Come with me.
You, follow me.
- Is it over?
- Yes, it's over. It's over.
Go.
Go, go. Go.
Go. Go.
Where is your wife?
She's not well either.
She went to the spa.
You are so good to me.
Truly. Thank you.
Please, please.
No, I mean to come to my opera.
You, you are the only colleague of mine
who came.
Mozart.
I would never miss anything
you had written.
- It's just a vaudeville.
- No, no.
It's a sublime piece.
The grandest operone.
I tell you...
you are the greatest composer
known to me.
Do you mean it?
- It's him.
- Who?
The man.
He's here.
Tell him to go away.
Tell him I'm still working on it.
Don't let him in.
No, no. Wait.
Ask him if he would give me...
some money now.
Tell him if he would,
it will help me to finish it.
- Salieri?
- Yes.
- Can we come in?
- Better not. He's sleeping.
- He's all right, though?
- Yes, he's just exhausted.
He became dizzy, that's all.
Well, tell him we came by,
won't you?
Of course.
Give him this. That's his share.
- That should cheer him up.
- Indeed.
And now, good night to you all.
It was...
perfection, truly.
Thank you.
What happened?
He said to give you this.
And if you finish by tomorrow night,
he will pay you another hundred ducats.
Another...?
That's too soon. Tomorrow night...
It's impossible.
- Did he say a hundred?
- Yes.
It's too soon.
Can I...?
Could I help you?
Would you?
Actually you could.
- I wanna go.
- Where?
- I wanna go back to Vienna.
- Now?
- Yes.
- Why?
I feel wrong.
I feel wrong being here.
- Where did I stop?
- The end of the Recordare.
So now Confutatis...
How would you translate that?
"Consigned to flames of woe".
- Do you believe in it?
- What?
A fire which never dies,
burning you forever.
Oh, yes.
Possible.
- Come, let's begin.
- We ended in F major.
- Yes.
- So, now, A minor.
- A minor.
- Yes.
Confutatis. A minor.
Start with the voices.
- Basses first. Second beat of the...
- Time?
Common time.
Second beat of the first measure.
On A.
Second measure, second beat.
You see?
- Yes. G-sharp?
- Of course.
Second beat of the third measure,
on E.
Do you have me?
Show me.
Good. Good.
Now the tenors.
Fourth beat of the first measure,
on C.
Second measure, fourth beat. D.
- All right?
- Yes, continue.
Second beat of the fourth measure,
on F.
Now the orchestra.
Second bassoon and bass trombones, with the basses.
Identical notes and rhythm.
First bassoon, tenor trombones,
with the tenors.
- You go too fast.
- Do you have it?
- First bassoon to the trombone what?
- With the tenors.
- Identical?
- Of course, the instruments doubling the voices.
Now, trumpets and timpani. Trumpets in D.
Listen to me.
- I don't understand.
- Listen.
Trumpets in D, tonic and dominant.
First and third beats.
It goes with the harmony.
Yes. Yes, yes.
I understand. And that's all?
No, now for the real fire.
Strings in unison.
Ostinato, on A. Like this:
Next measure is rising.
Do you have it? Show me.
- It's wonderful.
- Yes, yes. Go on.
- Write that down.
- Yes, yes.
"Call me among the blessed".
C major.
Sopranos and altos in thirds.
Altos on C, sopranos above.
Sopranos up to F on the second voca?
And on dictus.
And underneath, just violins. Arpeggios.
Descending scale in eighth notes,
then back to ostinato again.
- And that`s it. Do you have it?
- You go too fast.
- Do you have it?
- You go too fast. One moment, please, one moment!
Good. Show me the whole thing
from the beginning.
Do you want to rest a bit?
No, I'm not tired at all.
We'll stop for a moment.
- Then we'll finish the Lacrimosa.
- I can keep going. I assure you.
Will you stay with me
while I sleep a little?
I'm not leaving you.
I'm so ashamed.
Of what?
I was foolish.
I thought you did not care for my work,
or me.
Forgive me.
What are you doing here?
Your husband took sick.
I brought him home.
Why you?
Because, madame, I was at hand.
Well, thank you very much.
You can go now.
He needs me, ma'am.
No, he doesn't.
And I don't want you here.
Just go, please.
- He asked me to stay.
- And I'm ask...
I'm back.
I missed you so much.
If you'd just...
show me that you need me.
And I'll try to do better too.
What is this?
No, Wolfie, not this. Not this.
You're not to work on this ever again.
I've decided.
This is not his handwriting.
It's mine.
I was assisting him.
He's not to work on this anymore.
- It's making him ill.
- But...
Good night.
I regret we have no servants
to show you out, Herr Salieri.
Please respect my wish and go.
Madame...
I will respect his.
Your merciful God.
He destroyed his own beloved,
rather than let a mediocrity
share in the smallest part
of his glory.
He killed Mozart.
And kept me alive to torture.
Thirty-two years of torture.
Thirty-two years of slowly
watching myself become extinct.
My music...
growing fainter.
All the time fainter,
till no one plays it at all.
And his...
Good morning, professor.
Time for the water closet.
Then we have your favorite breakfast.
Sugar rolls. He loves those.
Fresh sugar rolls.
I will speak for you, Father.
I speak for all mediocrities
in the world.
I`am their champion.
I`am their patron saint.
Mediocrities everywhere.
I absolve you.
I absolve you all.
Subtitles by SDI Media Group and Theus