RICHARD MILES: The Roman Empire
was the most successful
the world had ever known.
At its peak, in the second century AD,
it covered 5 million square kilometres.
From Hadrian's Wall in the north
to ancient Mesopotamia in the east.
All of it run by a system of remarkable
efficiency and stability.
They called it Pax Romana,
the Roman eace.
And its benefits were enjoyed
by 60 million people.
(BLEATING)
The Romans would proudly boast
of having come up
with the final word on civilisation.
Peace, security and prosperity,
all underwritten by an imperial power
with a civilising mission.
As long as you got with the programme,
paid your taxes,
committed to the Empire
and, of course, kept the peace,
the benefits of civilisation
would come to you.
What more could anyone want?
The answer was more than
the Pax Romana could supply.
This mighty empire would endure
some mad, bad and dangerous emperors,
but in the end it would be subverted
by an obscure religious cult
from the East.
(CONGREGATION SINGING)
Its followers would reject,
not just Rome
but all that Rome had come to mean
in the story of civilisation.
The city of man would be eclipsed
by the city of God.
Here's a rare thing in our story
of the ancient world,
a massive, expensive public monument,
dedicated not to some blood-soaked
triumph over a cringing enemy
but to that elusive, precious thing
called peace.
Surely the greatest good
that human civilisation can aspire to.
It was created at the behest of the man
who established the Pax Romana.
Augustus, Rome's first Emperor.
This is the Ara acis,
the Altar of Peace,
built by Augustus in 1 3 BC.
On this frieze here,
it shows Augustus coming back
from campaign.
The gaurantor and author of peace.
Quite a transformation
from the teenage warlord
who repeatedly ripped out the eyes
of one of his enemies.
Eighteen years earlier, plain old
Octavian Caesar, as he was then,
was the last man standing
in the brutal civil wars
that had torn
the Roman Republic apart.
As victor, he'd faced a simple choice,
resuscitate the Republic
ruled by the Senate and the people
or put it out of its misery.
But the canny Octavian,
rebranded ''Augustus'; found a third way.
He killed the Republic's soul
but kept its body alive.
On the frieze, we see Augustus
with three main constituencies.
The first of these is the Senate,
because Augustus was going to claim
that he was going to restore
the Roman Republic.
And to do that he needed to restore
the dignity and authority of the Senate.
The second group are the priesthood,
because Augustus was going to claim
that he is going to restore
traditional Roman religion.
But the third group is a real novelty.
We can see them up here.
Women and children.
These are members
of Augustus's immediate family.
It was Augustus who wanted to get
the people of Rome
used to a new concept.
An imperial dynasty.
As Augustus knew,
Romans had a visceral hatred of kings.
To plant his dynasty firmly
in this hostile soil,
Augustus had to master
a tricky political manoeuvre.
A Roman writer would later define
it as 'getting higher by stepping down''.
You can see what that meant in practice
in another public monument,
erected 30 years
after the Altar of eace.
The Res Gestae, literally
''The Things Done'; by Augustus,
is the carefully doctored Cv
of the man who brought the principles of
monarchy back to Rome after 500 years.
As a public testament,
the Res Gestae,
is a very odd document indeed.
Most Roman aristocrats on their epitaphs
will be boasting about their honours
and offices that they are decrewed.
But the Res Gestae
does the diametric opposite.
On it, Augustus boasts about the offices
that he has turned down.
So up here, we've got...
''The dictatorship,
which was offered to me
''in my absence and presence
by the people and Senate of Rome,
''I didn't take it.
''The consulship,
offered to me annually and eternally,
''I didn't take it.
''The coronation crown
that was offered to me,
''I didn't accept it.''
One title that
the self-denying Augustus did accept
was Pater Patriae,
Father of the Country.
And he garnished it with a
disingenuous little phrase
that added more smoke and mirrors
to this monarchy in disguise.
rimus inter pares,
or first amongst equals,
would remain the modus operandi
for all emperors after Augustus.
Augustus would maintain the charade
of visiting the Senate House
and seeking advice from its leaders.
And even half the provinces
would remain in senatorial control,
but they tended to be the ones
that didn't have large standing armies,
just in case.
The dead hand
of the Father of the Country
weighed heavily here in the Senate.
Woe betide the Senator who
failed to do Augustus's bidding.
And so the habits of debate and dissent
shrivelled and died.
(BELL TOLLING)
Augustus lived long enough to see
his imperial system take firm root.
But its resilience was tested
by what came next,
a succession of rulers
that gives the term ''Roman Emperor''
its lurid associations with vanity,
debauchery
and insanity.
This hall is literally full of emperors
and as you can see,
they come in various shapes and sizes.
One of the interesting things
about the Empire
is it often didn't seem to matter
what the man at the top was like.
He could be mad, bad and dangerous.
But the Empire
just carried on regardless.
The machinery of Empire,
trade, tax collecting and public works,
rarely missed a beat,
but the imperial system
distorted the values and ideals of Rome.
For Rome's elite, life under an emperor
was a form of exquisite torture.
The closer you got
to the centre of power,
the greater your chances
of an untimely death.
Such unspoken inequalities
often created embarrassing
and even dangerous situations.
The Emperor Claudius,
who often got things wrong,
used to turn up at senators' houses
for dinner, uninvited,
leaving his hosts to sit there quaking
in their boots over dinner
as his bodyguards served up the food.
And one obsequious senator
threw himself at the feet
of the aged Emperor Tiberius,
knocking him over.
And he almost ended up
with a guardsman's sword in his guts.
Many senators embraced Stoicism.
The cultivation of indifference
in the face of life's trials
and tribulations,
as a psychological defence mechanism
against these arbitrary
and dangerous times.
Many of them decided to exercise
the ultimate freedom
that they still had left under a tyrant.
And that was choosing the manner
and the time of their own deaths.
So there was a whole series
of senatorial suicides.
Including men inviting
all their friends to dinner,
where they read poetry, ate something,
and then they went off to the baths
where the guy who was going
to commit suicide slashed his wrists.
But then in another twist,
one of these guys
had his hands bandaged up again,
and he went out again,
spent some more time
discussing things with his friends
before going back in
and having the bandages removed
where he bled to death.
While Rome's imperial system drove its
elite to suicide,
the masses were encouraged
to behave like spoilt brats.
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
The million-strong population of Rome
was always one grievance away
from becoming a million-strong mob.
And so smart emperors kept it sweet
with panem et circenses,
bread and circuses.
The bread came first.
Augustus handed out a free monthly dole
of grain to 200,000 Romans,
one-fifth of the city's population.
He could afford to be generous
because Rome had acquired
the ancient world's great bread basket,
North Africa.
The abundant fruits of empire
helped fill the bellies of the Romans
and kept them quiet.
There was a trading boom
in the Mediterranean
unprecedented in the ancient world
as ships headed to Rome,
laden with grain, building materials
and amphora full of olive oil.
So much for the bread,
but the plebs
also demanded stronger meat.
(CROWD ExCLAIMING)
The circuses.
The Roman games had
gladiators, chariots and wild beasts.
These Las vegas-scale spectaculars
were paid for by the emperor
or his representatives.
(CROWD CHEERING)
And death
was always top of the bill.
In this murky, subterranean world,
animals and men would wait
before they were taken up
to the arena above,
to die for the entertainment
of the crowds there.
The Roman Empire,
built on bread and circuses,
cheap food and cheap thrills.
(PEOPLE APPLAUDING)
The grim theatre of death
that played out on the sandy floor
of the amphitheatre
was accompanied by cut and thrust
of a more subtle kind.
The political interaction
that took place between the crowd
and their emperor.
There were ways of doing it,
and ways of not doing it.
So, Tiberius got it completely wrong
and came across as being very aloof
because he didn't turn up at all.
Then, there were others like Claudius,
who just enjoyed it a bit too much.
He used to like
looking at the expressions
on the faces of the dying gladiators.
Others, also didn't
get involved enough, so Demition
liked to sit in his box
but he spent most of his time chatting
to a dwarf in a red cloak.
And then there was Nero,
who went too far
and actually became
the star of the show himself
and performed as a musician.
So for emperors,
the games were a time
when you had to get the balance right
between participation
and maintaining your dignity.
But keeping the Romans in Rome,
happy and docile,
(INAUDIBLE)
was only one part of the challenge
of running the empire.
What about the 59 million other citizens
and subjects of Rome
scattered over its vast territories?
To keep them in their place
as compliant, tax-paying units,
emperors depended upon the loyalty
and commitment of local elites.
It was they, in thousands of towns,
large and small,
who really ran the Roman Empire.
Extracting revenues,
building public works
and keeping order by imitating
the bread and circuses programme
developed in the capital.
The system was remarkably efficient
and streamlined.
The whole of the Empire was administered
by just 1 0,000 of these bureaucrats.
Modern Britain has half a million.
To cultivate and maintain their loyalty,
they were granted full citizen rights
and generous tax concessions.
And perhaps most importantly
there was the Imperial cult
which turned emperors
and their families into gods.
Here the Emperor Antoninus ius
is being elevated to the heavens
on the wings of an eagle.
In Ephesus in Turkey,
the divine Hadrian had his own temple.
And members of Augustus's dynasty
were worshipped here in Nimes in France.
This bronze statue behind me
is of the Emperor Claudius,
and it comes
from the temple of Augustus,
Herculaneum in Southern Italy.
But the Imperial cult
wasn't just about religion,
it was also about political control.
The problem that an emperor had
was how to connect
with his millions of subjects
over a huge empire,
people who he was never
going to meet personally.
The Imperial cult acted
as a kind of hologram,
beaming the emperor
right across his vast empire
and allowing him to create some kind of
personal connection with his subjects.
But when it came to religion,
the Romans were not fundamentalists.
Here at the Temple of Luxor in Egypt,
it was perfectly acceptable to worship
the ancient Egyptian gods
alongside the deified emperors
of the Imperial cult.
And elsewhere in the Empire,
there was plenty of other evidence
for Rome's religious tolerance.
We're here in the Bekaa valley
in Lebanon,
what was once Heliopolis,
the City of the Sun.
A little bit of Rome from Rome.
Before it was called Heliopolis,
this was known
as the Phoenician City of Baalbek.
Dedicated to the god, Baal.
Alexander Greekified the name.
But the Romans, when they took control,
preferred to keep things as they were.
Imperial Rome was just not interested
in name changes,
preferring instead to add new labels
rather than erasing the old.
In spiritual matters,
the Empire was a sponge,
absorbing foreign gods as readily
as it had gobbled up foreign territory.
This was the Temple of Jupiter.
But the Jupiter worshipped here
was also understood to be Baal-Hadad.
A local storm deity
who had been honoured here for centuries
before the first togas arrived.
The Temple of venus over there
was also the Temple of Astarte,
the Phoenician goddess of love.
And at the Temple of Bacchus,
the wine god,
it was also possible
to pray to Dionysus,
an ancient eastern fertility deity.
The Romans were big tent polytheists.
All were welcome
to local and traditional gods.
Just as long as they were willing
to offer up
a pinch of incense to the Imperial cult.
Rome tolerated everything,
except for rebellion, political disorder
and the non-payment of taxes.
For a region like this, which had known
the scourge of war in the past,
that must have sounded
like a pretty good deal.
But the ironic truth
about the Roman Empire was this.
The further you were from
the toxic centre that Rome was becoming,
the more the stability and security
created by the Pax Romana
could be enjoyed and exploited.
In the second century AD,
where I'm standing now
would have been on the very edge
of the Roman Empire.
This way lies Rome, 1 500 miles,
as the Imperial Eagle flies.
And this way lies Mesopotamia, ersia,
India, China,
and the very edges of the known world.
When we talk
about the edge of empire,
we tend to think
of Hadrian's famous wall,
clambering over the rain-soaked hills
of Cumbria and Northumberland,
manned by homesick squaddies
grumbling about their chilblains.
Well, here,
there was no wall or chilblains.
This was Palmyra,
the queen of the desert,
and it tells a very different story
of what life could be like
under the ax Romana.
Rome had acquired this desert territory
during the last decades of the Republic.
And almyra was first garrisoned
during the reign of Augustus.
Even then it was a vital link
in the east-west trade route,
providing an essential stopover point
between the upper waters
of the Euphrates
and the Mediterranean coast.
For the almyrans,
the arrival of the Romans simply meant
that a whole new market opportunity
had opened up.
From the workshops and factories
of Rome, supplies of manufactured goods.
From India and the east,
spices and silk.
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Of course,
we've met these people before.
The bronze-age merchants
travelling with their mule trains
from Ashur to Anatolia.
The iron-age Phoenicians
crisscrossing the Mediterranean
in their sturdy ships.
Well, they're here too, in Palmyra,
the essential middlemen,
stitching together to the political map
of the ancient world
with the thread of trade.
And as the Assyrians had their mules,
and the Phoenicians had their ships,
so the Palmyrans had
their favourite mode of transport.
The camel.
(BELLOWING)
By mastering the art of crossing
the desert with their camel trains,
the almyrans were able
to join together
what nature had put asunder.
But like all traders,
what the almyrans needed most
was peace and stability.
Reliable supplies of stock
and stable markets
so that they could pursue their ultimate
objective of getting rich, quick.
This wasn't always easy.
To the immediate east of them,
lay the kingdom of arthia,
a thorn in the side of Rome
for centuries.
Like others before him,
the Emperor Trajan decided to solve
Rome's eastern problems
once and for all.
He led his legions into arthia
and then beyond,
to the ancient cities of Mesopotamia
following the footsteps
of Alexander the Great.
Whereas Alexander's victories had
fuelled an appetite for further glory,
Trajan came to a rather
different conclusion.
This country is so measurably vast
and separated from Rome
by such incalculable distance
we cannot possibly administer it.
He then turned around
and went back west.
That was AD 1 1 7.
And if you wanted to date
the high watermark of the Roman Empire,
then Trajan's, rather world-weary
conclusion, would arguably be it.
Under Trajan's successor, Hadrian,
Rome reverted to a policy of peace
with its eastern neighbours.
After 500 years of expansion,
Rome finally decided enough was enough.
Fuzzy borders became lines
in the sand,
and almyra, on the critical interface
between the Roman
and the non-Roman world
became a free city.
And that was when the good times
really began to roll.
Sometime in the 2nd Century AD,
over around a 1 50 years afterwards,
the Palmyrans achieved
the perfect formula
in their relationship with Rome.
First of all, they were important
because they provided Rome
with something it wanted.
Silks and spices.
And second, there was no
conflict of interest there
because the Palmyrans
were only interested in profits,
whereas Rome, like all empires,
was obsessed with its own destiny.
Finally, and best of all,
the alymyrans were far enough away
from Rome
to be left alone to get on with it.
And today we can see the virtues
of being left alone,
in the elaborate mausoleums
put up by some of the leading families
of almyra,
both above ground and underground.
Memorials to their wealth and status,
but also the benefits of being
in the Empire
rather than of the Empire.
But it wasn't just merchant princes
who enjoyed the benefits of Empire.
The ancient Greeks always used to say
that the basis
for any successful society was Eunomia,
good order,
and that's what you can sense in a set
of remarkable archaeological finds
from some of Rome's Egyptian cities.
The banal blessings
of good order writ large.
As any private eye worth his salt
will tell you
what people throw away
is often more revealing
than what they keep and cherish.
And it was certainly the case here,
in the Roman City of Antonopoulos
are amongst the tonnes of broken
pottery, archaeologist struck gold.
Papyri, thousands and thousands of them.
So many that it's going to
take generations of scholars
to decipher and publish them all.
This wealth of written material
allows us to reconstruct
in minute detail
what life was like here
in the heyday of the Empire.
Most of it is the ancient equivalent
of those mountains of paper
that clog up our lives today.
Bills, tax returns, personal letters,
invitations, certificates,
contracts, to-do lists.
The kind of stuff that's either
too important to throw away
or too trivial to be bothered with.
In the nearby city of Oxyrhynchus
comes more of the same.
This one addresses the serious problem
of donkeys being driven too quickly
through the busy streets of the city.
And this little note was written
by two friends,
Apium and Epimus, to a school mate
of theirs, Ephroditos.
And it contains
the most extraordinary suggestion.
''If you let us bugger you,
if it's okay with you,
''we shall stop thrashing you.''
And there's even
a helpful little illustration here.
So Aphrodidius knew exactly
what was expected of him.
And then there's this.
This is a letter by Diogenes,
to one of his employees.
''A thousand times I've written to you
to cut down the vines of pohaya.
''But today again I get a letter from you
asking what should be done.
''To which I reply -
''Cut them down. Cut them down.
Cut them down. Cut them down
''and cut them down.
There I say it again and again.''
Go on, Diogenes,
why don't you say exactly what you mean?
But there's a twist to this tale
of hotrod donkey riders
smutty teenagers
and slow-witted servants.
And it suggests that the people
of Antonopoulos and Oxyrhynchus
had other things on their minds.
And you could say
that these concerns
presaged the decline and fall
of the Roman Empire.
Amongst the charming trivia,
archaeologist also found
this rather different text.
''The Kingdom is inside of you,
and it is outside of you.
''When you come to know yourselves,
when you'll become known
''and you will realise that it is you
who are the sons of the living father.
''But if you will not know yourselves,
you dwell in poverty,
''and it is you who are that poverty.''
These words are from the Apocryphal
Gospel of St Thomas,
from which three extracts
have been found
amongst the bills and the junk mail
and what it shows is
that alongside the everyday concerns
about vines and donkeys,
that there were people here
grappling with profound
and unsettling questions
about the meaning of life
and the fate of their immortal souls.
Questions which the Roman Empire,
despite its material wealth
was simply unable to answer.
In many ways,
the Roman Empire represents
the zenith of ancient civilisation.
Its values had taken root
throughout its far flung territories.
But its inability to address
the spiritual anxieties of its subjects
would prove to be a fatal flaw.
This weakness would be exposed
and exploited by an obscure Jewish sect
that begun in the Roman province
of Judaea
with the execution
of an unorthodox religious leader
called Yeshua Ben Yosef.
(BELL TOLLING)
Christianity would go on to become
the official religion of Rome.
And the major contributor
to its downfall.
The cult's extraordinary growth
began after the Jewish revolt of 66 AD,
and the destruction
of the High Temple in Jerusalem
by Titus, the son of the Roman Emperor,
vespasian.
This triumphal arch was built
to commemorate
Titus' suppression of the Jews.
And inside it, there are two friezes.
On one side, we have the Emperor,
flanked by the winged goddess
of victory in his chariot
and surrounded by his troops.
And on the other,
we have the spoils of victory.
The most sacred objects
from the temple on the mount.
The Menorah
and the silver trumpets amongst them.
So, this arch was as much about issuing
a severe warning
of the dangers
of resisting the ax Romana
as it was about tasting
the sweetness of victory.
But what the Romans actually did
was sow the seeds
for their later problems.
After the failed revolt,
/ews dispersed
throughout the Mediterranean world
carrying with them
the beliefs of Christianity.
These beliefs would put Christians
on a collision course with Rome.
They were fiercely monotheistic
and baulked at the Imperial cult.
They made a sharp distinction
between the sacred and the secular.
And they looked forward
to a glorious life after death,
making a mockery
of the Empire's worldly devotion
to the here and now.
Christianity initially took root away
from the Imperial centre
in places like Carthage in North Africa.
For the authorities here,
to be a Christian
was to be a revolutionary
and a target for persecution.
A new word will enter
the religious lexicon.
Martyr.
The problem for the Romans
was that for the Christians
martyrdom was a privilege,
not a punishment.
After all it offered a guaranteed pass
into the kingdom of heaven.
In Carthage in 203 AD,
the amphitheatre here
was the site
of a notorious killing of Christians.
Worryingly for the authorities,
one of the female victims,
erpetua, came from one of the cities'
elite families.
erpetua had been arrested
with a group of other Christians
including her pregnant servant,
Felicitas.
Both women refused to renounce
their faith,
and both were sentenced to die
in the amphitheatre.
Even though just two days
before the execution,
Felicitas gave birth to a baby daughter.
Felicitas and Perpetua were brought up
naked into the arena
and the crowd immediately
started shouting
for them to be sent down below again.
Not because they wanted
to show them mercy
because they felt squeamish
about Felicitas' lactating breasts
which were dripping milk
all over the arena floor.
When they were sent up again,
they were fully clothed.
They were whipped
and then a wild cow was sent
into the arena to trample them.
But even after that,
they were still alive
and swordsmen were sent into the arena
to finish them off.
The swordsman that was sent
in to kill Perpetua,
his hands were shaking so much
that she had to hold them
so he could cut her throat.
erpetua had got what she wanted,
a martyr's death,
and this bloody ritual
would be repeated sporadically
in amphitheatres
across the Roman Empire,
over the next century.
But persecution was never
a coherent policy.
And when the Roman authorities
abandoned it,
frustrated martyrs
had to find other ways
to express their rejection
of the Roman world.
If it couldn't be achieved quickly
through the executioner's blade,
salvation would have
to be earned the hard way
through extreme asceticism.
This is the world's oldest
Christian monastery
St Anthony's in Egypt.
Anthony was born
into a wealthy Egyptian family
around 250 AD.
At the age of 34,
he decided to renounce
his material possessions
and dedicate his life to God.
So, he headed into the desert
to live the life of a hermit in a cave.
-MILES: Father Damien.
-Yeah.
How many steps are there
up to the cave of St Anthony?
I think maybe one thousand
and three hundred.
You know that it's like
the way to the heaven.
It's a very narrow way
and very tough way
but when you reach there
you'll get the prize.
(BELL TOLLING)
So now we arrived.
Here is our treasure, actually.
This is the real monastery, I believe.
This is the cave of St Anthony
where he used to live here.
And I believe that his blessing
is still present inside the cave.
-Just go and have... And enjoy the time.
-Thank you very much, Father Damien.
Okay.
Christianity was particularly attractive
to those who wanted to opt out
from the comfortable certainties
of the imperial system.
They wanted spiritual
rather than material enrichment.
For these young men and women,
asceticism offered an escape
from the straitjacket of public service,
private enterprise
and family commitments,
whilst at the same time
offering a blueprint for a new life.
One of poverty, abstinence,
charity and penance.
(CHURCH BELL TOLLING)
(PRIEST SINGING)
For them all the achievements
of the Pax Romana,
the laws, the aqueducts,
the peace and the prosperity,
were essentially meaningless.
But it's hard to see how a small,
isolated group of gentle ascetics
with their eyes fervently focussed
on the promise of a world to come
could be a problem
to the mighty Roman Empire.
(ALL CHANTING)
Well, for a start, erpetua in Carthage,
Anthony in Egypt
and the thousands
who followed their example
were precisely
the kind of wealthy, educated people
who would have been expected
to take up active roles
in the running and the administration
of the Empire.
By dropping out
they sapped the energies of a system
that ultimately depended
on the active commitment of its elites
to keep the machinery of empire
ticking over.
But it would take
something far more radical
to turn this revolutionary movement
into a force to be reckoned with.
The spiritual restlessness
that drove some to martyrdom
and others to the desert
went to the very top
of the imperial system.
This is Constantine.
The man who would turn a agan Empire
into a Christian one.
He was a man of action
rather than a man of faith.
But even he seems to have been
looking for answers
that his civilisation couldn't supply.
Constantine was actually
quite promiscuous
when it came to one-to-one relationships
with individual gods.
By the time he got to Christianity,
he'd already been through Apollo
and the sun god Sol Invictus.
But his relationship with Christianity
would endure.
It was possibly because of
Christianity's monotheistic tendencies
fitted very well with the man
who had ultimately been responsible
for the collapse of the Tetrarchy.
One emperor, one god.
The Tetrarchy had involved
the carving up of the Empire
between four different emperors.
It had been created
by the Emperor Diocletian
at the end of the 3rd century AD
because the Empire had become too large
and unwieldy
for one man to rule.
But after Diocletian's death
the rival emperors,
inevitably, went to war.
This climaxed in 3 1 2 AD
at the battle of the Milvian Bridge
on the outskirts of Rome
where Constantine defeated
his rival Maxentius,
who drowned in the Tiber.
Christians travelling
with Constantine's army
were quick to attribute the victory,
commemorated on this arch,
to the divine favour of their God.
Constantine, always ready to give a god
the benefit of the doubt,
showed his gratitude a year later,
by passing an edict of toleration
granting Christians freedom of worship
throughout the Empire.
A decade later, when Constantine emerged
as sole emperor,
the obscure Messianic cult from Judaea
really came in from the cold.
Constantine demonstrated his commitment
to Christianity
with hard cash.
He endowed a series
of magnificent churches,
including Saint eter's Basilica
in Rome,
and the Church of the Holy Sepulchre,
/erusalem.
Which was built on the supposed site
of the Son of God's tomb
on the orders
of Constantine's pious mother, Helena.
These would become new centres
of political as well as spiritual power
in Constantine's empire.
In return for political support
and generous patronage,
Constantine expected one thing
above all from his church..
A consistent message
on Christianity's core beliefs.
The Council of Nicaea held in 325 AD
in present day Turkey
was the first and most famous attempt
of the Christian establishment
to get its story straight.
As you can see,
there's not much left of the place
where the first Council of Nicaea
was held.
However, although the bricks and mortar
are long gone,
the legacy of the meeting of bishops
that took place here
in 325 AD has endured.
Because it was here that the Rome
of Romulus and the Republic
and Augustus Caesar and the Empire
began to make way for a new Rome.
A Rome of priests, popes
and the Holy Catholic
and Apostolic Church.
Constantine presented the Council
with what seemed
like a reasonable request.
A firm date for Easter
and agreement on the precise nature
of the relationship
that stood at the heart
of Christian faith.
That between the Father, the Son
and the Holy Ghost.
Easier asked than answered.
These seats were used
for a much later Council of Nicaea
which was held here
in the Church of Hagia Sophia
centuries after the first one.
But I don't suppose the seating
technology had changed very much.
And the point of this
is that these seats are incredibly
cramped and uncomfortable.
And every time you sat down
they must have served as an invitation
to come up with a quick compromise.
And that's exactly
what Constantine wanted.
A quick, political fix
to what he said were nothing more
than small and trifling matters.
But what he didn't appreciate was that
this was a new type of politics,
the politics of faith.
And in this new political landscape
nothing was small or trifling.
The bishops ended up compromising
on a form of words
familiar to all Christians today.
''We believe in one God,
the Father Almighty,
''and in one Lord Jesus Christ,
Son of God,
''and begotten of the Father
and in the Holy Ghost. ''
(HORN BLOWING)
Constantine was not finished yet.
He made a decision that
effectively brought to an end
five hundred years of Roman history.
On the 1 1 th of May, 330,
Rome was finally eclipsed
as the capital of the Roman Empire.
Of course
there had been contenders before
but this time it was for real.
Five hundred miles east of Rome
on the straits of the Bosphorus,
Constantine founded
the city of Constantinople.
And he planned it to be
nothing less than the new Rome.
Constantine based himself
in Constantinople,
present day Istanbul,
until he died in 337 AD
when he was finally baptised
on his deathbed.
(BELL TOLLING)
With just one exception,
Constantine's successors
would follow his example
and be Christians.
Their support made the Church
a real power in the land
and towards the end
of the 4th century AD
began to assert its independence
from its imperial patrons.
The main driving force
on the Christians' side
was Ambrose, Bishop of Milan.
A clever and energetic man
who was clearly unfazed
with dealing with emperors.
Before he joined the Church,
Ambrose had had a successful career
as a senator and governor.
Now, Ambrose was firmly of the belief
that it was the Christian church,
not the Roman Emperor who was
God's main representative on Earth.
And this position was bound to set him
on a collision course
with emperors who were used
by this time
in intervening in religious affairs
whenever they felt like it.
So, the scene was now set
for a dramatic and very public showdown
here, in Imperial Milan.
It pitted Ambrose
against the Emperor Theodosius,
a battle hardened campaigner
but also a pious Christian.
The spark was the massacre
of 7,000 rebellious subjects
under the orders of Theodosius,
in Thessaloniki in Greece.
Many of the victims were Christians
and Ambrose felt compelled to respond.
He banned Theodosius
from the congregation in his cathedral
and threatened him with excommunication
if he didn't repent.
Theodosius took the hint,
and for the next couple of months
the citizens of Milan
were treated to the extraordinary
spectacle of their emperor,
the most powerful and feared man
in the Roman world.
Doing the acts of public penance,
stripped of his imperial insignia.
But when eventually,
the chastened emperor
was readmitted back
into the Catholic fold,
Ambrose insisted that he stood
with the congregation,
rather than joining the priests
in the sacred sanctuary.
Ambrose had emphatically and literally
put Theodosius in his place.
Ambrose's spectacular humiliation
of the Emperor
impressed the ambitious men
about where real power now lay.
One of these men was a brilliant scholar
called Augustine.
Baptized here in Milan
by Ambrose himself.
Augustine had been born into a fairly
prosperous family in North Africa.
And after a good education in Carthage,
had landed a professorship
here in Milan.
But after being baptized,
he decided to return home
and devote himself to God.
This was a decision
that would not only change his life
but also the whole course of
Western Christianity.
Augustine returned to Africa,
intending to follow the example of
St Anthony,
leading a simple monastic life.
But his plans were changed for him
when he visited Hippo Regius,
a port city on the North African coast.
When he worshipped
at the church here,
he soon got noticed.
With his classical education
and oratorical skills,
the congregation urged him to stay on,
which he did,
and eventually
he would become their bishop.
Augustine was soon playing
an active part
in the religious battles that raged,
using pulpit and pen
to attack pagans and heretics alike.
He'd been bishop for 1 5 years
when history gave him a controversy
that he could really get his teeth into.
In the late summer of 41 0,
shocking news reached Hippo Regius.
Rome, the founding capital,
the greatest empire
that history had ever known
had fallen to Aleric
and his visigothic army.
Three days of looting followed.
And many of Rome's finest buildings
were destroyed.
The mausoleum at the Great Augustus
was ransacked.
Burial urns were overturned.
And the ashes of Roman Emperors
were scattered on the streets.
Rome may have been stripped
of its pre-eminence by Constantine,
but it still retained
a symbolic importance,
and its fall to German barbarians
sent reverberations
throughout the Empire.
In the weeks and months that followed,
Hippo filled with traumatised refugees
from Rome.
They wanted to know why the Mother City
had fallen.
Augustine took up his pen
and gave them an answer.
It was a blistering attack
on the myth and mystique of Rome.
Writing a Christian counter history
of the city,
a no-holds-barred, decline and fall,
from the city's virtuous founders
to the decadent, selfish,
materialistic citizens of his own day.
''If Rome fell,'' Augustine argued,
''it was because it deserved to.''
In his coup de grace, Augustine
attacked the very ideals that Rome,
and indeed all the great civilisations
of the Ancient World aspired to.
These earthly cities
were doomed to fail
because they were the work
of corrupt mankind.
It took Augustine 1 3 years
to finish his masterpiece,
The City of God.
And for me,
there are a few bleaker assessments
of the futility
of civilisation building.
For Augustine, no purpose or meaning
could be found in the Earthly City.
Only the City of God offered these.
And that could only be reached
beyond the grave.
Until that glorious release,
the righteous man
should act like a pilgrim
in the fallen world of mankind.
Taking advantage of
the peace and security
that civilisation offered,
but without ever mistaking it
for anything substantial or enduring.
The good man was just passing through
in the great technological, political,
and cultural achievements
of civilisation
were mere stepping stones
to the eternal glory of the City of God.
(MUEZZIN CALLING)
It's been 1 500 years now,
since the City of God
took on the City of Man.
And in that time,
other prophets from other religions
have added their voices of criticism.
Despite its manifold
and serial failures,
the City of Man has endured.
Elaborate schemes for political reform,
social justice or national greatness
have been tried and tested,
often to destruction.
And in the darkest days,
many of which have fallen
in our own times,
the very idea of civilisation
has been called into question.
But despite all the calamities,
crises, and dead-ends,
we have returned again and again
to the possibilities offered
by the City of Man.
Hoping to get it right next time.
There's no going back to
the comfortable securities
of family, kin, and tribe.
Civilisation has transformed us
into a species
which for better or worse
chooses to live with strangers.
And we need to keep on trying
to find ways
of making that unlikely choice work.
Personally, I'm optimistic.
Homo sapiens, they say, has been
around for at least 1 60,000 years.
The City, for less than 6000.
So it's early days yet,
we must keep the faith
and try and make it work.