-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-
Downfall
I feel as if I should be angry
with that child, that...
naive young girl.
Or that I must not forgive her...
for not recognizing the
nature of that monster.
For not being aware of what
she was getting into.
And especially that I went
along without thinking.
Because I wasn't a fanatical Nazi.
I could have said, in Berlin:
"No, I'm not doing it. I don't want
to go to the Führer's headquarters."
But I didn't do that.
I was too curious.
I also didn't realize...
that destiny would take me somewhere
I didn't want to be.
But, nevertheless, I find it hard
to forgive myself.
The ladies are here.
It's confirmed.
–They can pass.
"Wolfsschanze"
The Führer's Headquarters
November 1942
Rastenburg, East Prussia
Sit down, ladies.
One moment. The Führer is feeding
his dog. He'll see you in a minute.
Can you tell us... How are we supposed
to address the Führer?
The Führer speaks to you first
and you reply: Heil, mein Führer.
And the Nazi salute?
–That won't be necessary.
since the Führer isn't looking for
a soldier, but for a secretary.
Act as normal and calm
as you can.
I'll see if he
has time for you.
Mein Führer,
the ladies from Berlin are there.
Thank you, ladies, for coming
in the middle of the night.
Sometimes, during a war,
one is not in control of time.
Can I ask your name?
–Margarethe Lorenz. Heil, mein Führer.
Where are you from?
–From Fulda. Heil, mein Führer.
And what is your name?
–Ursula Puttkammer. Heil, mein Führer.
No need for that.
Where are you from?
Frankfurt am Main, mein Füh...
Hannah Potrovsky,
born and raised in Berlin.
In Pankow, to be precise.
Hedwig Brandt
from Crailsheim, Swabia.
And you are?
–Traudl Humps. I'm from Munich.
A lady from Munich.
Fräulein Humps,
shall we start then?
My Blondi won't hurt you.
She's very intelligent.
She's much smarter
than most people.
First, sit down, please.
Don't be nervous. I make
many mistakes during dictation.
You won't make nearly as many.
You're very young.
How old are you?
–22, mein Führer.
My fellow German countrymen and women...
...fellow party members.
It is, I think, rather remarkable...
that, after 20 years of service, a man still
stands in front of his supporters...
...and that in all those 20 years, his
program has never needed modification.
I suggest we try it again.
I did it.
He hired me.
Berlin - April 20, 1945
Hitler's 56th birthday
Two and a half years later
Take cover.
Continue. Hurry.
Get that off the street.
Take cover.
That's artillery fire.
–Don't be silly. Where would it be coming from?
You're right. Those aren't planes,
it is artillery.
It's the Russians.
What a birthday present.
Burgdorf, where are those
artillery shells coming from?
Happy birthday,
mein Führer.
Downtown Berlin is under fire.
Shells have hit near the
Brandenburg Gate and the Reichstag.
Where did they come from?
–We don't know yet.
I have Koller on the line.
–Give me Koller.
Koller, do you know Berlin
is under artillery fire?
No.
–Can't you hear the shooting?
No, I'm in the Werder Game Park.
–Berlin is in chaos.
Apparently, the Russians captured
a railway bridge over the Oder.
The enemy has no railway
artillery near the Oder.
It's not long-range artillery.
The anti-aircraft defense near the
Zoo-Bunker reports they're calibers of...
...10 to 12 centimeters. The Russians
have positions near Marzahn.
That's only 12 kilometers from the center.
Are the Russians that close?
They should hang the entire
Luftwaffe leadership.
This is unheard of.
The Russians are 12 kilometers
from the city center.
Nobody told me anything.
I had to ask.
Maybe it's long-range artillery,
after all.
That railway bridge over the Oder...
–Nonsense.
You shouldn't do that, Fräulein Braun.
He already eats nothing
but cake all day long.
Don't be so strict.
It's his birthday.
He deserves something nice.
He has so little fun.
I'll bring up some more bottles.
Suddenly everybody wants some.
I'm glad that you help him in these
difficult times. He appreciates you enormously.
What do I do for him?
–Cheer him up.
His generals always bring him their troubles.
He doesn't want to hear it anymore.
You'd be troubled, too.
The city center is already
being shelled.
I hope it doesn't rain down
during his birthday celebration.
Nothing will happen.
–Still, it seems risky.
Just do like everybody else, Frau Jung,
and let the Führer decide.
That Himmler,
such a pompous buffoon.
Party bosses, everywhere.
They make me so sick.
The Führer started
"Clausewitz" today.
Berlin on the front lines.
He won't be able to keep the city.
If the Führer stays here,
the Reich will go down with him.
We have to talk him out of it.
Talk to Hewel.
He's the only diplomat
with any influence on him.
Hewel tried everything.
It's useless.
Talk to your sister-in-law, then.
Why not? You're married
to the sister of Eva Braun.
We must try everything.
Berlin is almost surrounded.
You're still young.
You'll be a father soon.
Do you want die here?
–Absolutely not.
Gentlemen, the Führer.
Everything out, quickly.
We're leaving in two hours.
What's going on?
–We're leaving.
"Clausewitz" has started.
All the ministries and departments
are leaving Berlin.
And who's going to look after
the people and the soldiers?
Don't ask me, professor.
–This is insane.
Professor.
I won't allow the
evacuation of my office.
Is that so?
–The food supply will collapse.
A good soldier can
always find food.
And when there's fighting all over the city,
where does he get it? The population.
It's irresponsible.
–It's an order from the Führer.
As a department head, I
report to the SS and to Himmler.
But as a doctor, I'm part of the Wehrmacht
and they're not leaving yet.
Keep that in mind.
The professor stays in Berlin.
Get him the proper papers.
We're leaving.
Everything for Germany.
Heil, mein Führer.
Führer, I...
They're in such a hurry
to get away from here.
The brown nosing is the worst.
They say "Sieg Heil," but they think
"Lick my... you know what."
Mein Führer, I beg you to leave Berlin.
It's not too late yet.
Too late?
Hewel, come here for a moment.
I'm sure you agree we should contact
the Allies...
...and start conducting politics.
–Certainly. We need politics.
Politics?
I don't do politics anymore.
I'm fed up with it.
When I'm dead, you'll have plenty
of time for politics.
It's OK, dear Himmler.
My loyal Heinrich.
It's OK.
Just go.
He has no strength left.
What did you expect from a
vegetarian teetotaler?
Seriously, though, Fegelein.
I'm taking control now.
Berlin will fall in a few days.
When the Führer's dead, who will
the Allies negotiate with?
Why do you think they'll
negotiate with you?
The Nazi state and my SS are needed
to maintain order.
One hour with Eisenhower
and he'll feel the same way.
The first contact has been made.
–Careful, that's high treason.
Fegelein, I have other concerns.
Should I give Eisenhower the Nazi salute,
or shake his hand?
Look at this.
The cleaner guests arrive
later in the evening.
Leaving already, gentlemen?
I wanted to talk to you.
The scorched-earth orders...
–I really have to go now.
Come and see me one day
in Hohenlychen.
I'm going north to help with the
battle of Berlin there.
You know, Speer... There's an
advantage to those bombings.
It's easier to clean up debris
than to demolish everything ourselves.
When the war is won,
reconstruction will be quick.
We've spent thousands of hours
together with these models.
You're a true genius, Speer.
Yes, absolutely. Only you and I know that
the Third Reich would be inconceivable...
...with only warehouses and factories.
Skyscrapers and hotels.
This Third Reich will be a
treasury of art and culture...
...that will survive thousands of years.
We see, before us, the ancient cities,
the Acropolis...
...medieval cities,
with their cathedrals...
...and we know that the people
need that.
Yes, Speer.
That was my vision...
...and it still is.
Mein Führer, if you want to realize
these plans, you must leave Berlin.
Eva, you say something.
He's the Führer.
He knows what's best.
You must leave Berlin.
The Russians almost have us isolated.
I can't do that, my child.
I would be like a lama priest
with an empty prayer wheel.
I have to solve the problem,
here in Berlin, or perish.
Speer...
...what do you think?
You have to be onstage
when the curtain falls.
Reload.
Go away.
Leave me alone.
How old are you? Twelve?
And you? Fourteen?
Why are you here?
To play at war? Go home.
Who are you? What do you want?
–I want my son. Alive.
You should be proud.
He destroyed two tanks.
The Führer will decorate
him for it today.
You're young.
Which front did you fight on?
I... haven't had the honor yet.
Consider yourself lucky.
Send the children home.
We'll defend this position
to the last man.
What position?
This isn't a position, it's a trap.
The Russians will come from two sides
and you won't be able to get out.
We'll shoot back.
–With what?
We'll use flak as artillery.
The Russians will arrive with several
armies, tanks and heavy artillery.
Do you really think you'll
last even five minutes?
We have sworn it
to the Führer.
Don't you understand?
The war is lost. It's over.
Go away. Right now.
If you're still here when the Russians
arrive, you'll all be dead.
The 9th Army must retreat
or they'll be decimated...
The 9th Army will not retreat.
Busse must fight where he stands.
Führer, then the 9th Army is lost.
We'll push back the Soviet armies
in the north and east...
...with a ruthless, mighty attack.
With what units, mein Führer?
Steiner will attack from the north
and join the 9th Army.
The 9th Army is unable to move.
The enemy outnumbers us ten times.
Wenck's 12th Army must
support them.
The 12th Army is approaching the Elbe.
–Then it must turn around.
Then the western front would be open.
–Do you doubt my orders?
I think I've made myself clear.
I've reconciled myself to it.
I will remain in the capital.
It is neither possible nor
will it be permitted...
...for these cultureless
barbarians to conquer Europe.
I am the final bulwark against it.
The fight for Berlin
will decide the fate of Germany.
Only here can the moral victory
be gained.
If the Führer must die,
it will be in the ruins of Berlin.
He owes it to world history.
His historical role must be played out here.
Mohnke, you're here.
–Mein Führer.
"Clausewitz" started today.
Berlin has become a front city.
You will be the commandant of the
Reichs Chancellery defense.
We'll fight until the last man in Berlin.
There are still three million civilians
here. They have to be evacuated.
I understand your concern, Mohnke.
But we have to be ice cold.
We cannot worry ourselves
for so-called citizens.
With all due respect, what will
happen to the women and children...
...and the thousands of wounded
and elderly?
In a war such as this,
there are no civilians.
The Führer has lost all
sense of reality.
He's moving divisions around
that no longer exist.
Steiner's group has been scattered,
yet Steiner must attack. Madness.
But why don't you tell him that?
–He doesn't listen to reason.
Something has to happen.
–Are you crazy? He'll throw us out.
We're soldiers.
We took an oath.
Does that mean we can't use
our own brains anymore?
And that's coming from you?
An opportunist? A ruthless careerist?
I beg your pardon?
Where were you?
–None of your business.
The most successful tank hunters of the
Berlin Hitler Youth stand before you.
I'm proud of you.
This boy took out two tanks
using anti-tank shells.
His name is Peter Kranz.
–So you're Peter.
I wish my generals were
as brave as you.
Good, good.
You've made history.
And when Germania rises
from these ruins...
...you will be the heroes.
Heil, to you.
I don't know about you,
but I prefer air raids.
What will happen to us?
–I could go if I wanted to.
But everybody is deserting him.
We can't all go, can we?
I can't go either.
I wouldn't know
where to go.
My parents and all
my friends warned me...
Don't get involved with the Nazis.
What should I say,
"Hello, I made a mistake"?
"When things went wrong,
I admitted my mistake."
Life will go on.
What do you think, Colonel?
–We have to go.
Where to?
–I don't know.
Wherever we're needed.
Let's go upstairs.
We'll party.
Come on.
Come, children.
We should have fun today.
Wherever the enemy goes,
all they'll find is destruction.
That's the death sentence
for the German people.
No power, no gas, no drinking
water, no coal, no transportation.
If you destroy all
the infrastructure...
...our country will go back
to the Middle Ages.
This order denies the people
any chance of survival.
If the war is lost, what does it matter
if the people are lost too?
The German people's primary needs of
life aren't important right now.
On the contrary,
we'd do best to destroy them ourselves.
Our people proved to be weak, and according
to the laws of nature, they should die out.
They're your people.
You're their Führer.
What remains after this battle...
...is only the inferior.
The superior will have fallen.
Come along.
You have to dance.
Care to dance, Fräulein Braun?
–I'd love to.
Excuse me?
–Of course.
What is it?
We have to leave Berlin, Eva.
You must convince him.
Or else, come with me.
You'll die.
Can somebody play some music?
I want to dance.
Dance.
Do you have a request?
–A swing.
Traudl.
It's all so unreal.
It's like a dream you
can't wake up from.
It keeps on going.
Gerda, I don't feel well.
Traudl, come.
I'm at my command post.
I did not move
my command post.
To the west? How so?
I'm 1000 meters from the enemy.
–General.
So, General?
I'm to be shot.
–What? Why?
They think I moved my
command post to the west.
Be sensible, General.
–Come with me.
Schenck.
–Mohnke.
I'm under the chancellery.
I'm commandant of its defense now.
I need aid.
–That will be difficult. Everything's gone.
My adjutant and I are
the only ones here.
You're a doctor, aren't you?
–Yes, an internist.
Commandeer a car and
bring all the medication...
...that you can find to me.
I'll do my best.
–Thanks. Hurry..
I must speak to the Führer.
About what?
–I'm to be shot.
Wait here.
Your weapons, please.
Not here.
Guard Post 2.
Understood.
General...
Not you.
What is this?
Why am I to be shot?
You know that any evasive maneuver
towards the west is forbidden.
Officers who don't obey
must be shot.
What do you mean?
My troops have been fighting for days.
My command post
is a kilometer from the front line.
Continue.
Do you see this?
I forbid you to take that tone with me.
And now, do whatever
you feel you must.
It's best if you tell this to the
Führer yourself. Come along.
You can't pass, Colonel.
–Orders from Brigade Führer Mohnke.
I have to get into the hospital.
We need medication.
There's nobody left.
They all took off.
And the wounded?
–How should I know?
I'm going to have a look.
You stay here.
Be very careful.
There are lots of Russians here.
See that? That's where the
Reich ends. Behind it is Russkie-Land.
May I?
He's damned stubborn.
Why doesn't he let me do that?
Am I supposed to tie him up?
What was I to do?
I'm disabled.
Do you want your son to be, too?
Don't shout at me like that.
He wanted to be part of the Hitler Youth.
Just like thousands of others.
He wants to defend himself,
and avenge himself.
Yes, look at me.
You make me shit.
You've suffered,
but you could fight.
We could do nothing
when it rained bombs.
We had only
our fear and our rage.
Arming children wasn't my idea.
The Führer said...
The Führer...
He's sent entire armies to their graves.
Now he lets children fight against two
million Russians. He's gone insane.
Coward.
Peter, stay there.
I want talk to you.
What would you have me do? Tell me.
My compliments.
I should have been back by now.
Are you sure the Führer still needs me?
Drink.
–Führer's orders.
You made a big impression
on the Führer.
But you don't think Steiner
will attack, do you?
I doubt whether Steiner
is able to do anything...
...but you probably know that
better than I do.
If Steiner doesn't attack,
Berlin is lost.
The Führer was impressed
with your report.
He puts you in command of
the defense of Berlin.
I'd have preferred to
be shot.
Fall back.
Let them get closer.
Tank alert.
Easy. Wait, kid.
They're still too far.
Stay in the bunker, ladies.
Is that German artillery I hear?
–I'm afraid not.
But hasn't Steiner's
attack started?
You have to go as fast as you can.
Time is running out.
But the Führer has
the situation under control.
Steiner's attack will make
all the difference.
The Führer says it will change
military history.
Everybody but the Führer knows
that's a fantasy.
I wonder if he even believes it himself.
–Why would he play games?
What does he have to lose?
I don't believe a word of it.
The enemy has made a breakthrough.
They took Zossen and are advancing
towards Stahnsdorf.
They're at the city's northern border,
between Frohnau and Pankow.
In the east, they've reached
Lichtenberg, Mahlsdorf and Karlshorst.
When Steiner attacks,
everything will be alright.
Mein Führer...
Steiner...
Steiner didn't have sufficient forces.
The attack did not happen.
The following stay in the room:
Keitel, Jodl, Krebs and Burgdorf.
That was an order.
Steiner's attack was an order.
How dare you
ignore my orders?
Is this what it's come to?
The military, everybody lied
to me. Even the SS.
The generals are no more than
a bunch of disloyal cowards.
I can't allow that...
Cowards, traitors and incompetents.
–Mein Führer, that's outrageous.
The generals are the scum
of the German people.
No sense of honor.
You call yourself General because
you spent years at the academy...
...where you only learned
to use knife and fork.
For years, the military
obstructed me.
All you ever did is
thwart me.
I should have had...
...all the high officers executed.
Like Stalin did.
I never went to the academy.
But I conquered all
of Europe on my own.
Traitors.
I've been betrayed and deceived
from the start.
Such enormous betrayal
of the German people.
But all these traitors will pay.
With their own blood.
They'll drown
in their own blood.
Calm down, Gerda.
All my orders have
been ignored.
How can I be a leader
under these circumstances?
It's over.
The war is lost.
But if you think this means
I'll leave Berlin...
...you're mistaken. I'd rather
shoot a bullet through my head.
Do what you want.
The Führer wasn't serious about
shooting himself, was he?
Frau Junge, Frau Christian.
Get changed. In one hour,
a plane will take you south.
Everything is lost.
Hopelessly lost.
You know I'll stay with you.
You can't send me away.
Mein Führer, I'm staying too.
What now?
Time for this charade to end.
Do you want us to stop fighting?
That's inconceivable.
The Führer doesn't want us to capitulate.
No more November 1918. Ever.
But he doesn't want to be in charge
anymore. He said "Do what you want."
Nobody can replace him.
The Führer is the Führer.
The Führer's confused.
He'll recover.
Great.
And then what?
No capitulation. That was
never his intention.
We owe it to him.
–Hollow phrases.
We have to act now,
or it will be too late.
You're only looking after yourself.
–Mind your words.
Damn.
We'll never get out of here alive.
It's all over.
We've got to wait.
Even the Führer doesn't believe in it
anymore. What will happen to us?
Günsche says there's a tunnel
that goes under the Russian lines.
Why did you say
you wanted to stay with him?
I don't know.
Honestly.
Will we ever be able to
buy bread again?
At the bakery, like before?
It stopped.
Let's go for a walk.
Traudl.
Look here.
Ah, children, I'm lighting another one.
Let's go down again.
You know that statue outside?
It would look good in my garden, by the pond.
Will you buy it for me
if we get out of here?
My dear, I don't know who owns
that statue.
It's state property, certainly.
I can't put it in a private garden.
If you manage to escape Berlin,
surely you can make a small exception.
Female logic.
You're very dirty.
You can't wear this coat anymore.
You don't have to walk
around like some old man.
This is my work uniform.
I can't be see apronless, my
colored pencils in disarray.
Mommy.
Ammunition. Fast.
Where's the medic?
Where did they come from?
–Volkssturm. Drafted this afternoon.
They have to get
out of the field of fire.
The Volkssturm is under the
direct command of Dr. Goebbels.
I want them out of here.
This is insane.
I'll take the responsibility.
I think this is wrong.
–Great.
Stop. Lights out.
Stop. Stay where you are.
Stay where you are.
–Alright, Germans.
Help. They want to kill us.
–What is all this?
A Greifkommando.
–You're kidding.
Stop it.
Let those men go.
What's this?
–You have no authority here.
These men are fugitives.
Traitors are shot.
They're old men. Civilians.
You can't do this.
Who's going to stop me?
You maybe?
Stop it. That's enough.
Dismissed.
This man's a doctor.
Can you operate?
–Not really.
Don't let the children
take too many toys.
And not too many pajamas.
They're no longer needed.
Herr Minister...
–Frau Junge, my family will arrive soon.
Can you look after them for a moment?
Thank you.
Brigade Führer, what can I do for you?
Your Volkssturm is easy prey
for the Russians.
They have neither combat experience
nor good weapons.
Their unconditional belief
in the final victory makes up for that.
Herr Minister, without weapons
those men can't fight.
Their deaths will be pointless.
I don't pity them.
I repeat:
The people called this
upon themselves.
This may come as a surprise to you,
but have no illusion.
We didn't force the people.
They gave us a mandate.
And now their little necks
are being snapped.
Eva, you have to leave the Führer.
Don't be stupid.
This is about life and death.
How can you say that?
Where are you?
I decided
not to die in Berlin.
Does my sister know where you are?
–Think about it. I'll call you back.
Children, your room is to the right.
Wait for me.
Hello, Frau Goebbels.
–Good to see you, Frau Junge.
Line up, children.
Helga, come. Line up.
Let's make ourselves look good and
then we'll go say hello to Uncle Hitler.
Do you remember the song?
I agree.
If we don't amputate, he'll die.
Give yourself room to work.
Cut down to the artery.
Be brave, colleague.
Take hold of the artery.
Clamp it.
Saw.
The best thing to do is
shoot yourself in the mouth.
Then your skull explodes.
You won't feel a thing.
You'll be dead immediately.
I want to be a beautiful corpse.
I'll take poison.
If I have to die,
at least let it be painless.
That's definitely painless.
It paralyses the nervous system
and the respiratory system.
A matter of seconds.
Can I have one too?
–Me too.
Himmler supplied me well.
Thank you.
I would have liked to give you
a nicer present.
Berlin, April 23 1945.
My dear little sister, I'm sorry
to write this to you.
But such is how it is. It could
be over any moment.
First of all: Hermann isn't with us.
But I'm sure
you'll see him again.
He'll get through this
and fight on from Bavaria.
The Führer has lost all hope
of a positive outcome.
Dear son, I don't know
if you will receive this letter.
Maybe someone will allow me
to send you a last greeting.
I stayed with dad
against his will.
Last Sunday, the Führer
wanted to help me escape.
But you know your mother.
We have the same blood.
I won't even think about it.
Our ideology is
going down the drain...
...and with it, everything that made
life beautiful and worthwhile.
A world without the Führer and National
Socialism is not worth living in.
That is why I brought
the children, too.
They are too good for the
life that awaits them.
God will have mercy on me
if I bring them redemption myself.
I'll wear my bracelet with the green
stone until the very end.
After that, I want
you to always wear it.
Unfortunately, my diamond watch
is with the watchmaker.
I've included the address below.
I hope you're lucky enough to get it.
I want you to have it.
You'll also get the bracelet
with the topaz pendant.
A birthday present
from the Führer.
I owe some money
to the Heise company.
There may be more debts, but
no more than 1500 Reichsmarks.
All correspondence with
the Führer must be burned.
I'm sending you some food and tobacco.
Also, the coffee is for Lindner and Kathl.
The cigarettes are for Mandi, the tobacco
for dad, the chocolate for mom.
I can't think of anything else.
That's it for today.
Dear sister, I wish
you lots of happiness.
And remember,
you will see Hermann again.
The warmest regards
and a kiss from...
...your sister.
Peter.
I brought some bread.
I have to go, dad. They need me.
–Stay here.
Let me go.
–Easy, boy.
Let him go.
The Führer needs everyone.
I'm tired of your bullshit.
–Wilhelm.
What did you say?
Kiss my ass.
They should hang you.
With somebody like you we'd make short work.
Let's go get some water.
–There's no water here.
Then we'll have to go outside and look.
–Are you drunk?
Come on, hero. I'll protect you.
Inge.
Give me that gun.
Give it here.
I don't fight against children.
Berlin is not really
as bad off as it seems.
The divisions must be kept intact.
Supplement them with civilians if necessary.
If we stop the Soviets here,
the whole world will be taken aback.
If it's really true...
...that there are rifts between
the Allies, and that happens...
...then a reversal is possible...
...and I can deliver a blow to the head
of this insatiable Bolshevik colossus.
If I'm successful here,
and save the capital...
...then the world will realize
that only one man is capable...
...of stopping the Bolsheviks.
And that is me.
If I win this battle, then it's not
for personal honor and glory.
But for history.
If all goes well, perfect. In the opposite
case, Europe will become Bolshevik.
And in five years, the Führer and
National Socialism will become legendary.
Sanctified by the last great battle.
Everything that the world reproaches
us for will be swept aside.
Only here in Berlin
can everything still be saved.
Each last man must be utilized.
That is our duty.
Grand Admiral Dönitz will be happy to learn
that things are so well with the Führer.
Such energy.
–It's a miracle.
He is and remains the Führer.
And just yesterday there were rumors
that he'd succumbed to depression.
You said it yourself: rumors.
The V2 will ensure
a reversal of the situation.
Their range must be enormous.
When will they be ready?
I can't say anything.
It's a strict secret.
Naturally. Excuse me.
Here I am.
Got you.
Excuse us.
–It's nothing.
Go play upstairs.
General Field Marshal,
the Führer would like to speak with you.
Listen, Keitel.
I want you to leave tonight.
Go to Dönitz and help him
get everything organized.
Things have to be
started up again.
I don't understand you.
We have no more oil fields.
That's catastrophic.
It makes any serious operation
impossible.
Once everything is settled here,
we must recover our oil fields.
Any other questions?
–No, mein Führer.
Good.
Have a good trip.
Fritz.
Martha.
The operator is dead and the entire
Army press service has left.
Frau Junge, bring this
to Herr Bormann. It's urgent.
Bad news?
This has just come in.
–Thank you very much, Frau Junge.
A dispatch from Göring.
He writes:
Mein Führer,
based on your decision...
...to remain in Berlin,
do you agree...
...that I thereby take command...
...with complete freedom of action?
If I receive no reply by 2200 hours,
I'll assume you have been incapacitated.
I will then act on behalf
of the country and the Fatherland.
That's high treason.
And betrayal of you.
Göring's concerns are not
entirely unjustified.
If our communication
system fails...
...we'll be cut off
from the outside world.
We won't be able
to issue orders anymore.
I think Göring wants
to seize power.
I never trusted his clique
at Obersalzberg.
This looks like a coup.
That failure. That parasite.
Parvenu. Sluggard.
How dare he say
I'm incapacitated?
Hello.
–Herr Speer. How did you get into Berlin?
It wasn't easy,
but I must speak with the Führer.
If I were you,
I'd wait a bit.
The Luftwaffe.
What has he done to it?
For that alone,
he should be executed.
That morphine addict
corrupted the country.
And now this.
He betrays me.
Me of all people.
I want Göring stripped
of his power, immediately.
And, in case I don't
survive the war...
...he's to be
executed immediately.
What's going to happen to us?
Is there any hope left?
Frau Junge, leave here
before it's too late.
The Führer is staying.
We can't leave him behind, can we?
He doesn't need anybody for what
awaits him. Least of all you.
But Herr Goebbels and his wife
are staying. And the children.
But the children...
I always thought...
...that there was a way out.
Warmer, warmer, warmer...
Hot.
Look, Heide.
–It's beautiful.
Uncle Albert.
Uncle Albert, won't you stay with us?
–I can't, Helga. I have work to do.
You can work here too.
Good evening, Herr Speer.
–Frau Christian. Are you
running a kindergarten now?
Mom is sick.
What does she have?
–I don't know.
The doctor wants her to stay in bed.
Herr minister,
Frau Braun would like to speak with you.
Good luck.
See you soon, children.
–See you soon.
Who wants some apple juice?
–Me.
Tell Frau Braun that I'll be by.
Come in.
Albert. Hello.
You have a fever.
Albert, I can't take
it anymore.
Why don't you leave with
the children, Magda?
Leave?
And go where?
I can arrange a barge to
take you to Schwanenwerder.
You can hide
until everything's over.
I've thought about it.
My children can't grow up in
a world without National Socialism.
Think about it some more. The
children have a right to a future.
If National Socialism dies,
there will be no future.
I can't believe
you really want that.
Go.
I'll come by again
before I leave.
Come in.
I knew you'd come.
You wouldn't desert
the Führer.
I've come to say goodbye to the Führer.
I'm going back to Hamburg tonight.
Of course, you must go.
Sit down.
I brought some furniture
you designed.
I couldn't leave it behind.
Please, you must've
not eaten all day.
That's true.
It's very important that you came.
It shows him you're on his side.
Did he ever doubt that?
Lately, he often thought
you were against him too.
I always said you'd come
and here you are.
I think he liked it that you
advised him to stay in Berlin.
I think it's best, too.
And, you know...
...it may sound strange...
...but I'm really happy here.
And I'm not afraid.
Herr Speer...
The Führer...
When you speak with him...
There's the question of whether we'll
remain here, or fly to Berchtesgaden.
Advise him to leave, Herr Speer.
He listens to you.
Persuade him that if we don't leave Berlin,
the Bolsheviks will cut our throat.
So, you came.
–Mein Führer, I...
It's OK.
Let's sit down.
I had great plans
for the Germans and the world.
Nobody understood me.
Not even my old brothers in arms.
The opportunities we had.
The whole world was ours to grab.
Too late.
I can be proud only...
for openly fighting the Jews...
...and for cleansing the Lebensraum
of the Jewish poison.
I don't find it hard to go on.
One brief moment...
...and then eternal peace.
But please spare the people,
mein Führer.
If my people cannot endure
this ordeal...
...I won't shed a tear.
They get what they deserve.
They brought this fate
upon themselves.
For months...
...I have to tell you this...
...for months I've sabotaged
your orders for destruction.
I not only ignored your orders,
but even acted against them.
I had to tell you.
My personal loyalty to you
has never wavered.
So you're leaving.
Good.
Goodbye.
I wish you all the best.
Come in.
The very best.
Eat as so much as
you can, gentlemen.
Peter.
It's alright, son.
He has a fever.
Yes, but he's alive.
If God wants to do
someone a favor
He sends him out into the world
gives him a bite to eat
and then sends him to a sausage factory.
The lazy ones who lie in bed
are not invigorated by the dawn.
They know only of rocking cradles,
of worries, burden, need and bread.
The streams gush in the mountains.
Larks flutter in the air.
Why would I not sing along
loudly and from full breast?
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-