-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-
Fanny.
Mother.
Siri.
Maj.
Grandmother.
Alexander.
What are you doing?
Do you want to play cards
before dinner?
Fanny and Alexander.
This is the 43rd Christmas
we're celebrating together.
My dear Ester! Is it?
Yes, the 43rd.
Well, well, who'd have thought it?
Yes, it's odd.
Dear Ester.
Good evening, Mrs. Ekdahl.
Good evening, girls.
- Alida, you may join the other girls.
- Thank you, Mrs. Ekdahl.
- Why are you so sullen?
- I'm not sullen.
I can see that you are.
You're always sullen
on Christmas eve.
- I don't know what you mean.
- You heard me. You're sullen.
Old hag.
Worthy Joseph, do not fear
thy angel is thee ever near
I come in haste to bring thee word
from thy creator and thy God
Mary and the child now wake
and quickly into safety take
Herod with his murdering hand
threatens every man-child in this land
all this I have noted well
and shall do as you foretell.
Praised be God upon his throne
who thus protects my only son.
Thus, good people, ends our play
it all ends well on this holy day.
The son of God, saved from the sword
is our saviour, Christ the Lord.
We know that in his mercy mild
he guards every woman, man and child.
man and each boy.
A time of joyous Christmas cheer
we wish to all, both far and near
let no one into darkness fall.
A merry Christmas one and all.
traditionally the Ekdahls give a party
for the theatre staff down on the stage.
The guests are what you'd call
a rather mixed lot.
Quite different from what we're used to
here in the theatre restaurant.
Nevertheless, I don't want to see
any supercilious glances,
snootiness, or raised eyebrows.
I want to see generosity,
warmth and kindness. Is that clear?
- Yes, sir.
- That's the spirit!
Alma and Petra,
take the Christmas basket.
I'll take the punch bowl.
- Are we ready?
- Yes, sir.
Forward march!
Come along, Carlchen.
We mustn't be late
to your mother's like last year.
Come along.
Let's go.
Hurry up.
Merry Christmas!
Merry Christmas, Oscar.
Help yourselves, everybody!
Step forward, step forward.
Don't be shy.
My dear friends.
for 22 years...
in the capacity of theatre manager,
I致e stood here and made a speech...
without really having any talent...
for that sort of thing.
Especially if you think of my father,
who was brilliant at speeches.
My only talent,
if you can call it that in my case...
is that I love this little world...
inside the thick walls
of this playhouse.
And I知 fond of the people
who work in this little world.
Outside is the big world,
and sometimes
the little world succeeds...
in reflecting the big one...
so that we understand it better.
Or perhaps we give the people
who come here
a chance to forget for a while...
for a few short moments...
the harsh world outside.
Our theatre is...
a little room...
of orderliness, routine, care...
...and love.
I don't know why I feel...
so comically solemn... this evening.
When you've given Ismael his dinner,
turn off the lights in the shop
and lock up.
I have the key.
Good night, Aron.
Good night, uncle lsak.
lsak!
Merry Christmas.
I can't think where they all are.
They should have been here
a long time ago.
I expect Oscar is making
a long, dull speech.
I think I hear them
down in the street.
Ester, bring me my furcoat.
There comes my family.
Merry Christmas.
Merry Christmas, grandma.
Merry Christmas, aunt.
Mom, you look so beautiful.
What is it, drling?
Aunt Emma how nice to see you.
Aunt Emma, how nice. Welcome.
What time is it?
The only question is:
Where are Carl and Lydia?
Perhaps they got the wrong time.
Christmas dinner is always at 4:30.
Alexander, run down
and ring uncle Carl痴 doorbell.
- Carlchen, please hurry.
- Shut up!
- We're so late.
We arrive late every year.
- I'm doing this for your sake.
- No more, mein Carlchen.
- Mom.
- Well, Carl.
Merry Christmas, aunt.
Well, at last we can have dinner.
What would Maj say to a little visit
in her room this evening?
The master must be joking.
Are you all right, sir?
I'm fine.
I must help the girls with the tree.
- Aren't you angry?
- Angry?
I think it's sweet.
Children, come.
Uncle Carl is going to treat you
to one helluva fireworks show.
Stay here.
Ready?
Number one.
Now comes number two.
Now comes number three.
Alexander, bring the candle.
"And it came to pass in those days
that there went out a decree
from Caesar Augustus
that all the world should be taxed.
And this taxing was first made
when Cyrenius was governor of Syria.
And all went to be taxed,
every one into his own city.
And Joseph also went up from Galilee
out of the city of Nazareth,
into Judea...
unto the city of David,
which is called Bethlehem...
because he was of the house
and lineage of David,
to be taxed with Mary his wife,
who was pregnant.
- Give up?
- No!
I'm sorry.
It's a terrible mess in here.
Come see us later
and you'll get a Christmas present.
Thank you, Mrs. Ekdahl.
Now then, children, to bed.
Hurry up, Alexander.
To bed now, children.
Now say your prayers.
Thank you God for this day.
Please make me good.
May your angel stay by me
through the night.
God bless papa and mama,
grandpapa and grandmama,
myself and my brothers and sisters
and cousins, uncles and aunts,
Vega, Ester, Maj, Siri, Berta, Alida, Lisen
and uncle Isak and everybody else.
Amen.
- Good night, Alexander.
- Good night, sweetheart.
Good night. Sleep well.
Putte kisses like a real man.
Alexander.
Look at my Christmas present.
Look what Mrs. Ekdahl gave me.
Aren't I beautiful?
Don't I look lovely?
I look like a real lady.
Don't you think?
Tonight you can't sleep in Maj's bed
because Maj will have a visitor.
And I can't just have
all the men in my bed.
But you're Maj's sweetheart.
You know that.
Well, my dear ones,
it's time to say good night.
We're getting up early.
Carlchen! Wake up.
We're going home.
Good night, mama.
Carl's a bit tired. I'll give him a hand.
Come along now.
We're going home.
Good night.
Good night, mom.
- I stayed behind.
- So I noticed.
There she lies, the beautiful girl,
poor Arabella.
Little does she know what awaits her.
She's alone in the whole house.
Her mother is dead, and her father
is carousing with loose companions.
Who comes there as the clock
strikes 12:00 in the castle tower?
"Fear seizes me.
What is that terrifying white figure
floating on the moonbeams
and drawing near my bed?
It is my dead mother.
My mother's ghost."
No more noise in here now!
Go to sleep, children.
Good night.
I thought I smelled
kerosene in the nursery.
- Kerosene?
- Yes, kerosene.
There's no kerosene lamp
in the nursery.
Well, it smells like it anyway.
Here we go, Isak.
I've made some nice strong coffee.
Much better than Vega痴
awful dishwater.
Give this a try.
What can the time be?
Ten past 3:00.
We can sit for two hours,
and then I must change
for early service.
How good it is to have you here!
You're my best friend.
Whatever would I do without you?
Last year I enjoyed Christmas.
This year all I wanted to do was cry.
I suppose I知 getting old.
Do you think I致e aged?
You've grown older, yes.
I thought so.
Yes, I just wanted to cry.
Though I love having
the grandchildren, of course.
I didn't think Oscar looked well.
He wears himself out
with that theatre.
And the idea of him playing
the ghost.
He should take it easy.
Besides, he's an awfully bad actor.
I wonder if Emilie realizes
that he's weak and needs rest.
I think I値l have a word with her.
He's capable, of course.
Capable and conscientious.
Can you believe the theatre
even makes a small profit?
Isn't that splendid?
A few years ago I contributed
a minimum of 50,000 kronor per year.
I didn't care, but Oscar felt
so awkward asking me for money.
Not like Carl.
He asked me for a new loan,
but I refused.
If he comes to you for money,
you must say no too.
- Promise me that.
- Yes, yes.
I don't understand it.
Time and again
I clear everything up for him.
After a year, he's in dire straits again.
He says he doesn't go to moneylenders.
- Do you know?
- No.
And that poor German woman
he's married to.
How could he have fallen for her?
It must be something erotic.
What do you think?
Erotic? Yes, perhaps.
- You're not listening.
- Yes, I am.
Never mind. The main thing is
that you keep me company.
Carl and Gustav Adolf are oversexed.
They take after their father.
He was oversexed.
At times I thought
it was too much of a good thing,
but I never refused.
Gustav Adolf is incorrigible.
I've spoken with Alma, and she wisely says
she doesn't mind his philandering,
because he's the kindest husband
in the world.
It's fortunate that Alma
is so understanding.
Perhaps I ought to warn that nursemaid Maj,
or whatever her name is.
I must say she's very pretty,
and good with the children.
Beautiful colouring and a nice figure.
Pity she limps, the poor thing.
Are you sad
because you've grown old?
I'm certainly not.
Everything's getting worse.
Worse people,
worse machines, worse wars...
and worse weather.
I'm glad I値l soon be dead.
You're an incorrigible old misanthrope
and always have been.
- I don't agree with you.
- I thought as much.
That doesn't stop me from crying.
Would you mind if I cry a little?
No, upon my soul, I can't.
The tears won't come.
I'll have to have some more cognac.
What are you laughing at?
Do you remember when we sat there
on the sofa kissing madly?
You had unbuttoned my blouse,
and something else too.
Then suddenly the curtain
was drawn aside,
and there stood my dear husband.
It was just like a play by Feydeau.
I screamed and you made for the door.
He rushed off to get his pistol,
with me hanging on his leg.
You became friends for life.
Your husband was a great-hearted man.
Now I知 weeping.
The happy, splendid life is over,
and the horrible,
dirty life engulfs us.
That's the way it is.
This won't do.
I must wash up
and redo my makeup,
do my hair and put on
my corset and silk dress.
A weepy, lovesick woman turns
into a self-possessed grandmother.
We all play our parts.
Some play them negligently,
others with great care.
I'm one of the latter.
Good night, my lovely Helena.
You were a sweet lover.
Like strawberries.
You wanted me to help you
with your morning toilet, Mrs. Ekdahl.
The time is ten to 5:00.
A cafe on castle street.
Your own cakes and pastries,
tarts and confections.
What do you say to that, little Maj?
You'd be in charge of it.
Just yesterday I said to Alma,
"look at Maj. She's a princess."
What breasts you have, my girl.
Let me see properly.
You drive me crazy.
Don't be afraid, child.
I am a wonderful lover.
All the women say that.
Once you get me on my back,
you'll forget about the cafe.
I swear.
Give me something to write on.
Come. Come over here.
Here's a pen.
Now I値l write:
"Maj Kling...
is the proprietress of my cafe."
Signed, Gustav Adolf Ekdahl.
Christmas night, 1907.
There! That's a contract.
Stick it under a lawyer's nose
if I forget my promise.
Be careful not to put me
in the family way.
Well, what do you say?
Aren't I nice?
Ever felt such a wooden leg?
Damnation!
The rocket went off too soon.
Oh, well, it happens.
Wasn't it wonderful?
You're a real Billy goat, sir.
And you're my little lamb.
I must lie on my back.
I'm all in a sweat.
- I ate and drank too much.
- You're not ill?
Not me!
I feel like a bakery ablaze.
Or should I say cafe?
Ill? When I知 with
such a tasty little morsel?
Sit on top of me.
Oh, you're impossible, sir!
Ride a rocking horse to Banbury cross
to see a fine lady on a white steed
- My goodness, how your heart's pounding.
- I've got a splendid heart.
- Your heart this beating.
- I Have a splendid heart.
Now you'll have to give me a new bed.
You'll have a cafe,
an apartment,
beautiful furniture, and a big bed.
- And pretty clothes.
- No one will be prettier.
You will be Gustav Adolf's mistress,
and I値l come see you
every Wednesday and Saturday at 3:00.
How silly you are.
- What?
- I said you're silly.
- Silly, am I?
- You're a real numbskull.
I'm not a numbskull!
You are, for imagining
I壇 want anything from you.
Don't you want anything?
Don't you see I was joking?
Joking?
In what way?
Don't be angry.
I'm not, but I don't like
being treated like an idiot.
- Stop laughing.
- I think you're so funny.
I can feel a cold coming on.
My throat hurts when I swallow.
My teeth are tingling.
It's freezing in here.
Why isn't there any heat?
We don't have any credit
with the wood merchant.
We owe 150 kronor.
Das weisst du doch.
You haven't learned
a damn bit of Swedish in 23 years.
Speak Swedish!
I do my best.
Last Tuesday I asked mama
for ten thousand to sort out my affairs.
She took out a paper
that said I owed her 37,000.
It's incredible.
- You'll have to go to the Jew.
- I've already been.
I'm paying one hell
of an exorbitant interest rate,
and if I don't pay on time,
he'll show the paper to mama.
I have some jewellery.
Idiot.
That would be nice. Professor Ekdahl
running to the pawnbroker.
Aren't you coming to bed?
Come, Carlchen.
Come and sit by me.
You smell bad.
Have you given up washing,
or are you starting to rot?
No. I don't smell bad at all.
You have olfactory hallucinations.
It's bleeding.
- Shall I bandage it up?
- No.
- Won't you try and get some sleep?
- Yes.
I feel sorry for you, mein Carlchen.
How is it one becomes second-rate?
Can you tell me that?
How does the dust fall?
When has one lost?
First I知 a prince,
heir to the kingdom.
Suddenly, before I know it...
I知 deposed.
Death taps me on the shoulder.
The room is cold...
and we can't pay for kindling.
I'm stupid and unkind.
And I知 most unkind...
to the only person who cares for me.
You can never forgive me.
I'm a shit and a cad.
If you like,
I値l make you a hot toddy.
Don't be so damned servile!
Wipe your mouth.
Your lips are always wet. It's disgusting!
I didn't mean to be rude.
I know, mein liebling.
Oh, life!
Insomnia, poverty and humiliation.
Stretch out your hand
and you grope in the emptiness.
Why am I such a bloody coward?
Good night.
- Good morning, papa.
- Good morning, Petra.
Won't you give me a kiss?
- Good morning, Gustav Adolf.
- Good morning, Alma.
Go and fry three eggs
and some ham for papa,
and make two cheese sandwiches.
- What will you drink?
- Beer.
Petra, you know
where the beer crate is.
No, wait, I think there's some stout
in the cupboard.
- Would you rather have stout?
- Yes.
Don't stand there staring.
We have to be at grandma's in an hour.
- How do you feel?
- Cognac.
- I've put out your clothes.
- Thank you.
And there's hot water
if you want a bath.
That would be nice.
Hurry up now.
You're a damned handsome woman.
And you're a big shit.
- Come to bed.
- I just did my hair.
We'll have a quick one standing up.
- Petra's coming with breakfast.
- We'll lock the door.
Come on then, but make it quick.
- I don't think I can.
- You can't?
No. There must be something wrong.
- You're not sick, are you?
- I'm fit as a fiddle.
- Lie down on the bed.
- Yes, I guess I could do that.
- Shall I bring in the breakfast tray?
- Yes, please.
To think that I haven't killed you.
Now what do you say?
Well, my friends, it's time.
Sleeping within my orchard
my custom always of the afternoon
upon my secure hour thy uncle stole
with juice of cursed hebenon in a vial
and in the porches of my ears
did pour the leperous distilment,
whose effect holds
such an enmity with blood of man
that swift as quicksilver
it courses through
the natural gates and alleys
of the body
and with a sudden vigour
it doth possess and curd,
like eager droppings into milk,
the thin and wholesome blood:
So did it mine and a most
instant tetter bark'd about
most lazar-like,
with vile and loathsome crust.
Oh, horrible, most horrible!
If thou hast nature in thee,
bear it not.
Let not the royal bed of Denmark be
a couch for luxury and damned incest.
I've forgotten what I am to do.
You get up and exit upstage centre.
- Where am I?
- Here... at the theatre.
Let's go home and rest.
What's happened?
You're tired, that's all.
Shall I call for the ambulance?
What am I doing here?
You were acting.
I was acting?
Why was I acting?
Come along, Oscar.
Let's go home.
Am I going to die now?
Please help me.
I'll get a carriage.
He needs his overcoat.
Alexander, come along.
Come on.
Stop!
I said stop! Hey, you!
Take the cart behind you!
No.
We know nothing yet.
Yes, let's hope so.
Thank you for calling.
- How is our dear Oscar?
- We can only hope.
- How is he?
- It's a matter of hours.
- Is he in pain?
- He sleeps most of the time.
Go see Ester and Vega
for hot chocolate and sandwiches.
Just imagine, children.
This letter will go all the way
to a mission in China.
Mr. Albrektsson told me
his poodle had four puppies.
A friend of mine
has lived there for 50 years.
He wondered
if you'd like a puppy.
Mom won't let us
have dogs or cats.
- We could keep it here.
- Really?
- Yes.
- Splendid.
Otherwise it'll be sold.
When I was in China,
working in the fields with my friend,
we had a dog and three cats.
- Want to play again?
- You take red, then.
Mr. Albrektsson
makes lots of money on his dogs,
but he wants to give this puppy away.
He's wealthy in his own right.
It's his wife's money, dear Ester.
Would you two like
a molasses sandwich?
Yes, please, miss Vega.
There, the letter's finished.
Come, Fanny,
and I値l let you lick the envelope.
- Would you like to borrow the flute?
- No, thank you.
- You want to lick the stamp?
You lick the stamp, then.
Thank you, sweetheart.
Leave me alone.
Come in.
Your mom asked me to come get you.
Let's put down the sandwiches.
Come, Alexander.
Don't be afraid.
Come here, Alexander.
Come on.
I'll wait outside.
Come here, Fanny.
Tell Alexander
there's nothing to be afraid of.
I'll tell him.
I could play the ghost now...
really well.
Nothing.
Nothing...
separates me from all of you.
Not now...
...and not later.
I know that.
I see it...
quite clearly.
I'll be closer to you now...
than when I lived.
Now I壇 like to look at Alexander.
Alexander.
Father says there's nothing
to be afraid of.
Don't be childish now.
Try to be a good boy.
Fanny, wake up.
Did you hear that?
Piss, hell, shit,
fart, cock, cunt, damn, hell,
crap, ass, piss, cock, butt, pussy.
Siri, tell the children
they may leave the table.
Yes, ma'am.
Did you hear something?
Alexander, wake up.
There's something out there.
Good day.
Good day, Alexander.
Please give my regards
to your mother.
Hello.
What's wrong?
Alexander, someone wishes to talk to you.
The hot chocolate will have to wait.
- What have I done?
- You know quite well.
- Good day, Alexander.
- Good day.
We met once before.
Under sadder circumstances,
when I officiated at your father's funeral.
Since then, your mother has turned to me
with her worries, as is only natural.
I am a close friend
of your grandmother.
I'm the spiritual guide of the parish.
The Bishop has been very good to me
during this difficult time.
We've also spoken of you, my son.
I've told the Bishop how proud I am
of my well-behaved children.
You and your sister
are doing well at school, I知 told.
Diligent and attentive,
and earning good grades.
Isn't that correct, Alexander?
Don't be afraid.
I'm your friend and wish you well.
You believe me, don't you?
But diligence and good grades
are not everything in this world.
Blow your nose, Alexander.
That's filthy!
Didn't Maj give you a clean handkerchief?
Yes.
Goddamn it all!
As I said, diligence and good grades
aren't everything in this world.
Listen to the Bishop, Alexander.
I'm sure he is.
Aren't you, Alexander?
You're anxious to know
what I知 going to say.
You're a big boy now.
So I値l talk to you man to man.
Can you tell me -
can you explain to me
what a lie is
and what the truth is?
You think that was a stupid question,
and it probably was.
I was just kidding with you.
Of course you know what a lie is
and what the truth is, don't you?
Splendid, my boy..
I am satisfied.
You also know why one lies.
Why does one lie?
Can you explain to me why one lies?
Because you don't
want to tell the truth.
A very sly answer, my young friend.
But you won't get off so easily.
I asked you...
why does one not tell the truth?
I don't know.
We have plenty of time, Alexander,
and I'm so interested in your answer
that I'am prepared for
to wait indefinitely.
You may not believe that,
but it's true.
One lies to gain an advantage.
Good answer, my boy.
Good and concise.
Forgive me if I ask another question,
a bit more personal this time.
Can you explain to your mother and me
why you lied at school?
What?
Your teacher has written to me,
saying that you've been spreading
the most incredible lies.
Like what?
Sold to a circus!
Do you deny
that you told your classmates
that I sold you to a travelling circus,
and that at the end of the semester
they're coming to get you?
You are to train
as an acrobat and circus rider,
together with a gypsy
your age named Tamara.
Go to your mother
and ask her forgiveness
for all the sorrow and worry
you've caused her.
Go to your mother
and ask her to forgive you.
Did you hear what I said or not?
I ask mother's forgiveness for lying,
and I promise never to do it again.
The matter is resolved
and need never be mentioned again.
Imagination is a splendid thing,
a mighty force, a gift from God.
It's held in trust for us
by the great artists,
writers and musicians.
I'll get Fanny.
Come Alexander.
I have something important
to tell you.
Edvard has asked if I will marry him.
I've accepted with gratitude and joy.
I've been alone for a long time,
and my children need a firm hand.
A father.
Of course, a great deal will be -
may God in his mercy
take care of our little family.
Let us kneel down
and unite in a heartfelt prayer.
May God our father in his mercy
take care of our little family
and bless us and keep us from evil
all the days of our life.
God give me strength
to be a guardian and a worthy example
to these little fatherless ones.
Give me strength as well
to be a support
to this lonely young woman.
In the 15th century,
when this house was built,
they didn't bother much about comfort.
My predecessors kept it all as it was,
and I follow the tradition.
These old rooms have
an imperishable beauty.
We should be grateful that we may live
in an atmosphere of purity and austerity.
Ah, here come my mother and sister.
Welcome Mrs. Ekdahl.
Thank you.
This is my sister Henrietta.
- Welcome to the Bishop's palace.
- Thank you.
Come and say hello, children.
This is Mrs. Tander,
our capable cook,
who's been with our family
for 30 years.
This is my future wife,
Mrs. Emilie Ekdahl.
Good day, Mrs. Ekdahl. Welcome.
These are our capable helpers:
Karna, Selma and little Justina.
Now we'll go see my aunt,
who, alas, is sick and bedridden.
How are you today, aunt Elsa?
We have a visitor.
Don't be afraid, children.
Come and say hello.
My future wife, Mrs. Emilie Ekdahl,
the famous actress.
Hello, miss Bergius.
The children have fallen asleep.
It's late and we must go home.
- Not yet.
- What is it, Edvard?
I have a wish.
A single wish, but an important one.
You may change your mind
if you find it impossible.
Tell me your wish.
I want you to come to my house
without possessions.
What do you mean?
I want you to leave your home...
your clothes, jewels, furniture...
your valuables...
your friends, habits and thoughts.
I want you to leave
your former life entirely.
Am I to come naked?
I'm serious, my dear.
I want you to come
to your new life as if newly born.
- And the children?
- The children also.
- Their toys, dolls, books -
- Nothing.
- I must talk to them.
- It's your decision.
I can decide for myself,
but not for the children.
I must ask them.
They must sacrifice something
for their mother's happiness.
You're angry.
Kiss me.
I'm not angry, not in the least.
I'll win them over.
Think it over, Emilie.
I've already thought it over.
For me it's not hard
to grant your wish.
I've never cared for anything
very seriously.
I've sometimes wondered
if there wasn't something
very wrong with my feelings.
I couldn't understand
why nothing really hurt...
why I never felt really happy.
I know now that
the crucial moment has come.
I know that we'll hurt each other,
but I'm not afraid.
I also know that we will
make each other happy.
And I sometimes weep from fear,
because time is so short,
the days pass so quickly,
and nothing lasts forever.
Kiss me, now,
and hold me in your arms,
as only you can.
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-