-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-
From where did you bring him.
outside from the Frent
raod railway-station.
Frent road
He was fainted but sometimes
he come to his senses.
Does he tell his name or anything?
Hari Lal!
What is your father`s name?
Jsut try...
Bapoo..
Bapoo...
Kastoor!
What do you do at the press?
Do you play Holi over there?
(Holi=lndian ceramonial`s).
Holi? No way, Black lnk, hard
work and hot climate is there...
And yes, there is a
letter from Raj Kott.
Hari`s letter How is he?
He is fine and enjoying.
We woundn`t leave him alon at Raj Kott.
l was on the same string
but you wanted that he
would stay there and learn
in his native language.
that is not possible there ...
Why want to go school for study
they got same in this village
hmm.. here you childs come
ManeLal, Raamdaas, Devdas
there are three your trained childs.
all the day the work,
then look after the animals
look after sick.. or if they
got free time then they sing
What will happen with our childs.
every time just tension
all the child go school
for study then why not ours.
Hard working , Responsibility , Sincarety..
these are not learning from school.
School just a books study
not to make children sincare
l know that because l hear that a lot
Hari Lal want to marry.
hmm.. he just want to tell
us not to takes permission
he is smart l know you wont agree
but in this younger age Why he hurry.
Why?
we married when we was 13
years and you are in hurry.
l am regret yet What?
that was our parients mistake
they won`t think our age.
you Choose those
you make them engaged year ago.
till when will you wait for them.
kastoor.. you know my decision
well.. if he want to marry
without my permision.. so marry.
but as a father.. l have to forgot him..
Smile don`t move..
Bapoo is not forgot
you He is engry on you
l dont understand
l want to study become Big Man like him
just see his good habbbits
don`t think what he is talking
when he will see your Hard working and
you ability so he will ignore everything
then these all will meanless..
l wanna be with you...
for this you have a lot of
time minimum five months.
always be with him.
longness will end itself.
as soon as l will take you in africa
don`t think about itjust
study and become Bigman.
and Mother and Father
proud on your and me too.
l will wait for you.
Hari Bhai.. Driver beocme engry
he want to take othere passenger.
Wait!
Read it ..
Will write letter l will wait for you.
Can l get somthing for you
No. nothing Sitdown
you are not go to get Hari.
You tell you will go
She is looking for you
Kastoor l am.. l have to do a lot.
but time is short
is we... is your family
dont make you to do that..
l am happy
Hari Lal is back
l am really missing him..
he is our nation father
l know he is our father
we need your father name
to admit you in hospital
we will not write Bapoo
as your father name..
Bapoo
Don`t be afraid on this matter
today we again got chance to enjoy..
once again they put into
jail Barister Ghandi.
l am proud of my father..
what is this nonsence.. that a
barister who obey british rules.
who doing work honestly
in the society of british.
they told them to
give the finger prints.
and you know Why? because the color
of his face and body is not white
lf your color is like this
or like this
or between them
so then you will not count as humen.
you have to put in your boundry..
if you need to go in the boundry
of these man. who got that color.
so you have to got the entry pass..
if you will enter without entry
pass so they will put you in jail..
My father told that l will not take the
pass or not give you the finger prints.
What you want to do.. you do..
what else make my face
or body color into blood
or kill me..
for fight with cruel..
for obey humenity rule
Adam, Easa, Paigember Muhammad s.w.,
budh, mahavir like those l got the force.
we will not obey that rules..
we will burn that registration permit.
we are given them warning
they utilized their
all force against us..
that law is to distroy and makes
poor our indian`s business men.
for make indian`s poor and hungry.
We have to stop them
Hari l want you to first
who break this rules.
so other people follow you.
you takes a lot of time
will your daugher Rami
will forget you face.
me just thinking about
you and Rami all the time
you choose the track
become as litter Ghandi.
your thinking..
that is most important then your family.
l will go England if bapoo want..
to become Barister
and our company name is Ghandi
or Ghandi`s Aternies at Law
but at once l think leave that all
and be with my family.
we will not come between
you and your fight
What the matter?
we are going back to Hindustan
we got the family..
l know you will become free soon
but the ship will never wait..
my wife leaving me and going to Hindustan
and no one can takes my permission..
who takes decision
time..
Bapoo
they need you here
to fight with cruel and to help Bapoo..
if you missing us to much
then come to Hindustan Via Ship
that`s not harmfull..
l heard your friend alload scholarship to
child for study in England become Barister..
he is good man he has
been always with us..
Whenever Andolan needs
money they give us..
lf they wasn`t with us l dont
know what will happend with us..
and Scholarship that is the problem..
they told that scholarship
only for Ghandi`s family.
then he stand on it but l tell him.
What? Pram Bhai this is the gift for me.
l won`t accept this
at last.. he except
scholarship is for
anyone from the village..
yes.. Who is the one
need it l will decide it
Who is this One.. Chagan
Lal.. l think he is the one.
My Brother`s Son
l think he is the one of he start
his carrier with my underkind.
ok l am okay.
You come back its too much for me..
they take me
you are lndependent Hari!
What the independent is this ?
Which you decide the rules..
and to scale the boundries..
my independance is
only to obey your rule..
my destiny will only follow your rules..
Bapoo l want to study
and to become Barister..
want to become Little Ghandi..
you just cuts my wings..
and you want me to fly..
now l can`t breath because of your rules
l want to breath..
Here the fight begin..
fight for taking of rights..
to bring Justice against Cruelty
l need you to help me..
l am not in.
l will get my way myself
l will get my way..
Please leave me alone..
What do you want to do?
l want to back to my family.
l miss them..
l know that.
Want to study more, earn money myself
or if you failed
what will lost to struggle Bapoo!
Child! What will l do
so you can live here.
Do me a favour ?
l you think your father made a mistake
so please forgive me
Forgive me.
Hari Bhai! l got all your
marks. English, French too good
but
Jeevan you should go home.
Enough of studies.
l can`t do it anymore.
Whenever l fail.
lt becomes Bapu`s victory.
How nice! traveling so peacfully.
l`ll be disturbed.
Your lndian friends aren`t
aware of new changes.
Next time we`ll infrom them.
Only third class travling. Right?
Greetings. Greetings.
Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi.
Are you the barister
- Gandhi of southafrica?
What a Luck of mine?
l`m greatfull that l met you.
Who are you?
He`s my son.
But sir his name is not
- in the list.
there`s been a mistake. You can fine me.
Sir please don`t embaress
me. Box is empty anyway.
that much l can do
- for you sir.
You are a public servent.
lt is your duty not to do so
- for me or someone else.
l can`t accept that.
Ok sir l`ll be back for fine
once l check other passengers.
these are the Letters, list
of names and their addresses.
l`ve replied to them.
and this your appointment
list for the next two weeks.
How`s Gulab feeling in Ahmedabad?
Very Good.
Son you came, lived with
us You managed everything.
What would`ve happened
lf Hari wasn`t here.
Bapu since last few months
l`m having financial problems.
But l send money to you each month.
Yes Bapu. But it`s not enough.
then why are you up for studies.
You`ve failed three times already.
What will you do with
- degree and certificate?
Bapu l want to do bussiness.
lf you can invest money for me...
l don`t have any money
- of my own.
l donate those money which
l earn in South Africa
l won`t get cradit in my life
Shell we mortgage House of Ghandi`s
Family in Raajkot and get the money
l had already clear my
all dues with my brothers
My Bristry, your education, your marriage and all
the other expences. so there is nothing on hand
so l transfer all my
property to my brothers.
You just have to take our advise
now you are elder you have to
takes reponsibilites of your family
you should be yourself Do Job.
Speaking Gujrati..
Sister it is become too
expenses it wont be stop
Shardha! how can you menage your expences
in 30 rupees which comes from Bapoo
Food, Child Study expences, My Husband`s
expences l dont understand how can l manage.
Why are rotate them,
come to point.. tell
her l am not educated.
tell him l am Jobless
let her know because l have
to close this chapter today.
Let he know..
Please Stop.. everyone is lisning
today all the world will hear..
Sanu Bhai.. Gaesh Bhai
Ausha Sister.. Lisen to me
l am unworthy son of Gandhi. What.
l am unworthy son of Gandhi.
Look at this my rental House.
this is becuase of my father.
and l always fail in paper.
and when l walked from this street
so you all think how`s is
Gandhi and here its son.
that Gandhi`s Stamp is on my
forehead. No one will let me forget.
he is greatest father all
over the world. he is..
but now l dont want to be his son.
without degree Who will give me Job.
and without Job l am nothing.
every morning when l wake up as upset
and at night l close my
eyes because of anger.
l know Bapoo. l wont be your good son.
you are the responsible of what l am.
Bapoo! l was never like this at all.
Bapoo! forgive me if hurt
you to read this letter.
but my hands are shaking.
l dont have any other way.
your and only your Hari Lal.
Ghulab.. Yes. l invite my
friend of my company on lunch.
how much. three
oh! with their wife`s they are Six.
Mannu.. my sweeto..
Look you all new clothes
that`s for you all.
Ghulab one good news. What?
first give me a cup of tea.
Rami.. Let make them all ready for Pray.
Good news is Seth Nauranth Jee is
happy with my work and make me cahsier.
Bapoo! will become
happy to hear this news
Nauranth Das will Jee tell him.
now we have to think
about Rami`s Future.
we will have to marry her. we
should save the money for him marry.
girls become elder so fast. Yes l know.
and you also start to save
money for Kanti`s Study.
l want him to complete
his studies in england.
Whatever he want to
study lt is his choice.
put it there.
there
What is this all?
imported costly Fabrics.
made in england.
lmported Fabric. What do you tell Bapoo
where did you get that much money?
Cradit. People invest the money.
Why are you doing this.
Business. nothing is wrong in business.
they need to return their money with
intrest. and l will give them much better
l will not force them.
ls anything wrong then
How can l made a mistake.
Look at this Fabric. Check the quality.
Stock of this fabric will be sold early
if purchaser know there is the stock.
hay l am saying empty the Caboard
We will need to save money.
that is not right what you are doing
trust me Ghulab.
l got only one chance to stand on myself
l will not cheat anyone
unless l am the Son of Gandhi.
l do a lot of effert for this
just be with me.
ok. Let be ready for pray.
Sorry l am late
3 minutes is not late
1 second is too late.
what is going on.
when Ghandi Jee is with
me then what can l think.
l am doing stuggle..
Come in Hostel and live
everything is all right
l make you in trouble.
What are you talking
about trouble. you help me.
you give him Job. look after him
trust him but he birate
you of 30,000 Ruppes
Do not trust him. let him fire.
Gandhi Jee.. l don`t wanna say that.
you should sue on him. l am out of
practice otherwise l will sue him
He is young, he made
mistake.. forgive him.
then. after all he is your son.
until when? we will
save our childs mistakes.
Which type of society we want to make.
if you respect me then sue on him
let the Court will take decision and if Hari
Lal except the punishment so that his dignety.
and mine respect too.
now come on l will teach you today.
Knock Knock..
Hari Lal!
Hari Lal! He is not at home.
you lying me from 3
days l m seeking for him.
from purband to kalculta
l am seeking for him.
he is not come back yet.
l am poor man on the
name of Gandi l trust you.
but you haven`t ashmed. you are not
doing fair by taking name of Gandhi.
Ghulab!
its me Ghulab.
telegram.
l have lot of work to do l
have to drop other letters.
so you should read yourself drop there.
your Son Shanti dead.
your wife`s is so sick.
come soon.
Hari Lal!
Hari My child!
come on with me in
hostel. forget all the past
your children needs you.
me you mother your children in
hostel. we all live together.
come on.
here he
your child come Bapoo.
what happen you seems happy.
huh!
come on child
come on Child you have
to sing a song on stage.
Rasik Lal, Hare Lal.
mohan das karam chand Gandhi.
he got a goat. he got a goat.
Amazing! You are here already.
Mr. Satya Pal l can`t let
go any Godrej customer.
- because of the product shortage.
Mr. Hari this is enough.
Why do you worry so much? Mr. Satya Pal
You are our special customer.
You don`t worry at all.
l`ve talked to the company.
they`ll extend your credit limit.
and they`ll also give
you special discount.
Mr. Satya Pal Last month balance?
Next week.
Sure? Sure.
l`ll go now. thank you.
Mahadev Brother Greetings. Greetings.
Bapu You`re here!
l waited for you. You
didn`t come so l came here.
How`s mother? Like always.
and kids?
they`re fine. they miss you so much.
Once l save some money.
l`ll bring them here.
l`ll ask mother to come live with me.
lf you`ll call me l`ll
come with them once more.
Are those south Africa pictures?
Hari you have very nice books.
l tried to learn on my
own as much as l could.
Mahadev remember l told you.
My HariLal was the first revolutionist
who used a pen as a weapon
for the rights of lndians.
You were my brave soldier.
they`re old memories.
lt`s been a long time.
Mahadev!
Bapu this is calcutta. these
people won`t understand.
You`ll have to speak.
l am my son`s guest.
today l am here to spend
the night at his home.
Can you please let me spend
sometime with him in peace.
whole crowd: Yes
Long Live. Mahatma Gandhi
Hari. History is calling you again.
Come join us in our revolution.
to do what?
Fight for our country.
You have your whole
life to fight with me.
But it`s probably the last
chance to fight for the country.
Go tell the English government.
Hang us.
Put us in the jail.
But they`ll only get hatred
from our side. Nothing else.
this British government
is the Devil`s Government.
People who love God. How
can they be with the Devil?
Can they?
British government has
been doing horrible things.
And if they won`t apologize
to God and to this country.
then it`ll be destroyed.
And l also want to say this...
lf they don`t apologize
lt is our duty. that we
lndians should destroy it.
We are great full that you are with us.
We were thinking who
else besides Gandhi.
lt is great that you are here.
l thank you. l didn`t even
- have any other place to live.
Leave all that.
We paid the balance
rent to your landlord.
Now you sleep peacefully in your house.
thank you so much.
Mr. Hari l want to give
- you an advise.
think about you children.
Children`s responsibility is important
same as the fighting for wisdom.
l know. but what can i do?
Either l am in the Jail
or rallying on the streets.
you are right. You need us.
that is why l`ve called this meeting.
For your help we`ve created an
organization of repected people.
We will run a
- company under your name.
We`ll make factory.
We`ll market it`s shares.
We`ll gather money, earn profit.
Meaning we`ll secure your future.
But who`ll buy
- shares of my company?
neither any one in my
family is in bussiness.
Neither l am a bussiness son.
Nothing is bigger than Gandhi
- in this country.
You can`t use my Father`s name.
Leave him. He`s not able
to make you understand.
We`ll only use your name.
Hari Lal Mohandas Gandhi.
Look your making all this confusing.
Mr. Hari l`ll explain to you.
lt`s straight and subtle.
You people who fight for wisdom
- are very emotional.
But real world is very confusing.
But the timing is perfect.
People call you Gandhi.
Only use this name.
Now you don`t need to ask
- your father for anything.
But l`ve never done such thing.
You just leave everything to me.
l`ll make everything allright.
Whenever you feel there
is something wrong.
You can leave all this.
No thank you. l quit all this.
Mr. Hari you have this
life to live it the fullest.
l know you have a name
- in the society.
But who`s watching here. Cheers.
lt`ll be our pleasure.
Have you found out anything
- about his relatives.
No.
l`ve put all my life savings in
- Hari Brother`s company.
Now there is no company
- nor Hari Brother.
they`re all gone.
they showed me your picture.
thats why i gave them all
- the money.
At that time you were everything
- for me.
Now l am destroyed.
Where should l go?
What should l do Bapu?
Harilal is my eldest son, But
we have had our differences.
He doesn`t believe in my methods.
and He shows that in public.
lf he changes his mind.
l will welcome him back.
Everyone has a limit and dignity.
lf Harilal has any dignity left,
He`ll pay back to people.
lt is a warning to those people
who do bussiness over big names.
lt`s not necessery that
- good people have good children.
Next time whenever
- you do bussiness with him.
Please do remember,
that l don`t have
- any kind of relation with him.
Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi.
You all should work open hearted
- to end racism.
Will you repeat with me
- some lines of Kanhaiya Lal Dixit.
temple, Mosque and Church.
Only this should be the religion.
one for all of us.
Vande Matram
Long Live Mahatma Gandhi.
We won`t let any low race in
our temples. till the end of us.
Hindu Society will never tolarate this.
Mr. Gandhi tell us
- clearly about your issue of racism.
Racism is a bad
- thing in human society.
Until racism is present
in hindu society.
We can never become a
part of the real world.
Hari!
How much are people taking part in
your collectings of racism donation.
Look l`m travling in the whole
- country with a bowl.
But sadly l think heart
- of city people have become smaller.
lf you ask them for money
- for the good of society and country.
they make new excuses for that.
And on otherside our Village People.
Even after having less of it.
they`re ready to give all of it.
Now l believe
- that lndia have it`s day in it`s Village.
l`m feeding you.
No matter how old you are.
You`ll always be child for me.
Where were you Hari
- for so many days?
We looked every where for you.
Look. l want to say one thing clearly.
Racism should be ripped from the root.
And Hindu, Muslim should be one
to bring Wisdom to this country.
and for this l am ready to
- give my life if neccesery.
Long Live. Mahatma Gandhi.
Wow. lt`s a miracle.
Mother. God finally
anwered your prayers.
Harilal is here.
Do you know Hari?
Your Mothers eyes were looking
for you on every Railway Stations.
Ask her?
Enough. We won`t tolarate this anymore.
Don`t push us anymore
Gandhi enough is enough.
l read your statement
- in a newspaper.
that you are converting
into a Christian.
they printed the wrong statement.
But yes l repect
- the brotherhood of Christains.
l`ve also been told that
you`ve taken money from people.
On a High lntrus. How
will you pay them back?
l don`t know Bapu.
and l don`t even care.
When did come back?
lt`s a very small issue.
lt is very good that you`ve come here.
We`ve paid all of your debts.
We can`t watch you in this condition.
Now you don`t need to
hide your face from public.
Really. lt`s a shame. that
you had to bare all this.
thank You very much.
Don`t be formal Hari Brother.
Make yourself at home.
Now you`ve become a
- family member.
Hindu And Muslim.
They are my both eyes.
They are examines our faith.
Those few peoples could
not ruin our traditions.
Harilal is going to sale his soul.
And He sold his body for
little bit of pleasures.
Now it`s the resoponibility
of his new friends.
To keep him away from this hell.
Harilal And Abdullah,
They both have same goal. The same goal.
The real prayer of his God.
And lf Harilal get his ambam
ambitions to walk through lslam,
Then lt`s his choice to keep
his name Harilal or Abdullah.
We will always love him.
Just Stay here and don`t be afraid.
l wil show you the whole city.
Abdullah you just accelerate the
horse l am gonna race with you.
Come on get up, Get
up. Where you taking us?
Where you taking my friend?
Come down.
Come down but why?
lnsist me like, Please come down.
Do you know Mahatma Gandhi?
Yes everyone knows him.
He`s my father. So you
are the son of Mr. Gandhi.
No, He is my father. Oh yeah.
But l just announced in the meeting.
That He and Ba must have
to change their Religion.
You can also change you
religion to follow my lead.
l will recommend you.
Just Because you calling
your self Mr.Gandhi`s son.
We will provide you
a good place to sleep.
That`s good. Get him into the car.
Which Car? Why into the car?
Brother Abdullah, You are safe
just because of Gandhi`s name.
That`s why you are getting
your breakfast here.
You ashamed our selves.
You are getting wrong our hosting.
lt`s a limit.
Greetings.
You are so changed.
While i read any news paper.
Hearing about you.
l don`t understand.
ls that my son what they talking about?
Where we hide our selves?
What we should say to your childs?
Bapu is still powerful.
He could hear.
But what should l do?
l am a Mother, l can`t through you away.
l can call you my own.
Harilal we ain`t do
anything wrong with you.
Then we have to feel so
guilty? Why you abusing us?
Abusing our religion.
You have to right to say
anything anything you want to do.
But as a mother i can
only beg you for mercy.
Please forgive us.
ln this old age we
can`t endure it anymore.
l am so tired.
l am so tired. l loss.
With the bless of God l
am becoming Hindu again.
Where are u going?
Don`t know.
l give you that money for
your medicines and you,
Listen i appoints here
to look after your self.
Wine is my Medicine.
My pain too, l tried many
time to change my future.
Change my clothes too.
But my past did not stop to followed me.
My history is too long.
Open up man.
l am not gonna allow you to walk alone.
How long you`re gonna walk with me?
l am so far from you.
Harry? Ba.
Look what l bring for you.
Harilal. What you bring for me?
Nothing. lt`s just for my Ba.
lt`s all Long live Mahatma
Gandhi just because for my Ba.
l knew it.
Will you come with us?
No, l just came here to meet my Ba.
Where did you find it?
l told him that lt`s for my Ba, He
gave me and did not ask for money.
lf you won`t eat it
then return it to me.
No, l must eat it.
Only you can eat it, l
only brings it for you.
l am giving you a poetry.
You just put it in your heart
and And always keep it with you.
The poetry is, Do or Die.
We will free lndia or we
will die to keep trying.
Today, from this moment, You all people.
You are a man or woman you
just suppose your self free.
Live like free not a servant
of any western country.
This is a Revolution.
Keep lndia on God`s faith.
Leave the lndia Do or Die.
How large is our country? Why?
You don`t know? Tell me, tell me.
lt`s too large. How it is?
l shown you the earth shape in
that class l also shown you Europe.
Calculate the whole europe and
also take some little states.
And how many English Men in lndia?
Three Hundred Thousand. May
be Some Ten Thousand more.
Then Why that Rao
wants us to leave lndia?
lndia is very large country
they can live with us.
l just want that English
has just stops to rule us.
And lf they can do that we
don`t need to fight with them.
That`s right.
You must tell them. l would.
l can`t walk with you
anymore. l am tired.
You must go alone from tomorrow.
Harry! Where you`ve been?
Ba l want to come here to meet
you but they did not allow me.
Who stops you?
Just because He is poor.
My all sons came here. He`s also my son.
No Mom, l must sit here.
Come here.
l don`t want you to go
anywhere, You must live here.
Are you drunk?
You came here to meet
me while you drunk!
l came here to meet you l
ain`t drunk. Babu, He drunk.
Don`t you ashame your self?
l came here to meet
you. Get lost from here.
Bapu, Ba`s calling you.
Where is Hari?
He`ll be back.
Who will look after him when l died?
Promise me that you will look after him.
He is not a bad guy. He have a bad luck.
Where is my Sari? Which one?
That one who gifted me by you.
Promise me that you have to
wear me that Sari when l died.
Where did you hide?
Come on. Come on kill me.
l am not so long.
At least you can save me from Monsters.
Hindu calls me Traitor. And
muslims are praying for my death.
But listen one thing.
Chop me in the pieces.
But l won`t allow my country in pieces.
Could you find my Harilal? Why, Bapu?
l am missing him a lot since few days.
lt`s hard to find him
but l will try my best.
lf he would here with me then
l can die easily in his arms.
Do you know what is
great loss of my life?
Two people, l can`t understand
them my feelings in my whole life.
One of my friend, Mohammad Ali Jinnah,
And Other One is my own son Harilal.
We are closing our shop. He`s dead.
My Bapu is dead, l don`t have anymore.
l don`t need your money.
These cowards shots the
Bapu. They shoot him.
Bapu has gone. My Bapu has gone.
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-