PREVIOUSLY,
ON "WICKED CITY"...
I'VE NEVER FELT CLOSER
TO ANYONE.
BABY, YOU USED TO LOVE GETTING
DOWN ON YOUR KNEES FOR ME.
GET OUT OF MY HOUSE.
[ BANG ON WINDOW ]
THE COPS KNEW WHERE
AND WHEN TO HIT US.
I'M NOT A RAT.
IT'S TIME
TO CUT LOOSE ENDS.
[ GUNSHOT ]
LET'S SEE IF YOU
CAN DO BETTER.
THE VICTIMS THAT HE TARGETS,
THE WAY HE KILLS THEM.
HE'S KILLING HIS MOTHER,
OVER AND OVER AGAIN.
Man: IT'S 5:30 A.M.
IN LOS ANGELES,
AND ALREADY,
78 DEGREES OUTSIDE.
LOOKS LIKE TODAY'S GONNA BE
THE HOTTEST DAY OF THE YEAR.
[ SIREN WAILS IN DISTANCE ]
YOU HAVE TO GO.
I DO?
MM-HMM.
I'VE GOT TO GET TO WORK.
REALLY?
YOU GOT THE EARLY SHIFT
TODAY, HUH?
OH, I GOT EVERY SHIFT
NOW THAT BUCKET'S...
GONE.
GRAHAM HAS ME WORKING AT ENZO'S
ON THE STRIP --
THAT NEW CLUB?
FANCY.
GUESS THAT'S ONE WAY TO KEEP
PEOPLE WORKING HARD --
BLOW THEIR CO-WORKERS'
BRAINS OUT.
WELL, DON'T WORRY.
I'M GONNA HAVE GRAHAM
BEHIND BARS IN NO TIME --
AND HIS BOSS.
I HAVE NO DOUBT.
SO YOU'LL KEEP YOUR EYES OPEN
FOR BUYERS WITH FANCY CARS?
LET ME KNOW
IF SOMETHING POPS UP?
YOU THINK THAT'S THE KEY?
THE KILLER DRIVES
DIFFERENT HIGH-END CARS?
NOW IF I CAN FIGURE OUT WHY,
IT MIGHT JUST GET ME SOMETHING.
WELL, WE KNOW HE'S PROBABLY
STEALING THEM,
'CAUSE A GUY LIKE THIS
ISN'T BUYING THEM.
YEAH, BUT WH-WHY
IS HE USING THEM --
ALL THOSE DIFFERENT CARS?
IT'S NOT TO BLEND IN.
THEY'RE VINTAGE.
PEOPLE NOTICE.
YEAH, THAT'S WEIRD.
SOMEONE LIKE THIS PROBABLY
WOULDN'T WANT TO BRING
ATTENTION TO HIMSELF.
RIGHT.
AND HE HASN'T --
NOT SINCE HE WAS ABOUT
9 YEARS OLD.
CHECK THIS OUT.
THIS IS THE ONLY VISUAL
I HAVE ON HIM.
THAT'S THE KILLER?
CUTE KID, HUH?
I WONDER IF HE KNEW
WHAT HE'D BECOME...
IF HE FELT THE DARKNESS.
[ SIGHS ]
I KNEW I WANTED
TO BE A COP.
YEAH? ME TOO.
I USED TO WEAR MY BROTHER'S
TOY GUN AND HOLSTER EVERYWHERE.
[ BOTH CHUCKLE ]
I WOULD HAVE LOVED TO SEE YOU
AS A LITTLE GIRL.
WELL, I WOULD'VE
KICKED YOUR ASS.
YEAH?
OH, YEAH.
ALL RIGHT,
GET OUT OF HERE.
WE BOTH GOT WORK.
Betty: BUT I NEVER
WANT YOU TO LEAVE.
BUT I HAVE TO.
THESE CARS WON'T
REUPHOLSTER THEMSELVES.
I WISH THEY DID.
I'M SO HAPPY WITH YOU.
I FEEL SO SAFE.
AND YOU ARE.
BUT I CAN'T ALWAYS BE THERE,
YOU KNOW?
OF COURSE.
I GOT YOU SOMETHING.
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-
SAFETY FIRST.
HONEY, I LOVE IT.
AH, YES.
YOU WANT ME TO CUBE YOU,
McCLAREN?
YEAH, RIGHT.
DIVER,
WE'RE THE FOURTH ESTATE.
A LITTLE PROFESSIONALISM?
[ DOOR OPENS ]
HEY.
I GOT SOMETHING FOR YOU --
THE HOLLYWOOD SLAYER AS A KID.
SO? WHY'D YOU
BRING IT TO US?
FIRST NAME'S COOPER.
SHOULD BE ABOUT
28, 29 YEARS OLD RIGHT NOW.
HE LOOKS SO SWEET.
YOU TWO ARE GONNA RUN A STORY
ON BABY SLAYER THERE.
"ARE MONSTERS BORN
OR MADE OR..."
ALL THAT CRAP YOU DO.
"ALL THAT CRAP."
WITH THE PICTURE FRONT
AND CENTER, PLUS THE TIP LINE,
WE'RE HOPING SOMEBODY
RECOGNIZES HIM.
SO CAN I COUNT
ON YOU GUYS?
NO.
SURE.
WE'RE HALFWAY THERE.
YOU WANT TO LET THE COPS FORCE
US INTO WRITING A PIECE?
IT'S A HUGE SCOOP.
YOU JUST HATE JACK ROTH.
I DON'T HATE HIM.
JUST THAT DUDLEY DO-RIGHT
WON'T PLAY --
ALL TAKE, NO GIVE.
HEY, HEY.
EXCUSE ME.
HOW ABOUT I
TAKE YOU DOWNTOWN?
JACKASS.
FINE, BUT I WANT
SOMETHING IN RETURN.
GETTING GREEDY, MAN.
I'VE BEEN LOOKING FOR BUCKET,
THAT GUY YOU POPPED A WEEK AGO.
DUDE'S BEEN MISSING
EVER SINCE.
SINCE WHEN DO YOU CARE
ABOUT DRUG DEALERS?
SINCE THE KILLER CARES.
THE HOLLYWOOD SLAYER PLANTS
"FLY BRAND" COKE ON HIS VICTIMS.
THAT'S WHAT BUCKET SELLS.
AT LEAST THAT'S WHAT
I'VE BEEN TOLD, ANYWAY.
NOW, THAT'S FOR CALLING
MY WORK "CRAP," BROTHER.
YOU GAVE HIM THAT?
I HAD TO TRADE.
I MEAN, HOW DO YOU THINK WE
FOUND BUCKET IN THE FIRST PLACE?
JUST MAKE SURE THE PHOTO
RUNS FRONT AND CENTER.
YES, SIR.
LET ME SEE THAT.
HI, THERE.
HI.
MAN, NICE WHEELS, HUH?
LOOKS EXPENSIVE.
SURE.
JIMMY LOVETT.
UH, NEIGHBOR.
YOU LIVE AROUND HERE?
NO, I'M JUST,
UH, VISITING.
EXCUSE ME.
OH!
[ LAUGHS ]
[ ENGINE TURNS OVER ]
SEE YA.
YEAH, I'LL SEE YA.
♪♪
[ INDISTINCT TALKING ]
HEY, BETTY.
[ SIGHS ]
WHAT A NICE SURPRISE.
IS IT REALLY?
Kent: HI, THERE.
HI.
HEY, BABE.
JIMMY, IT'S NICE
TO SEE YOU AGAIN.
YOU'VE MET.
YEAH.
THAT'S NICE.
JIMMY IS...HERE
WITH HIS KIDS.
OH.
YEAH, OVER THERE.
YEAH,
LITTLE ONE'S A REAL WIMP.
YEAH, WELL, MOST CHILDREN
MODEL THEIR BEHAVIOR
ON THE SAME-SEX PARENT.
I GOT TO GET THESE OUT OF
THE SUN BEFORE THEY MELT.
MM, SEE YA.
SO THAT'S YOUR NEW
BOYFRIEND, HUH?
UM, IT'S NONE
OF YOUR BUSINESS.
WELL, I THINK IT IS.
OUR KIDS PLAY TOGETHER.
I'M GUESSING HE'S GONNA
BE AROUND A LOT.
YOU KNOW, WE DON'T WANT A BAD
ELEMENT IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
WHAT ARE YOU SAYING?
OH, COME ON.
LIKE YOU DIDN'T KNOW.
DIFFERENT CARS EVERY DAY?
THAT JAG, THE FURY,
THE HOURS HE KEEPS.
WHOO! [ LAUGHS ]
YEAH, IT TOOK ME A WHILE,
BUT I FINALLY FIGURED IT OUT.
YOUR HUNK
IS A DRUG DEALER.
[ LAUGHS ]
HE'S A DRUG DEALER?
YEAH.
HMM.
AND I CAN'T HAVE
NO DOPE PUSHER
COMING INTO
THIS NEIGHBORHOOD.
SO I'M ASKING RON
TO LOOK INTO IT.
RON?
MY COUSIN IN THE LAPD.
YOU CALLED THE POLICE?
MM-HMM.
RON'LL LOOK AT KENT HARD.
EVERYTHING --
HIS WORK, HIS HOME.
MAN HAS SECRETS.
THEY GOT A WAY
OF COMING OUT.
JIMMY, KENT IS NOT
A DRUG DEALER.
MAYBE THAT'S WHAT
HE'S TELLING YOU,
BUT DO YOU THINK THE
POLICE WILL BELIEVE
YOU DIDN'T REALLY KNOW?
PROBABLY NOT.
W-- SHOOT.
I WONDER IF THEY'LL TAKE
YOUR KIDS STRAIGHT AWAY
OR WILL THEY GIVE YOU
A HEARING OR SOMETHING.
NO ONE'S TAKING
MY KIDS ANYWHERE.
KENT'S DIRTY --
THEY'D BE STUPID
NOT TO LOOK AT
THE GIRLFRIEND, RIGHT?
MAYBE ARREST HER,
GET HER TO TESTIFY.
THAT'S WHEN CHILD SERVICES
SWOOPS IN.
[ LAUGHING ]
WHOOP!
BUT HEY, LOOK.
I JUST WANTED TO WARN YOU,
'CAUSE I'M ALWAYS
LOOKING OUT FOR YOU.
'CAUSE THAT'S WHAT FRIENDS
ARE FOR.
YOU KNOW WHAT ELSE
FRIENDS ARE FOR?
JUST BEING SWEET
TO EACH OTHER.
MMM.
[ INHALES DEEPLY ]
ONE NIGHT OF FUN, BETTY...
THEN I'LL LEAVE YOU
AND YOUR BOYFRIEND ALONE.
I'LL TELL YOUR WIFE.
[ LAUGHS ]
IT WOULDN'T BE
THE FIRST TIME.
MM.
SO TONIGHT,
AROUND 6:00...
MY PLACE.
WIFE'LL BE AT WORK.
[ MOANS ]
[ SMOOCHES ]
HERE'S THE PAPER
YOU LIKE.
THANKS, DAVE.
I DON'T KNOW WHY YOU LIKE
LOOKING AT ALL THAT GORE
WHEN THE NEW PLAYBOY
JUST CAME OUT.
FIND THIS WORLD
INTRIGUING.
SO, UH,
DIFFERENT FROM OURS.
GUYS, WHOA.
♪♪
[ PHONE RINGS ]
Paco: HEY, JACK, SOME CHICK
IN THE VALLEY
IS CLAIMING SHE KNOWS
YOUR GUY COOPER.
SO THIS IS THE COOPER
THAT YOU KNEW IN JUNIOR HIGH.
DO YOU THINK THE NEWS STATIONS
WANT TO TALK TO ME TOO?
MA'AM, THE PHOTO.
YEAH, YEAH.
THAT'S COOPER FLYNN.
"FLYNN".
YOU SURE ABOUT THAT?
DO YOU WANT TO HEAR
THE STORY OR NOT?
OF COURSE I'M SURE.
I HAD TO SIT ACROSS
THE KITCHEN TABLE
FROM HIS GEEKY FACE
FOR LIKE A MONTH.
HE TUTORED ME
IN SCIENCE CLASS.
OKAY, SO COOPER
WAS A SMART KID?
IF BY SMART
YOU MEAN "LOSER," YES.
I WAS A FINALIST
AT THE LOS ANGELES
CHEERLEADER CHAMPIONSHIP
IN SEVENTH GRADE.
I HAD OTHER THINGS GOING ON
BESIDES THE PERIODIC TABLE,
YOU KNOW?
I BET YOU WERE AMAZING.
I STILL AM.
NOW, YOU SAY THAT HE TUTORED YOU
AT HIS HOUSE.
YEP.
WHAT DO YOU REMEMBER
ABOUT THAT?
HIS GRANDFATHER SMELLED LIKE
PEE AND MOTHBALLS.
AND COOPER BUILT
THOSE STUPID MODEL CARS.
[ CHUCKLES ]
FINALLY, A REAL LEAD.
YEAH.
FLYNN --
AN ACTUAL LAST NAME.
OKAY, I'LL PUT
BUKOWSKI ON IT --
SEE IF WE CAN GET A SOCIAL
OR BIRTH CERTIFICATE.
AND DON'T FORGET,
WE NOW KNOW
HE WAS A LOSER
WHO BUILT MODEL CARS.
YOU KNOW, THERE'S
NOTHING WRONG WITH BUILDING
MODEL CARS, OKAY?
IT PROMOTES
DISCIPLINE, FOCUS.
GIVE ME BUKOWSKI, ASAP.
Man: YES, SIR.
YOU GET A MESSAGE
FROM DIVER...
HOPING YOU'LL GIVE HIM ANOTHER
VALUABLE PIECE OF EVIDENCE?
YOU KNOW, WE WOULD'VE NEVER
FOUND BUCKET
HAD IT NOT BEEN
FOR THAT TRADE.
REMEMBER THAT.
YEAH, WELL, DIVER'S LOOKING
FOR A DEAD MAN.
YOU KNOW,
GRAHAM OFFED HIM...
RIGHT IN FRONT OF DIANE.
REALLY?
YEAH.
DAMN.
YEAH, WELL,
THAT GUY'S A MANIAC ANYWAY.
NAH, THIS WAS JUST,
UH, FAMILY STUFF.
MY WIFE --
SOON TO BE EX-WIFE --
I TOLD HER THAT I CAN'T PICK UP
MY KIDS TONIGHT,
AND SHE'S NOT TOO HAPPY
ABOUT THAT.
HOW LONG'S IT BEEN?
WELL, WE'VE BEEN SEPARATED
OVER A YEAR NOW.
NOT MY CHOICE,
BUT DEFINITELY MY FAULT.
LET ME GUESS --
YOU'RE HARD TO LIVE WITH.
I HAVE MY DEMONS.
DON'T ALL COPS?
YEAH, ONLY MINE
AFFECTED MY SON.
HE HAS NIGHT TERRORS NOW.
THAT SUCKS.
YOU KNOW, WE THINK
THAT THE SELFISH THINGS
THAT WE DO TO CUT LOOSE,
JUST GET OUT OF OUR OWN HEAD,
THAT IT WON'T AFFECT US.
WE CONTROL IT, BUT...
THEN WE LOSE THE THING THAT WE
ACTUALLY NEED -- OUR FAMILY.
[ WHISTLING ]
[ PHONE RINGS ]
HELLO AND GOOD EVENING.
HI.
YOU SOUND CHIPPER.
You're not worried about
that article in the paper?
THAT PICTURE IS OF YOU,
ISN'T IT?
I-I DIDN'T KNOW YOUR NAME
WAS REALLY COOPER.
YOU KNOW,
I ALWAYS PREFERRED KENT.
I THOUGHT IT SOUNDED COOL.
PLUS,
IT'S WHAT YOU CALL ME.
THAT'S WHY
I NEVER TOLD YOU.
Don't worry
about the story.
It doesn't matter.
I promise.
So what are you
doing tonight?
I'M GONNA BE WATCHING
"LOVE BOAT"...
a little "Fantasy Island"
if I'm feeling adventurous.
WELL, DON'T BE TOO ADVENTUROUS
WITHOUT ME.
NEVER.
So, you coming over?
PROBABLY NOT.
DEPENDS HOW LONG
THIS PROJECT TAKES.
SOMETIMES THESE THINGS
CAN GET A LITTLE MESSY.
AND BETTY,
about your friend Jimmy.
HE'S NOT MY FRIEND.
Well, he was,
though, right?
I MEAN, YOU GUYS DATED.
I COULD TELL.
Look, it's okay.
I JUST DON'T THINK
HE'S VERY GOOD FOR THE KIDS.
That's all.
I don't really care
for him.
[ SIGHS ]
NEITHER DO I.
I DON'T CARE ABOUT YOUR PAST.
I CARE ABOUT YOUR FUTURE.
KENT.
YOU KNOW I'D DO ANYTHING
FOR YOU.
LIKEWISE.
ANYTHING.
I'll see you.
BYE.
[ Dial tone ]
[ SIGHS ]
[ WHISTLES ]
♪♪
[ KNOCK ON DOOR ]
I -- I GOT IT!
[ SIGHS ]
WIFE CAME HOME EARLY.
SHE GOT A COLD OR SOMETHING.
COME ON. WE'RE GONNA HAVE TO
TAKE THIS PARTY ELSEWHERE.
COME ON.
OR WE COULD JUST CANCEL.
MAYBE IT'S A SIGN
IT WASN'T MEANT TO BE.
BABY, COME ON.
I'M GONNA DO MY BEST WORK
ON YOU.
YOU'RE GONNA LOVE IT.
Jack: SO, HOW WAS THE CONCERT,
HONEY?
STING IS A GOD.
I SERIOUSLY THINK
HE LOOKED AT ME.
WELL, YOU KNOW WHAT?
I'M SURE HE DID.
HOW CAN YOU HATE A BAND
CALLED "THE POLICE"?
[ CHUCKLES ]
UH, BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT.
WELL, THIS MAY BE YOUR LAST
CONCERT PICK-UP,
BECAUSE IN THREE MONTHS,
I'LL BE DRIVING MYSELF.
THREE MONTHS?
THAT'S NOT POSSIBLE.
NO. YOUR --
YOUR MATH IS OFF.
WHAT?
THREE MONTHS?
CAST YOUR MIND WAY BACK --
15 YEARS AND 9 MONTHS AGO --
WHEN I WAS BORN?
[ SIGHS ]
THIS IS LIKE MY FAVORITE TIME.
YOU KNOW, IT'S OUR CHANCE
TO JUST CHILL TOGETHER.
DON'T SAY "CHILL," DAD.
THAT'S TOTALLY GEEKY
COMING FROM YOU.
OH [CHUCKLES] TOTALLY.
AND DON'T WORRY.
YOU CAN TAKE MOM
TO A CONCERT,
LIKE, I DON'T KNOW,
BARRY MANILOW.
TRY ZEPPELIN.
LOOK, THREE MONTHS --
I'M DRIVING.
18 MONTHS --
I GRADUATE FROM HIGH SCHOOL,
AND IN TWO YEARS,
I'M OFF TO COLLEGE.
HEY, I KNOW THIS.
WHAT ARE YOU TRYING TO DO?
YOU WANT TO SEE ME CRY?
JUST GET USED TO IT.
SOON, IT'LL JUST BE YOU
AND MOM...
OKAY.
AND BARRY MANILOW.
[ CHUCKLES ]
THANK YOU. YOU KNOW WHAT?
JUST PIPE DOWN.
[ MUSIC PLAYS LIGHTLY ON RADIO ]
UP NEXT, "OVERLOAD"
BY TALKING HEADS.
THIS IS FROM RANDALL
TO HIS MAIN SQUEEZE, LEILA.
WHY DO PEOPLE DO
THESE DEDICATIONS?
I MEAN, H-HOW DO THEY EVEN KNOW
THE PERSON IS LISTENING?
BECAUSE YOU TELL THEM TO.
YOU SET THE WHOLE THING UP
SO THEY'RE RIGHT THERE LISTENING
WHEN THE SONG COMES ON.
[ THE TALKING HEADS'
"THE OVERLOAD" PLAYS ]
♪ TERRIBLE SIGNAL ♪
Jack:
THE RADIO DEDICATIONS --
LIKE "FOR EMILY F.,
FROM YOUR SECRET ADMIRER" --
THE KILLER IS WITH THE WOMEN
WHEN THE DEDICATIONS COME ON.
OKAY, SO WHAT.
SO, WE CALLED
THE RADIO STATION,
AND THE TIMELINES
MATCH EXACTLY.
I MEAN,
JUST THINK ABOUT IT.
THE SLAYER, HE LEAVES
THE CLUB WITH THE VICTIM,
DRIVES HER IN HIS CAR,
SHE HEARS THE DEDICATION...
THEN HE KILLS HER
IN THAT CAR.
SO IT'S A BIG
HONKING MESS.
EXACTLY, THAT'S WHY HE NEEDS
ALL THESE DIFFERENT VEHICLES,
BECAUSE THEY'RE TRASHED
AFTERWARDS.
ALL RIGHT.
MILLER AND I WILL GET BACK
INTO THE
STOLEN VEHICLE REPORTS.
OKAY, I'LL TAKE USED CAR
DEALERSHIPS. JUNKYARDS?
SURE, GIVE THE MEXICAN
THE SCRAP YARDS.
YOU SAID THAT, NOT ME.
TOUCH BASE
IF YOU FIND ANYTHING.
[ "THE OVERLOAD" CONTINUES ]
♪ I VALUE THESE MOMENTS ♪
♪ WE'RE OLDER THAN ♪
♪ WE REALIZE ♪
♪ IN SOMEONE'S EYES ♪
[ MOANS SOFTLY ]
[ GASPS ]
HI, KAREN McCLAREN.
[ BREATHING HEAVILY ]
HOW DID YOU GET IN?
YOU ROOMMATE'S WINDOW.
SHE LEFT IT OPEN,
WHILE SHE'S OUT CLUBBING.
SO HER ROOM WOULD BE COOL,
SCREW EVERYBODY ELSE.
SELFISH.
DOESN'T SHE KNOW IT'S A
DANGEROUS WORLD OUT THERE?
[ CLICKS ]
I PULLED THE FUSE BOX.
YOU DON'T WANT TO GET A GOOD
LOOK AT MY FACE, KAREN.
THAT WOULD BE A PROBLEM.
DO YOU UNDERSTAND?
YEAH.
ATTAGIRL.
[ GASPS ]
WHY ARE YOU HERE?
I SAW SOMETHING IN YOU,
KAREN,
SOMETHING WORTHY.
AND THEN YOU PRINT
THAT PHOTO OF ME --
PUT ME AT RISK.
THEY PRESSURED US.
THE POLICE --
YOU'RE MINE...
NOT JACK ROTH'S.
YOU'RE MINE.
I'M SORRY.
THEN PROVE IT.
BE MY VOICE,
NOT THEIRS.
THEN YOU HAVE TO SHARE
SOMETHING WITH ME...
ABOUT YOU --
SOMETHING REAL.
[ SIGHS ]
HOW ABOUT AN INTERVIEW?
[ THE ROLLING STONES'
"PLAY WITH FIRE" PLAYS ]
♪ WELL, YOU GOT YOUR DIAMONDS ♪
♪ AND YOU GOT
YOUR PRETTY CLOTHES ♪
♪ AND THE CHAUFFEUR
DRIVES YOUR CAR ♪
♪ YOU LET EVERYBODY KNOW ♪
♪ BUT DON'T PLAY WITH ME ♪
♪ 'CAUSE YOU'RE PLAYING
WITH FIRE ♪
CHEERS.
HEY.
YOU PAGED.
HOW ABOUT A DRINK?
I'M ON THE CLOCK,
SO ABSOLUTELY.
I THINK I GOT SOMETHING.
CALVIN, ONE OF MY GUYS,
SOLD FLY BRAND TO A GUY
IN A RED CORVETTE LAST WEEK.
CALVIN'S GOT A SERIOUS THING
FOR VETTES --
SAID IT WAS A BEAUTY.
DID YOU GET A DESCRIPTION
OF THE GUY?
HE SAID HE WAS WEARING GLASSES
AND A FEDORA,
LIKE HE WAS TRYING
TO HIDE HIS FACE.
THAT'S OUR GUY.
♪ ...WITH ME, 'CAUSE YOU'RE
PLAYING WITH FIRE ♪
HEY, D-MAN,
YOU SEEN BUCKET?
NO, MAN. HAVEN'T.
♪ ...'CAUSE YOU'RE PLAYING
WITH FIRE ♪
[ SIGHS ]
[ CHUCKLES ] WHAT?
THAT'S ALL I GOT.
[ CHUCKLES ]
WHAT ARE WE DOING?
I'M GIVING YOU VALUABLE
INFORMATION,
AND YOU'RE
DRINKING SCOTCH.
I MEAN US.
♪ SO DON'T PLAY WITH ME... ♪
DON'T YOU EVER THINK ABOUT,
YOU KNOW, THE FUTURE?
THE FUTURE?
YOU KNOW, SHOULDN'T WE AT LEAST
TALK ABOUT IT?
NO, JACK,
YOU'RE NOT DOING THIS TO ME.
YO, SKEEVE, MY MAN.
[ CHUCKLES ]
YOU SEEN BUCKET?
BUCKET?
NOBODY SEEN BUCKET SINCE
THE GIRL TOOK OVER THE ROUTE.
WHAT GIRL?
DIANE, WOULD YOU STOP
FOR A SECOND, PLEASE?
THERE IS NO THINKING
ABOUT US.
OKAY, WELL I JUST --
LOOK.
I LIKE WHAT WE HAVE.
IT'S GOOD.
LET'S NOT MAKE THIS INTO
SOMETHING IT CAN NEVER BE.
OH, WOW.
AIN'T THAT A THING?
TURN THE CHAIR AROUND,
KAREN.
DO IT.
SO, KAREN McCLAREN.
THE RHYME NEVER BUGGED YOU?
IT'S BETTER THAN KIKI.
GROWING UP, UNTIL L.A.,
ACTUALLY,
I'VE ALWAYS BEEN KIKI.
KIKI.
BUT KAREN IS FOR
A JOURNALIST --
SOMEONE WHO IS
TAKEN SERIOUSLY.
WELL, I'M SURE NOBODY
WOULD CALL YOU ANYTHING
BUT VERY, VERY SERIOUS.
[ INHALES SHARPLY ]
SO, SHALL...
WE...GET STARTED?
HEY.
[ GASPS ]
GET STARTED WITH THE INTERVIEW,
OF COURSE.
[ BREATHES SHAKILY ]
WHY DO YOU KILL THEM --
THE GIRLS -- UH, WOMEN?
WHY DOES ANYBODY DO ANYTHING?
BECAUSE IT FEELS GOOD.
SO THEY'RE JUST OBJECTS
TO YOU?
THEY DON'T MATTER?
VERA, WANDA,
EMILY, MALLORY,
NATASHA --
THEY MATTER VERY MUCH.
I THINK ABOUT THEM
ALL THE TIME.
IT'S THE CITY
THAT KILLS THEM, KAREN.
THE STRIP KILLS THEM.
THERE ARE MEN MAKE MILLIONS
SELLING DRUGS
THAT TAKE SO MANY
INNOCENT GIRLS --
MANY MORE
THAN I EVER COULD.
I DOUBT THE POLICE
SEE IT THAT WAY.
THE POLICE --
DETECTIVE ROTH?
HE'S GONNA FAIL.
HE'S GOING TO CATCH YOU.
DON'T YOU KNOW THAT?
[ LAUGHS ]
MY, MY.
KIKI'S GOT BALLS.
IT'S KAREN.
YOU NEED A NEW LOOK --
ONE THAT SHOWS WHAT A FORMIDABLE
WOMAN YOU'VE BECOME.
NEW NAME, NEW LOOK.
YOU SEE, WITH YOUR HAIR DOWN,
YOU LOOK LIKE A GIRL.
BUT LIKE THIS...
[ GASPS ]
[ BREATHING SHAKILY ]
LIKE THIS, YOU LOOK
SOPHISTICATED...
...POWERFUL.
THIS...
THIS IS KAREN.
♪♪
[ GASPS ]
THERE.
BEAUTIFUL.
[ BREATHING HEAVILY ]
YOU HAVEN'T GIVEN ME
ANYTHING YET --
NO NEW INFORMATION.
SURE I HAVE.
CAN YOU FIGURE IT OUT?
AND YOU CAN DO
SOMETHING FOR ME --
TELL JACK ROTH
I SAID "HI."
WHAT IS IT ABOUT
JACK ROTH?
WHY ARE YOU
OBSESSED WITH HIM?
IS IT PERSONAL?
HELLO?
[ EXHALES ]
[ BREATHES SHAKILY ]
[ REO SPEEDWAGON'S
"KEEP ON LOVING YOU" PLAYS ]
♪ YOU SHOULD'VE SEEN BY THE LOOK
IN MY EYES, BABY ♪
[ JIMMY GRUNTS ]
Betty: CAN YOU GET IT
OVER WITH ALREADY?
AW, BABY, YOU'RE SO GOOD.
OH, YOU'RE GONNA BE
MY REGULAR THING, NOW.
NO, JUST TONIGHT, JIMMY.
HEY, COME ON.
YOU BETTER STAY
ON MY GOOD SIDE --
THAT BOYFRIEND OF YOURS
GONNA BE GETTING ALL OF
HIS ACTION IN PRISON.
[ SIGHS ]
LORD KNOWS WHAT COULD HAPPEN
TO THOSE KIDS.
[ GRUNTS ]
OHH, YEAH.
WE ARE DOING THIS, BABY,
WHENEVER I WANT.
WHENEVER I SAY.
OH, YEAH. YOU GONNA BE MINE
FROM NOW ON, BABY.
[ GRUNTING ]
NO!
[ GASPS ]
[ BOTH GRUNTING ]
♪♪
[ GAGGING ]
♪ 'CAUSE IT'S THE ONLY THING
I WANNA DO ♪
[ THE STOOGES' "DIRT" PLAYS ]
♪ OOH, I BEEN DIRT ♪
♪ AND I DON'T CARE ♪
[ BREATHING HEAVILY ]
♪ 'CAUSE I'M BURNING... ♪
♪ ...INSIDE ♪
♪ OOOH ♪
♪ YEAH ♪
♪ YEAH, ALL RIGHT ♪
OH!
[ INSTRUMENTAL SOLO ]
[ MUSIC FADING ]
♪♪
[ TIRES SCREECH ]
[ DOG BARKS IN DISTANCE ]
Jack: HEY.
LOOK.
JACK, NO MORE TALKING.
[ SIGHS ]
OKAY.
NO MORE TALKING.
[ CAMERA SHUTTER CLICKS ]
♪♪
I LOVE YOU, JACK ROTH.
[ SIREN WAILS IN DISTANCE ]
[ CLEARS THROAT ]
HEY.
WHAT TIME IS IT?
TIME FOR YOU
TO GET GOING.
[ BEEPER BEEPS ]
[ BEEPER CHIRPS ]
[ POLICE RADIO CHATTER ]
HEY.
YOU OKAY?
[ SIGHS ]
THE KILLER SAID TO SAY "HI".
HI.
NO USABLE PRINTS.
NO HAIR.
NO FIBER TRACE.
I HATE THIS GUY.
BUT HE GAVE ME ONE CLUE.
HE LISTED FIVE GIRLS HE KILLED,
NOT FOUR.
VERA, EMILY, WANDA,
MALLORY, AND NATASHA.
NATASHA.
YOU'RE SURE?
OKAY, CHECK FOR
A MISSING PERSONS REPORT.
OKAY, WE NEED TO
FIGURE OUT A PLACE
FOR YOU AND YOUR ROOMMATE
TO STAY.
ANNIE'S ALREADY GONE.
MY ROOMMATE --
SHE'S CATCHING THE FIRST FLIGHT
BACK TO MINNEAPOLIS.
ME -- I'LL FIGURE IT OUT.
KAREN,
I DON'T KNOW WHAT TO SAY,
BUT I PROMISE YOU, WE WILL
PROTECT YOU BETTER THIS TIME.
I'M GONNA TAKE A QUICK LOOK
AROUND, OKAY?
HELLO.
WHAT'S THE MATTER?
I TASTE ADRENALINE
IN YOUR MOUTH.
WHAT-- WHAT'S HAPPENED?
[ GASPS LIGHTLY ]
TELL ME.
I DID SOMETHING.
HOW BAD IS IT?
IT'S BAD.
♪♪
DID YOU GET IT HANDLED?
I DID.
I STUCK A UNIFORM OUTSIDE
THE DOOR TO L.A. NOTORIOUS --
A STAND-UP GUY AND HE'S BUILT
LIKE A LINEBACKER.
OKAY, WELL, PUT AN EVEN
BIGGER GUY IN THE BACK.
THAT CANNOT HAPPEN AGAIN.
WHAT ABOUT NATASHA?
ANYTHING ON THAT?
IT'S DONE. UH, NO.
I GOT NOTHING THERE YET,
AND I GOT NO PAPER
ON COOPER FLYNN.
THEY SAY THE BIRTH
CERTIFICATES --
THEY'RE ALL IN BOXES
AT THE COUNTY CLERK'S.
[ PHONE RINGS ]
THAT COULD TAKE WEEKS.
YEAH. ROTH. GO.
HEY, LOOK, JACK.
I'VE BEEN AT IT ALL NIGHT.
NO ONE'S TRIED TO CRUSH UP
A MESSED UP VINTAGE CAR.
BESIDES, GUYS HERE TELL ME THEY
WOULDN'T DESTROY IT ANYWAY.
They'd fix it
and they'd sell it.
OKAY. WHAT'S NEXT?
WELL, ME TELLING YOU
HOW HE DOES IT.
I THINK I FIGURED IT OUT.
ALL RIGHT, SO AFTER
THE SLAYER KILLS THESE WOMEN,
OBVIOUSLY HE'S LEAVING ONE HELL
OF A MESS.
SO IF HE'S NOT JUNKING THE CARS,
HE MUST BE REPAIRING THEM.
SO WHAT IF HE DOES THAT FOR
A LIVING? HE'S A CAR RESTORER.
TAKES THE CUSTOMER'S CAR --
USES IT FOR THE KILL.
AND AFTERWARDS, HE PULLS
ALL THE BLOODY STUFF OUT
AND HE REPLACES IT
WITH BRAND-NEW SEATS,
A NEW DASH -- THE WORKS.
DETECTIVE.
CALL BACK.
AND THEN HE CHARGES YOU
TOP DOLLAR FOR IT.
NOW, SLAYER'S GRANDFATHER --
HE UPHOLSTERED FURNITURE,
SO WE'RE THINKING MAYBE THE GUY
PICKED UP A FEW TIPS.
THIS IS L.A.
HOW MANY SHOPS WE TALKING ABOUT?
WE GOT 31 TOTAL
LISTED BUSINESSES.
THERE ARE PROBABLY
WAY MORE,
BUT WE'LL START THERE,
WORK OUR WAY DOWN.
DIVVY THEM UP.
I SAVED THESE TWO FOR US.
A KILLER DOESN'T OFTEN PLAY
WHERE HE WORKS.
THESE TWO ARE WELL OUTSIDE
THE KILL ZONE.
GOT TO START SOMEWHERE.
KENT? HEY.
IS SOMETHING WRONG?
KENT.
HOW COULD YOU DO THAT?
YOU SNEAK OUT WITH SOMEBODY ELSE
AND DO IT.
JIMMY FORCED ME TO DO IT.
I DID NOT WANT TO HAVE SEX
WITH HIM.
HE --
IT'S NOT ABOUT THAT.
SEX IS WHAT EVERYBODY DOES.
WHAT WE DO IS SPECIAL.
IT'S UNIQUE.
YOU MEAN KILLING HIM?
YOU BETRAYED ME.
HOW -- HOW DO YOU NOT SEE THAT?
I DIDN'T KNOW
THAT IT WAS GONNA HAPPEN.
MAYBE I THOUGHT I COULD HANDLE
HIM, AND I COULDN'T,
AND I-I JUST MADE
A MISTAKE.
YOU MADE A CHOICE.
IT WAS CHEATING.
IF YOU WOULD'VE ASKED ME TO,
I WOULD'VE KILLED HIM FOR YOU.
I WOULD'VE
TAKEN CARE OF YOU.
I TAKE CARE OF MYSELF
BECAUSE OF YOU.
YOU TAUGHT ME THAT, BABY --
JUST DON'T.
KENT.
I DON'T THINK
I CAN DO THIS.
THIS -- THIS "US".
KENT.
I'VE GOT WORK TO DO.
[ TIRES SCREECH ]
Paco: THEY DON'T OPEN
FOR ANOTHER COUPLE HOURS.
SHOULD WE TRY
TO GET A WARRANT?
LOOK.
THINK THAT'S THE CAR DIANE
WAS TALKING ABOUT?
LET'S GET S.I.D. OUT HERE
AND FIND OUT.
GET SOME UNITS
OUT HERE, TOO.
THIS IS DETECTIVE CONTRERAS,
REQUESTING...
Betty: I'M SO SORRY.
I NEED TO REMOVE THE BODY,
CLEAN OUT AS MUCH AS I CAN,
QUICKLY.
THEN I'LL TAKE THE CAR.
I WON'T HAVE TIME
TO REUPHOLSTER IT,
BUT AT LEAST I CAN GET
THESE SEATS OUT.
GO HOME, BETTY.
[ SIRENS CHIRP ]
WHAT THE HELL? COOPER COULD BE
HERE WITHIN THE HOUR.
DID YOU TELL THEM?
YES, I TOLD THEM.
HEY! WE SAID
SET UP A PERIMETER
ONE BLOCK WEST,
ONE BLOCK EAST.
ONE BLOCK!
GET BACK IN THE CAR.
BACK IN THE CAR.
THE GUY COULD BE HERE
ANY TIME.
GET BACK IN THE CAR
AND KILL THESE LIGHTS.
MOVE! MOVE! MOVE!
♪♪
I DON'T KNOW WHAT HAPPENED,
JACK.
Karen: AS A HEADLINE --
"INTERVIEW WITH A KILLER."
I'VE BEEN WRITING
SINCE I GOT HERE.
I COULDN'T STOP.
"SITTING THERE AS THE SLAYER
TOUCHED MY NECK,
I WAS TERRIFIED
BUT ALSO EXHILARATED...
LIKE I WAS SITTING
AT THE TOP
OF A ROLLER COASTER'S
TALLEST HILL."
YEAH, I KIND OF LOVE
THAT LINE, TOO.
THE WHOLE THING'S GARBAGE.
THERE'S NO WAY
WE'RE RUNNING IT.
GARBAGE?
IT'S A GOOD PIECE.
"HE TOUCHED ME.
I NEARLY SWOONED, DEAR READER."
YOU SOUND PATHETIC.
YOU SOUND LIKE HIS GIRLFRIEND.
YOU ARE NOT SERIOUS
RIGHT NOW.
HE'S A MONSTER,
AND YOU'RE TALKING
ABOUT HIM BEING A THRILL
ON A ROLLER COASTER.
HE WOULDN'T HURT ME.
OH, MY GOD.
YOU ARE DELUSIONAL!
HE COULD'VE KILLED YOU,
AND IT WOULD'VE BEEN MY FAULT.
YOUR FAULT?
'CAUSE I CONVINCED
YOU TO STAY.
BECAUSE...
I WANTED A STORY.
I MEAN, I-I WANTED YOU.
BUT I MAINLY WANTED
THE STORY BECAUSE --
JUST TO PUT MY PAPER
ON THE MAP --
TO BE THE BIG MAN.
BUT NOW,
IF HE HURT YOU...
ALL I'M SAYING IS YOU'RE HERE
BECAUSE OF ME.
I'M HERE BECAUSE OF ME,
BUT...
...IT'S SWEET
THAT YOU CARE.
I'M GLAD I STAYED.
AND NOT JUST
FOR THE STORY.
[ CHUCKLES ]
WELL, OKAY, THEN.
SORRY.
I-I SLEPT HERE LAST NIGHT.
DON'T BE SORRY.
YOU GOT TO STAY WITH ME
UNTIL ALL THIS IS OVER.
I MEAN,
IF -- IF THAT'S ALL RIGHT.
Man: RIGHT HERE, FELLAS.
HERE'S THE OFFICE.
Jack: THANKS.
WHOSE DESK IS THIS?
KENT'S A COOL MANAGER.
HARD WORK.
CLOCKS IN EARLY EVERY DAMN DAY.
THAT MAKES SENSE.
SEE, HE KILLS GIRLS
IN YOUR CUSTOMERS' CARS,
AND THEN HE SWAPS OUT
THE BLOODY SEATS
FOR BRAND-NEW UPHOLSTERY.
TO DO ALL THAT,
YOU'D HAVE TO --
YOU'D HAVE TO
GET IN EARLY.
♪♪
HI.
SORRY, I PROBABLY SHOULD'VE
CALLED TO REMIND YOU,
BUT I'VE GOT
THAT JOB INTERVIEW.
I DON'T MIND, GLORIA.
IT'S -- I JUST HAD A COUPLE
OF THINGS ON MY MIND.
OKAY, THANK YOU SO MUCH.
COME ON.
BYE, SWEETIE.
LOVE YOU.
LOVE YOU, TOO.
SEE YA.
BYE.
YOU READY?
YEAH.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
IT'S SO HOT, I THINK
WE SHOULD HAVE ICE CREAM.
KENT,
IT'S NOT EVEN LUNCH.
ICE CREAM FOR EVERYONE.
[ TV CHATTER ]
[ SIGHS ]
Man:
...225 YARDS RUSHING TODAY,
SIMPLY GUARANTEEING
THE STATE VICTORY.
TECH HAS NO ANSWER
FOR HIM DEFENSIVELY.
Announcer: AND NOW FOR
YOUR LOCAL LOS ANGELES NEWS,
HERE'S JASON BROWN.
Brown:
SOURCES TELL K.A.B.C.
THE LAPD IS MOVING IN
ON THE HOLLYWOOD SLAYER.
HIS TRAGIC VICTIMS
WERE ALL YOUNG WOMEN --
VERA BENNETT, EMILY FUENTES,
MALLORY KHARCHENKO,
AND A POTENTIAL VICTIM NOW
IDENTIFIED ONLY AS NATASHA.
DETECTIVES ARE WORKING
OFF OF CLUES
FOUND AT VARIOUS
CRIME SCENES,
AND THERE MAY BE A BREAK
IN THE CASE.
AND FROM WASHINGTON,
AT 9:00 A.M. THIS MORNING,
PRESIDENT REAGAN...
CHOCOLATE AND STRAWBERRY.
[ SIGHS ]
ISN'T STRAWBERRY
YOUR FAVORITE?
OH, YES.
IS EVERYTHING ALL RIGHT?
YEAH.
AND I HAVE APPROVED...
ARE YOU OKAY, KENT?
YEAH.
OKAY.
[ PRESIDENT REAGAN CONTINUES
INDISTINCTLY ]
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-