Kobe, Japan
Tombstone  Of  The  Fireflies
Seita, my geta...
We'll get new ones.
Where's Mommy?
She's waiting in the bomb shelter.
Seita!
This is Aya-chan.
Isn't this Taro?
Mommy wasn't here.
Let's go, she's waiting for us.
How could they drop a bomb
on the shelter?
Oh, I forgot.
Dosn't this belong to your mother?
Yes.
Take it for now, okay?
Your mother's in here.
Don't just stand there!
Seita...
Hey, Seita?
Setsuko!
What's wrong, Setsuko?
Setsuko?
What happened?
I swallowed it.
Does your tummy ache?
It'll come out soon.
Seita...
It's his fault.
Don't be cranky.
Seita, can you do that
thing that Setsuko loves...?
No.
Come on.
Please.
No.
Do it for her.
And for me too.
No.
You've caught a big one!
Seita.
Seita!
I'll take Mother to the hospital.
It's too late.
Seita, run around again, please!
Seita, you've really improved.
Thank you, Father.
But he shouldn't push himself
so hard...
Why's that?
Because he's born weak like me...
There's been no sign of asthma.
Mother, don't worry so much.
But you had an attack
the other night.
Seita is over his asthma now.
But...
Mother, I don't have asthma
anymore.
I've improved but Mother's heart
condition hasn't.
Medicine doesn't seem to help.
I'll rub your back to
ease your discomfort.
Seita...
No need to worry, he'll
make a fine man one day.
Setsuko, what's wrong?
Wait until your father and brother
finish eating.
Look at her, Dear.
Would you like to hold her?
Such a tiny, little hand...
Ah... fireflies.
What a big baby I have here!
Seita.
Is this my house?
Yes, it was our house.
We found it!
It's a glorious honor
To fight for the Emperor
The roaring cheers of
The whole o Japan
Where's Mommy?
In the hospital.
I want to see her.
Let's go visit our aunt
in Nishinomiya.
Mommy will come soon.
Wherever I go
In the war of justice
No enemy will intefere
With my heroic advances
Go, strong one!
Ma'am, you have nothing at all
to worry about.
Dig deeper on the left
there, will you?
Right there.
Somebody, move these things
out of way, quickly!
Don't worry!
You over there!
You're not from Tateishi Junior High,
are you?
I'm from Kobe 1st Junior High.
Where are you from?
Mikage.
I heard there was a
big air-raid there.
Did you lose your house?
I'm visiting my relative here.
In this area?
In the town of Shukugawa.
It's very close.
You play kendo?
Yes, sir.
After you settle in, come to the
school for a match.
I'm Tateishi's schoolmaster.
Schoolmaster?
Don't I look like one?
Maybe I should grow a mustache!
Hello?
Hello! Anybody home?
Yes, I'm in here!
Who can it be...
Just when I'm busy.
Yes, yes. Who is it?
What's wrong with you?
I didn't tell you to come in!
The gate was open...
That doesn't mean you can come in.
Didn't your parents teach you
any manners? What is it?
My mother sent some things to you
in the event...
Are you Seita from Mikage?
Your father's the Navy Captain?
I know you! I remember you.
Is that your sister?
I think I saw her once when
she was a baby.
It's Setsuko.
That's right, Setsuko!
We lost our house in the air-raid.
And your father?
He's on a Navy cruiser,
serving the country.
And your mother?
In the hospital.
And...?
Did you get the package?
A package?
I don't know anything about it...
other told us to visit you
in case of an emergency.
You're still kids
and you have no place to live.
I commiserate with you.
Do you know commiserate?
Yes, I do.
I'm a widow now...
My husband died in combat
half a year ago.
But I'm not alone.
I have a son and a daughter.
They're out working now.
It's a small house.
There's no room for you to stay.
Sorry. It's just impossible.
Take care now.
Please give me the package then...
Stop going on about the package!
I don't know anything about it.
Can we go, Seita?
That's right, off you go.
Seita.
Wait a minute.
What do you have in there?
Look at those delicacies!
What luxury a navy officer's
family enjoys!
Kindness begets kindness...
Do you know that?
Yes, I do.
Setsuko, you are so fair!
You're just like a doll.
Good work, Seita.
You can stay in this room.
Thank you very much.
You're so polite.
You've been well brought up.
That's an organ.
Know how to play?
Play it any time you want.
And Seita, let me tell you
something...
We are distant relatives with
just a slight connection.
There's really no reason why
I should take care of you.
But I hate to be uncharitable.
Do you know uncharitable?
No, ma'am.
Well anyway, I'm taking you in
so I expect you to share too.
What're you doing, Mom?
You startled me!
Hi, son.
I'm hungry.
Is that all you can say?
How about helping me clean up
this messy cupboard?
I have to try to get this in.
That's the Navy family's package.
Keep it in the hallway.
I can't leave it there.
More importantly, what are those
kids doing here?
They're distant relatives
from Mikage...
You mean, the Navy family?
Shut up! They'll hear you.
Those who've lost homes in the war
are entitled to tin rations.
I want to eat tinned beef.
Mom would do anything for food...
Quiet! How ill mannered you are!
I'm done, thank you.
You know your manners, Setsuko.
Are you full?
Eat up or you won't become
a big girl.
Girls that age are cute!
You were once cute like that.
Really?
I'm done, thank you.
Can I have a word with you?
Your mother's dead?
I have her bones in here.
You're lucky you have her bones.
I don't even know where
my husband died...
I have to ask you a favor.
Don't tell Setsuko about Mother.
She believes that Mom's
in the hospital.
All right. I'm well known for
my discretion.
Seita...
Seita?
Can't you sleep?
Did you have a dream?
I'm scared...
What's all the noise?
And at this time of night too...
I'm sorry.
I'll be the one who's blamed for
the noise.
Seita.
I want Mommy. I want to see her.
Get snappy and move it!
Pour it properly or it won't
do any good.
Put your soul in it and pour
as if you're attacking the enemy!
We'll keep doing it till
you get it right.
Seita, don't just stand there.
You're in the neighbors group now.
This is a distant relative of mine.
Oh, the poor boy...
Their house burnt down while his dad,
a Navy Captain was away.
His mother died too...
He escaped with his little sister
and came to us.
Aunt, don't talk about mother...
I have two children to take care
but how could I turn them away?
Kids eat a lot so it's difficult
to provide for them.
As for me, I don't mind if I eat
twice or only once a day.
As long as the kids
have enough to eat...
Atta Lady!
Most of us can only afford to
take care of ourselves.
How incredible of you to take care
of somebody else's kids!
Oh, I'm just doing
what seems right.
Hello.
Everyone, let's do it again.
There's a variety of incendiary bombs.
Electrons have sparks flying out
of them.
So cover yourself with
a wet straw mat to...
Excuse me, Sir...
If you want to know anything
about incendiary bombs, ask me.
There's no time to put out fires
in a raid, you should just run.
Don't be foolish!
You're not supposed to run.
Houses are the foundation
of the nation.
You extinguish the fire so it doesn't
spread to other houses, you fool!
Come on, let's go!
Why did you have to talk
back to the Leader?
I felt so ashamed that I
wanted to hide.
The schoolmaster.
I can offer you nothing but tea.
That's fine. I appreciate it.
What was it that you came to
talk about?
It's about Seita.
Did the boy do something wrong?
Not at all.
I came across him the other day
and he told me that he lost
his house in an air-raid.
When I heard about him
moving into this town
I somehow thought of him as being
my responsibility too.
Did he mention to you how long
he was planning to stay?
No, he didn't.
Do you intend to continue
taking care of them...?
Oh, I think so...
Seita, I'm scared.
Seita, don't scare Setsuko.
Seita, do you like to sing?
I love songs.
I love songs too.
But I'm not allowed to make a
noise at home, so I can't sing.
The foal's mane
Is wet with morning dew
Both my hands get wet
When I stroke it
It neighs back to me
When I call its name
Shall we run up
The hill path?
Giddyup, Whoa
Going up the hill
I raised you from
A foal in the hay
Now you're a horse
With shiny fur
Don't get a stomachache
Don't catch a cold
Aunt...
Where's your brother?
He's pumping water.
What are you doing?
I'm tidying up because it's so messy.
That's Mommy's.
Such an important thing shouldn't
just be left here.
Some bad person might steal it.
Setsuko, do you know why
your mommy's bag is here?
Setsuko.
Do you want me to tell you where
your mommy's gone?
Sorry.
Where do you think you're going?
Come up here.
Then I'll help you with that.
"War hero's house"
Come in.
You a junior high student?
Where from?
Mikage.
Wasn't there an air-raid there?
Is your family okay?
Did they die?
Father's on a Navy cruiser,
serving the country.
Navy. Will you join the Navy
like your dad?
I don't know.
Why not?
I have asthma.
That's good. You can serve the
nation right here, like me.
I'm leaving.
Don't get upset.
Beanbags. Take all you want.
You can cook the beans inside
when you're hungry.
For my sister...
What are you doing here?
Me?
I suffer from bad asthma
just like you.
It's not true!
I'm lying.
Do you...
Do you want to end up like this?
It's her husband.
He died when he was 24...
What a waste of a young life.
What's your name?
Seita.
Seita, get down and keep still.
Cover up like this.
Let the bad weather pass
over your head.
Look up when you think
the storm's gone.
There may be a blue sky
with no clouds.
But just when you thought
it was sunny
rain might come,
and a storm and lightening.
Hide under the blanket again.
No! I won't just hide quietly
under a blanket.
Seita, you're in no hurry.
Your turn will come anyway.
My turn?
Did you see that woman
run out of here?
We had a fight.
It was over something
embarrassingly trivial.
You get two people in a room,
they'll end up arguing.
That's what humans are like.
We end up killing each other.
It's always been like that.
Since the day that humans
were first on Earth.
It'll never change.
We'll keep on killing each other.
Wherever we are.
One day, it'll be your turn.
What will you do?
I'm going to get down like this
and hide like a mole.
You coward!
It's the best way.
Don't get upset, Seita.
Lucky you have asthma.
You can lay low like me.
No! I'd never do such a thing!
That's it, Seita.
That's just the way it is.
You have asthma.
Go home and lie down.
Take care of your sister for
the rest of your life.
That's the way to go.
No, I won't!
I'm going to go to war!
Supper.
It's suppertime.
What are you doing?
Supper, Setsuko.
Aren't you going to eat?
Go and eat.
I don't want to.
Seita, if you don't come and eat,
I'll take yours off the table.
That's okay.
Did you go and visit
the university student?
You shouldn't talk to that man.
First you talk back to the Leader...
It's so embarrassing!
Behave more like the son of
an lmperial Navy Captain!
- It will get worse if you scratch.
- It's itchy.
Just don't scratch.
Someone's sleeping...
Turn this way.
Mommy.
Let's go back.
Mother.
Mother, what's wrong?
It's a letter from your father.
A letter? But Dad died
half a year ago...
It was written
before he died.
"I trust that you all
are doing well."
"As for me, there's no need
to worry as I'm quite healthy..."
It's so hard...
It really gets me down.
The foal's mane
Is wet with morning dew
Both my hands get wet
When I stroke it
It neighs back to me
When I call its name
Stop it, stop that right now!
Who said that you could play that?
If you don't like it here,
why don't you get out now!
Don't cry.
I want to go home. I don't want
to stay here anymore.
Our house burned down.
"Schoolmaster's Office"
You're courageous to challenge me,
young man. I accept it.
Are you very good, sir?
Don't worry, I'm only so-so.
Tell me if you need anything.
Thank you, schoolmaster.
They lost their house just like you.
It's your turn, Seita.
I can't play.
You don't have to play the piano.
How about a song?
Seita, do that one, please.
Be quiet!
What's that?
You do it well.
What's he good at, Setsuko?
Setsuko, don't answer.
We have to go.
Wait, it's still early...
This kimono is too good for me.
Come on, just try it on and see.
It looks great on you.
That's Mother's!
No! As I told you,
I bought it years ago.
It's Mother's. I know it.
Kids can't recognize different
kimono patterns.
Give it back to me.
Don't be silly!
It is true that your mother asked me
to take care of you.
I received the package she sent me
but there wasn't much in it.
I've been making the most of
what she sent
so that you wouldn't have
an empty stomach.
It's all been for you.
Don't you see what I've been doing?
Give it back to me!
Right then!
From now on, I won't take care of
you anymore.
Does that suit you? Can you cook
for yourselves?
Just give me rice and we'll
look after ourselves.
I see.
Just as you say,
if that's what you want.
Does it cook rice well?
Cooking outside looks like a lot
of fun.
Did you have an argument with Mom?
Supper.
Come and eat.
I've made a delicious supper.
Is it done yet, Seita?
Just a minute.
Here, it's done.
It's done!
It's soggy...
Don't eat if you don't want to.
Is it yummy?
Seita, I can't sleep.
Shut up and sleep.
I said I can't.
Keep trying.
Be quiet.
What's all the noise?
Seita, make her be quiet.
Setsuko, look. Fireflies.
Setsuko. Haven't you had your
breakfast yet?
You can sit down here.
I'm on my way out now.
I'm done. See you later.
Me, too. Off I go.
Have a nice day.
They've gone to work for
the country.
Nobody can afford to sit around
doing nothing all day.
Aunt.
Can I sit down?
Of course you can, but I won't
serve you any food.
Setsuko.
Come on, breakfast is ready.
Ooh! What's for breakfast?
I wish I could have a taste!
The junior high school is on fire.
Look! The fire's getting bigger.
Schoolmaster, the school!
The schoolmaster ran away?
The neighbors' leader was the one
who found they'd disappeared.
The whole family?
Because the Emperor's photo
got burned.
How did it start?
Well, you know people were
staying at the school
who'd lost their homes.
Did they cause the fire?
Maybe they left a fire smoldering...
Seita.
What's the big panic?
The schoolmaster is dead!
And his family...
Just hide under a blanket.
"No Entry"
Hey, old man
Where are you going?
With that bamboo basket
Tied to your waist
I'm just going to the creek
To catch some loaches...
The foal's mane
Is wet with morning dew
Both my hands get wet
When I stroke it
It neighs back to me
When I call its name
Shall we run up
the hill path?
Giddyup, Whoa
Going up the hill
Give it back, it's Mother's!
Are you out of your mind?
This belongs to me!
I'll do whatever I want with it.
Give it back, you thief!
What did you call me?
After all I've done for you!
Where is the package?
Where did you hide it?
Wait, Seita! Stop there!
Okay, you win.
I'll give all your mother's
kimonos back.
That's everything.
Is this Mother's...?
I don't know.
But she sent me things in case
there wasn't enough food.
I've never seen this kimono...
She was fashionable, wasn't she?
Is that all there is?
You really are a greedy boy,
aren't you?
Well, there were more things
in the beginning.
But I had to provide for
you and Setsuko, didn't I?
Ineluctably I had to
exchange kimonos for food.
You know the word,
ineluctably?
Seita.
Mommy is dead.
She doesn't need kimonos anymore.
Get out of here.
How dare you call me a thief!
I don't want to see you anymore!
We're moving out.
Seita.
This is our house from now on.
Nobody will bother us here.
We'll be safe.
This is the kitchen.
That's the entrance.
Setsuko, give me a hand.
Seita, where's the toilet?
Outside.
Don't worry. I'll come with you.
Look, fireflies.
Seita.
The firefly.
It's dead.
What are they for?
For the graves.
Write the fireflies' names on them.
Do they have names?
They do.
They all have one.
"Fusako."
Jirokichi.
Kotaro.
Kuranosuke.
Yoshiko.
The foal's mane
Is wet with morning dew
Both my hands get wet
When I stroke it
It neighs back to me
When I call its name
Shall we run up
The hill path?
Giddyup, Whoa
Going up the hill
I raised you from
A foal in the hay
Now you're a horse
With shiny fur
Don't get a stomachache
Don't catch a cold
Come on, be strong
And give a big neig
Giddyup, Whoa
Give a big neigh
Setsuko, breakfast.
It's watery.
Don't eat if you don't want to.
I'm still hungry.
You do nothing for the country.
You traitor!
Let's go.
What's wrong, Setsuko?
My pooh's runny.
It's a kamikaze mission.
It looks like a firefly.
Yes, it does.
Setsuko, this is the last kimono.
Stop scratching.
It's itchy.
Don't scratch it!
Seita.
Have some.
What's this?
It's supper.
And some tea, too.
I'll fry some soy pulp for you too.
Eat as much as you like.
Won't you eat some?
You thief!
Setsuko.
Setsuko, I got an apple!
It's not an apple.
It's a potato.
Who cares what it is? Eat it.
I don't want it.
I'II eat it then.
You have to eat this.
Seita, where's Mommy?
I want to see Mommy.
Eat it.
I want a candy.
The tin's empty.
No.
You, fool!
Remember the cake from Juchheim?
That was only half a year ago.
And the chocolate Father sent us
from Shanghai...
It feels like it was ages ago but
it was only a year ago.
Mommy used to make peach compote.
Oh, yeah...
When I had diarrhea, she made
apple puree for me.
You said you didn't want any sweets.
You didn't eat the yokan.
I couldn't even swallow dumpling
soup the first time I had it...
Even that's a treat now.
What do you want to eat, Setsuko?
I want tempura.
A platter of sashimi...
And tokoroten jelly.
Great.
When we went out to eat
fish sukiyaki,
there was only one egg each but
Mother gave hers to me.
Chinese food from Nanking Town...
Lemonade on an excursion...
It sounds like a dream now.
Seita.
Yes?
Diarrhea...
Okay.
What are you doing here?
Who's there?
What're you doing in my field?
Hey, you!
Stop right there!
I'm sorry.
You, thief!
Seita?
Seita.
Would you care for a candy?
Delicious.
Diarrhea...
Oh, no. We have to call the doctor
and give you a shot.
Shosuke Suzuki...
The foal's mane
Is wet with morning dew
Both my hands get wet
When I stroke it
It neighs back to me
When I call its name
Shall we run up
The hill path?
Giddyup, Whoa
Going up the hill
I, the Emperor, understand
your apprehension.
However, as world conditions
demand
I have to repress my emotions
and endure the shame
to bring peace to
the world now and forever.
I, the Emperor, shall be with
his nation as long as...
Setsuko.
Seita.
You can have this.
It's yours.
Setsuko.
Don't go without me!
"Setsuko's grave"
Reo Yoshitake
Rina Hatakeyama
Seiko Matsuda
Keiko Matsuzaka
Original Story
Akiyuki Nosaka
Screenplay
Takuya Nishioka
Music
Castle In The Air
(Koko Tanikawa + Kazumi Watanabe)
Production
TV TOKYO Corporation
BANDAI VISUAL CO., LTD.
PONY CANYON INC.
EISEl GEKIJO Co., Ltd.
SAKUMA CONFECTIONERY CO., LTD.
TORNADO FILM
JOLLY ROGER INC.
PAL ENTERTAlNMENTS PRODUCTION
Director
Taro Hyugaji
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+ |T|h|e| |D|e|a|f| |B|o|y|s| |F|o|r| |B|o|y|s| |G|r|o|u|p|  +
E N J O Y   this   SRT   SUBTITLE   R e l e a s e
http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1250968
Hotaru No Haka - Tombstone Of The Fireflies (2008) English.srt
FPS: 23.976
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+ |T|h|e| |D|e|a|f| |B|o|y|s| |F|o|r| |B|o|y|s| |G|r|o|u|p|  +
We want more subtitles right NOW!
1) ALL DVD's to be subtitled.
2) ALL VIDEO GAMES to be subtitled.
3) ALL videos/DVD's used in lessons at school to be subtitled.
4) More pre-recorded & live subtitles on TV.
____           __            ___   __              ___        __               __
/     /   _   /    )  _   _ (_     /  _)        _  (_      _   /  _)        _   / _   _
(     /)  (-   /(_ /  (-  ( /  /     /(_)  () (/ _)   /   () /    /(_)  () (/ _)   (__)  /  () (/  /)
- Bringing you free subtitles       /                  Online  /  Since 1993    - /
-  |Africa| |Asia| |Australia| |Europe| |North America| |South America|   -  /