I owe everything to George
Bailey... Help him, dear Father.
Joseph, Jesus and Mary.
Help my friend, Mr. Bailey.
Help my son, George, tonight.
He never thinks about himself,
God, that's why he's in trouble.
George is a good guy.
Give him a break, God...
I love him, dear Lord.
Watch over him tonight...
Please, God, something's
the matter with Daddy...
Please bring Daddy back.
Hello, Joseph. Trouble?
Looks like we'll have
to send someone down.
A lot of people asking for help
for a man named George Bailey.
George Bailey. Yes. Tonight's
his crucial night. You're right.
We'll have to send someone down
immediately. Whose turn is it?
That's why I came to see you, sir.
It's that clock-maker's turn again.
Oh, Clarence. Hasn't got
his wings yet, has he?
We've passed him up right along.
Because, you know, sir, he's
got the I.Q. Of a rabbit.
Yes, but he's got the
faith of a child. Simple.
Joseph, send for Clarence.
You sent for me, sir?
Yes, Clarence. A man down
on earth needs our help.
Splendid! Is he sick?
No. Worse. He's discouraged.
At exactly ten forty-five
P.M., earth-time,
that man will be thinking seriously
of throwing away God's greatest gift.
Oh, dear, dear! His life! Then
I have only an hour to dress.
What are they wearing now?
You will spend that hour getting
acquainted with George Bailey.
Sir, lf I should accomplish this mission,
I mean, might I perhaps win my wings?
I've been waiting for over
two hundred years now, sir...
and people are beginniing to talk.
What's that book you've got there?
Oh, 'The Adventures of Tom Sawyer.'
Clarence, you do a good job with
George Bailey and you'll get your wings.
Oh, thank you, sir. Thank you.
Poor George. Sit down.
Sit down?! What are we...
If you're going to help a man, you want
to know something about him, don't you?
- Well, naturally, of course, I...
- Well, keep your eyes open.
- See the town?
- Where? I... I don't see a thing.
Oh, I forgot. You haven't
got your wings yet.
Now look, I'll help you out.
Concentrate.
Begin to see something?
Why, yes! This is amazing!
If you ever get your wings,
you'll see all by yourself.
Oh, wonderful!
Yippee!
Okay, boys, let's go.
Hey, who's that?
- That's your problem, George Bailey.
- A boy?!
That's him when he was twelve.
Back in nineteen nineteen.
Something happens here you'll
have to remember later on.
Come on, Marty. Come on, Marty.
- Hee-haw!
And here comes the scare-baby,
my kid brother, Harry Bailey!
I'm not scared!
Go, Harry! C'mon, Harry!
Attaboy, Harry! Come on, Harry!
Help, George! Help! Help!
...Harry, I'm coming!
- Help!
- Hang on, Harry!
I'm coming! Chain Gang!
George saved his
brother's life that day.
But it caught him that cold
which infected his left ear.
Cost him his hearing in that ear.
It was weeks before he was able
to go back to his after-school job
at old man Gower's Drugstore.
Mr. Potter!
Who's that? A king?
That's Henry F. Potter.
The richest and meanest
man in the county.
Hee-haw! Hee-haw!
Go to work, slave...
I wish I had a million
dollars! Hot dog!
It's me, Mr. Gower. George Bailey.
- You're late
- Yes, sir.
Hello, George. Hello, Mary.
Hello, Violet.
Two-cents' worth of shoelaces?
She was here first.
I'm still thinking.
Shoelaces?
Please, Georgie. I like him.
You like every boy.
What's wrong with that?
Here you are.
- Help me down.
- Help you down?!
Made up your mind yet?
I'll take chocolate.
With coconuts?
I don't like coconuts.
You don't like coconuts?
Say, brainless, don't you
know where coconuts come from?
Look it here... from Tahiti,
Fiji Islands, the Coral Sea!
A new magazine! I never saw it before.
Of course you never.
Only us explorers can get it.
I've been nominated for membership
in the National Geographic Society.
Is this the ear you can't hear on?
George Bailey, I'll love
you till the day I die.
I'm going out exploring
some day, you watch.
And I'm gonna have a couple of
harems, and maybe three or four wives.
Wait and see.
- George! George!
- Yes, sir.
You're not paid to be a canary.
No, sir...
Mr. Gower, do you want something?
- Anything?
- No.
- Anything I can do back here?
- Nope.
I'll get them, sir.
...take those capsules
over to Mrs. Blaine's.
- She's waiting for them.
- Yes, sir...
They have the diphtheria
there, haven't they, sir?
Ummm.
Is it a charge, sir?
Yes, charge.
- Mr. Gower, I think...
- Aw, get going!
Yes, sir.
Fast there, Captain
Cook! Where you headin'?
Got to see Pop, Uncle Billy.
- Some other time, George.
- It's important!
There's a squall in there
that's shapin' up into a storm.
Uncle Billy, telephone.
- Who is it?
- The Bank examiner.
Bank examiner?
Oh, I should have
called him yesterday.
Switch it inside.
I'm not crying, Mr. Potter.
Well, you're begging and
that's a whole lot worse.
All I'm asking for
is thirty days more.
- Pop!
- Just a minute, son.
Just thirty short days. I'll dig
up that five thousand somehow.
- Shove me up. Shove me up.
- Pop!
Have you put any real pressure on these
people of yours to pay those mortgages?
Times are bad, Mr. Potter. A lot
of these people are out of work.
- Then foreclose!
- I can't do that.
- These families have children.
- Pop!
They're not my children.
But they're somebody's
children, Mr. Potter.
Are you running a
business or a charity ward?
- Well, all right...
- Not with my money.
Mr. Potter, what makes you
such a hard-skulled character?
You have no family, no children.
You can't begin to spend
all the money you've got.
So I suppose I should give it
to miserable failures like you
and that idiot brother
of yours to spend for me.
He's not a failure!
- You can't say that about my father!
- George, George, quiet. George...
You're not! You're the
biggest man in town!
- Run along.
- Bigger than him.
- Run along!
- Bigger than everybody!
Gives you an idea of the Baileys.
Don't let him say things
like that about you, Pop.
All right, son. All right.
Thanks. I'll talk to you tonight.
What!
Why, that medicine should
have been there an hour ago.
It'll be over in five
minutes, Mrs. Blaine.
Where's Mrs. Blaine's box of capsules?
I feel...
- Didn't you hear what I said?
- Yes, sir, I...
What kind of tricks
are you playing anyway?
Why didn't you deliver
them right away?
Don't you know that boy's very sick?
You're hurting my sore ear.
You lazy loafer!
Mr. Gower, you don't
know what you're doing.
You put something
wrong in those capsules.
I know you're unhappy.
You got that telegram
and you're upset.
You put something
bad in those capsules.
It wasn't your fault, Mr. Gower.
Just look and see what you did.
Look at the bottle you
took the powder from.
It's poison! I tell you it's poison!
I know you feel bad.
I didn't know...
- Oh...
- Don't hurt my sore ear again.
- Oh, no, no, no...
Oh, George. George...
Oh, Mr. Gower, I
won't ever tell anyone.
I know what you're feeling.
I won't tell a soul.
- Hope to die, I won't.
- Oh, George, George...
An overnight bag,
genuine English cowhide,
combination lock, fitted
up with brushes, combs...
Nope! Nope, nope, nope, nope, nope.
Now look, Joe. Now look,
I, l-I want a big one.
What did you stop it for?
I want you to take a
good look at that face.
- Who is it?
- George Bailey.
Oh, you mean the kid that had his
ears slapped back by the druggist?
That's the kid.
Uh-huh. It's a good face.
I like it. I like George Bailey.
Tell me, did he ever tell
anyone about the pills?
Not a soul.
Did he ever marry the girl?
Did he ever go exploring?
Well, wait and see.
Big... see... I, I don't
want one for one night.
I want something for a
thousand and one nights.
With plenty of room here for labels
from Italy and Baghdad, Samarkand...
a great big one.
- I see, a flying carpet, huh?
- Yeah.
I don't suppose you'd like this
old second-hand job, would you?
Now you're talking.
Gee whiz, I could use that as
a raft in case the boat sunk.
- How much does this cost?
- No charge.
That's my trick ear, Joe. It
sounded as if you said no charge.
That's right.
Well, what's my name doing on it here?
A little present form old man Gower.
Came down and picked it out himself.
He did?!
What do you know about that...
my old boss. Isn't that nice?
What boat you sailing on?
I'm working across on a cattle boat.
- A cattle boat?
- Okay, I like cows.
- Hello, Mr. Gower.
- George!
How are you? Thanks ever
so much for the baggage.
- It's just exactly what I wanted.
- Aw, forget it.
Oh, it's wonderful
of you to think of it.
- Hope you enjoy it.
- Oh, oh, oh, oh.
I wish I had a million
dollars. Hot dog!
Avast there, Captain Cook!
You got your sealegs yet?
Parlez vous Francais, Mister?
Hey, send us some of their picture
postcards, will you, George?
Hey, George, don't take
any plugged nickels.
Hey, George, your suitcase is leaking.
Hey, Ernie! Hi, Ernie!
- Hiya, George.
- Hi, Bert.
- George...
- Hey, hey, I, I'm a rich tourist today.
- How about driving me home in style?
- Great.
Hop in Your Highness, hop in.
And for the carriage trade.
I put on my hat.
- Good afternoon, Mr. Bailey.
- Hello, Violet.
Hey, you look good. That's
some dress you got on there.
What! This old thing?
Why, I only wear it when
I don't care how I look.
- How would you like...
- Yes.
Want to come along, Bert?
We'll show you the town.
No, thanks. I, uh, I've gotta go
home and see what the wife's doing.
Family man.
George! Harry!
You're shaking the
house down! Stop it!
Oh, let them alone! I wish
I was up there with them.
But Harry'll tear his
dinner suit! George!
That's why all children
should be girls.
But if they were all girls,
there wouldn't be any...
Oh, never mind.
George! Harry! Come down
to dinner this minute.
Everything's getting cold and you know,
how long we've been waiting for you.
Okay, Mom!
- Here's a present for you, Pop.
- Oh, you two idiots!
- George, sit down and have dinner.
- I've eaten.
Well, aren't you going to finish
dressing for your graduating party?
- Look at you!
- I don't care.
It's George's tux. Annie, my
sweet, have you got those pies?
If you lay a hand on me,
I'll hit you with this broom.
Annie, I'm in love with you,
there's a moon out tonight.
Boy, oh, boy, oh, boy, my last meal
in the old Bailey Boarding House.
Oh, my lands, my blood pressure!
Pop, can I have the car? I have to
take over a lot of plates and things.
- What plates?
- Oh, Mom,
I'm Chairman of the Eats Committee
and we only need a couple of dozen.
Oh, no, you don't. Harry,
now, not my best Haviland.
Oh, let him have the plates, Mother.
Hope you have a good trip, George.
Uncle Billy and I are gonna miss you.
I'll miss you too, Pop. What's
the matter? You look tired.
- Oh, I had another tussle with Potter today.
- Oh.
I thought when we put him on the board of
Directors, he'd ease up on us a little bit.
Oh, what's eating that old
money-grubbing buzzard anyway?
Oh, he's a sick man.
Frustrated and sick.
And his mind's sick in
his soul, if he has one.
He hates everybody that has
anything that he can't have.
He hates us mostly, I guess.
Gangway! Gangway! So long, Pop.
So long!
- Harry, you got a match?
- Very funny. Very funny.
Put those things in the car and I'll
get your tie and studs ready for you.
- Now, hurry up, hurry up.
- Okay, Mom.
- You coming later?
- Don't you drop one of those.
- You coming later, George?
- What do you mean,
- and be bored to death?
- Couldn't want a better death.
Lots of pretty girls, and we're going
to use that new floor tonight, too.
- Oh, I hope it works.
- No gin tonight, son!
- Aw, Pop, just a little.
- No, son. Not one drop.
Oh!
Boys and girls and music...
why do they need gin?
Father, did I act like that when
I graduated from high school?
Pretty much.
You know, George, I wish we could
send Harry to college with you.
Your mother and I talked
it over half the night.
Mmm, we have that all figured out.
Harry'll take my job at the Building
and Loan, and work there four years,
then he'll go.
- He's pretty young for that job.
- Well, no younger than I was.
Maybe you were born older, George.
How's that?
I say, you were born older.
I suppose you've decided what you
want to do when you get out of college.
Oh well, you know what I've always
talked about... build things...
design new buildings...
plan modern cities...
- all that stuff.  - Still after that
first million before you're thirty.
No, I'll settle for half that in cash.
'Course it's just a hope, but uh,
you wouldn't consider coming back
to the Building and Loan, would you?
Well, I... I... Why, Annie, why,
why don't you draw up a chair?
Then you'd be more comfortable and you
could hear everything that's going on.
I would if I thought I'd hear
anything worth listening to.
You would, eh?
- I know it's soon to talk about it.
- Oh, now, Pop. I, I,
I couldn't. I couldn't face being cooped up for
the rest of my life in a shabby little office...
Oh, I'm sorry, Pop, I
didn't mean it that way,
but this business of nickels and
dimes and spending all your life
trying to figure out how to save three
cents on a length of pipe... I'd go crazy.
I... I wanna do something
big and something important.
You know, George, I feel that in a small
way we are doing something important.
Satisfying a fundamental urge.
It's deep in the race for a man to want
his own roof and walls and fireplace.
And we're helping him get those
things in our shabby little office.
I know, Pop. I, uh, I, I know
that I, I... I wish I felt...
but I, I've been hoarding pennies
like a miser here in order to...
Most of my friends have
already finished college.
I, uh, I just feel like if
I didn't get away, I'd bust.
Yes, yes. You're right, son.
You see what I mean, don't you, Pop?
This town is no place for any man
unless he's willing to crawl to Potter.
And you've got talent,
son. I've seen it.
You get yourself an education.
Then get out of here.
Pop, you want a shock?
I think you're a great guy.
Oh, did you hear that, Annie?
I heard it. About time one
of you lunkheads said it.
I'm going to miss old Annie.
Pop, I think I'll get dressed
and go over to Harry's party.
Have a good time, son.
Here you are.
George! Hello!
You know my kid brother, George?
I'm going to put him through college.
- Hello, George!
- Hee-haw!
Oh, oh, Sam Wainwright.
How are you? When did you get here?
Oh, this afternoon. I thought
I'd give the kids a treat.
Old college graduate now, huh?
Yeah. Old Joe College
Wainwright, they call me.
Well, freshman, looks like
you're going to make it after all.
- Yep.
- Hey, hey!
Harry! You're the guy I want to see.
- The Coach has heard all about you.
- He has?
Yeah. He's followed every
game and his mouth's watering.
He wants me to find out if you're
going to come along with us.
Well, I eh, I gotta
make some dough first.
Well, you'd better make it fast.
We need great ends like you.
Not broken-down old
guys like this one!
- Hee-haw!
George! Welcome back!
Hello, Mr. Partridge, how are you?
Putting a pool under this
floor was a great idea.
Saved us another building.
Now, Harry, Sam, have a lot of fun.
There's lots of stuff
here to eat and drink.
- Lots of pretty girls around.
- Hey, George...
- Hello, Violet. How are you...
- Hello. What am I bid?
- George...
- Marty. Well, it's old home week.
Marty! Glad to see you.
- Do me a favor, will you, George?
- What's that?
- Well, you remember my kid sister, Mary?
- Oh, yeah. Yeah.
"Mamma wants you, Marty."
"Mama wants you." Remember?
Dance with her, will you?
Oh, me? Oh, well, I feel funny
enough already, with all these kids.
Aw, come on. Be a sport.
Just dance with her one time and
you'll give her the thrill of her life.
- Aw, go on.
- Hey, sis!
And don't be long, Marty! I don't
want to be a wet nurse for...
And the next thing I knew,
some guy came up and tripped me.
That's the reason
why I came in fourth.
If it hadn't been for that, that
race would have been a cinch.
I tried to find out who it was
later but I couldn't find out.
Nobody'd ever tell you who... whoever,
whoever it was because they'd be scared.
- They know what kind of a guy I am...
- You remember George?
- This is Mary. Well, I'll be seeing you.
- Well... well... well...
Now, to get back to my story, see...
Hey, this is my dance.
Oh, why don't you
stop annoying people?
Well, I'm sorry. Hey!
- Well, hello.
- Hello.
- You look at me as if you didn't know me.
- Well, I don't.
You've passed me on the
street almost every day.
Me?! Uh-huh.
Uh-uh.
That was a little girl named
Mary Hatch. That wasn't you.
O-yes,
o-yes, o-yes!
The big Charleston contest!
The prize? A genuine loving cup!
Those not tapped by the judges
will remain on the floor. Let's go!
- I'm not very good at this.
- Neither am I.
Okay. What can we lose?
Hey, you're wonderful!
What's the matter, Othello, jealous?
Did you know there's a
swimming pool under this floor?
And did you know that button behind
you causes this floor to open up?
And did you further know that George
Bailey is dancing right over that crack?
And I've got the key?
Stand back, everybody! Stand back!
They're cheering us. We must be good.
Get out! Oh, well...
Buffalo Gals, can't
you come out tonight?
Can't you come out tonight?
Buffalo Gals, can't
you come out tonight?
And dance
by the light of the moon.
- Oh, Hot dog! Just like an organ.
- Beautiful.
I told Harry I thought
I'd be bored to death.
You, you should have seen the
commotion in that locker room.
I, I had to knock off three people
to get this stuff we're wearing here.
Here, let me, let me hold
that old wet dress of yours.
Do I look as funny as you do?
I guess I'm not quite
the football type.
I... You, you look wonderful!
You know, if it wasn't me talking I'd
say you were the prettiest girl in town.
Well, why don't you say it?
Well, I don't know. Maybe I will
say it. How old are you anyway?
- Eighteen.
- Eighteen?!
Why, it was only last
year you were seventeen.
Too young or too old?
Oh, no, no. Just right.
Your age fits you.
Yes, sir, you look a little
older without your clothes on.
I, I mean, without a
dress. You look older.
I, I mean, younger. You
look... y-y-you just look...
- Oh, oh!
- Oh, no. I wanna...
- Sir, my train, please!
A pox upon me for a clumsy lout.
Your... your caboose, me lady.
- You may kiss my hand.
- Ummm.
Hey.
Hey, Mary.
As I was lumbering down the street,
down the street, down the street...
Okay then, I'll throw a rock
at the old Granville house.
Oh, no, don't! L-I
love that old house.
No. You see, you make a wish and
then try and break some glass.
And you got to be a pretty
good shot nowadays, too.
Oh, no, George, don't.
It's full of romance, that old place.
I'd like to live in it.
- In that
place?! - Uh-huh.
I wouldn't live in it
as a ghost. Now watch.
There's a window right on
the second floor there, see?
- What did you wish, George?
- Well, not just one wish. A whole hatful.
Mary, I know what
I'm gonna do tomorrow
and the next day and the next
year and the year after that.
I'm shaking the dust of this
crummy little town off my feet
and I'm gonna see the world.
Italy, Greece, the
Parthenon... the Colesseum.
Then I'm coming back here and go
to college and see what they know
and then I'm going to build things.
I'm gonna build air fields.
I'm gonna build skyscrapers
a hundred stories high.
I'm gonna build bridges a mile long.
Well, are you gonna throw a rock?
Hey, that's pretty good.
What'd you wish, Mary?
Buffalo Gals, Can't
you come out tonight?
Can't you come out tonight?
Buffalo Gal, Can't
you come out tonight?
And dance by the light of the moon.
What'd you wish when
you threw that rock?
- Oh, no.
- Come on, tell me.
If I told you, it might not come true.
What is it you want, Mary?
What do you want?
You, you want the moon?!
Just say the word and I'll throw
a lasso around it and pull it down.
Hey, that's a pretty good idea.
- I'll give you the moon, Mary.
- I'll take it. Then what?
Well then, you could swallow it,
and it'd all dissolve, see?
And the moon beams'd shoot out
of your fingers and your toes
and the ends of your hair.
Am I talking too much?
Yes!
Why don't you kiss her instead
of talking her to death?
How's that?
Why don't you kiss her instead
of talking her to death?
Want me to kiss her, huh?
Aw, youth is wasted
on the wrong people!
Hey, hey, hold on. Hey,
mister, come on back out here.
I'll show you some kissing
that'll put hair back on your head.
What are you...
Mary?
Okay, I give up. Where are you?
Over here, in the hydrangea bushes.
Here you are. Catch.
Wait a minute. What am I doing?
This is a very interesting situation!
- Please give me my robe.
- Hmm.
A man doesn't get in a
situation like this every day.
I'd like to have my robe.
Not in Bedford Falls anyway.
- Ooooouch! Oh!
- Gesundheit.
- George Bailey!
- This requires a little thought here.
Give me my robe!
I've read about things
like this, but I never...
Shame on you! I'm going
to tell your mother on you!
Oh, my mother's way up
on the corner over there.
I'll call the police!
They're way downtown.
They'd be on my side, too.
Then, then, then I'm going to scream!
Maybe I could sell tickets.
Let's see. No, no, the point
is, in order to get this robe...
I've got it. I'll make
a deal with you, Mary.
George! George!
George! Come on home. Quick.
You father's had a stroke!
What?!
Mary! Mary, I'm sorry. I've got to go.
Come on, George. Let's hurry!
- Did you get a doctor?
- Yes. Campbell's there now.
I think that's all we'll need you for,
George, I know you're anxious to make a train.
I have a taxi waiting downstairs.
I want the Board to know that
George gave up his trip to Europe
to help straighten things out
here these past few months.
Good luck to you at school, George.
- Thanks.
- Good luck! So long!
Now we come to the real
purpose of this meeting...
to appoint a successor to
our dear friend, Peter Bailey.
Mr. Chairman, I'd like
to get to my real purpose.
- Wait just a minute now.
- Wait for what?
I claim this institution is
not necessary to this town.
Therefore, Mr. Chairman, I make a
motion to dissolve this institution
and turn its assets and
liabilities over to the receiver.
Potter, you dirty, contemptible...
I'll wring his neck,
so help me, George,
- you hear what that buzzard...
- Mr. Chairman,
it's too soon after Peter Bailey's death to
talk about chloroforming the Building and Loan.
Peter Bailey died three months ago.
I second Mr. Potter's motion.
Very well. In that case, I'll ask the
two executive officers to withdraw.
But before you go,
I'm sure the whole Board wishes
to express its deep sorrow
- at the passing of Peter Bailey.
- Thank you very much.
It was his faith and devotion that
are responsible for this organization.
I'll go further than that.
I'll say that to the public, Peter
Bailey was the Building and Loan.
Oh, that's fine,
Potter, coming from you,
considering that you probably
drove him to his grave.
Peter Bailey was not a business man.
That's what killed him. Oh, I don't mean
any disrespect to him, God rest his soul.
He was a man of high
ideals, so-called.
But ideals without common
sense can ruin this town.
Now, you take this loan
here to Ernie Bishop...
you know, that fellow that sits around all
day on his brains in his taxi, you know.
I happen to know the bank turned
down this loan, but he comes here
and we're building him a house
worth five thousand dollars.
- Why?
- Well, I handled that, Mr. Potter.
You have all the papers there.
His salary, insurance. I can
personally vouch for his character.
- A friend of yours.
- Yes, sir.
You see, if you shoot pool
with some employee here,
you can come and borrow money.
What does that get us?
A discontented, lazy rabble
instead of a thrifty working class.
And all because a few starry-eyed
dreamers like Peter Bailey
stir them up and fill their heads
with a lot of impossible ideas.
- Now, I say...
- Just a minute. Just a...
Just a minute. Now,
hold on, Mr. Potter.
You're right when you say my father
was no business man. I know that.
Why he ever started this cheap penny-ante
Building and Loan, I'll never know.
But neither you nor anybody else can
say anything against his character,
because his whole life was...
Why, in the twenty-five years since
he and Uncle Billy started this thing,
he never once thought of himself.
Isn't that right, Uncle Billy?
He didn't save enough money to
send Harry to school, let alone me.
But he did help a few people get
out of your slums, Mr. Potter.
And what's wrong with that?
Why... here, you are
all businessmen here.
Doesn't it make them better citizens?
Doesn't it make them better customers?
You... you said that uh... what'd
you say just a minute ago...
They, they had to wait and save their money
before they even thought of a decent home.
Wait! Wait for what?
Until their children
grow up and leave them?
Until they're so old and
broken-down that they...
Do you know how long it takes a working
man to save five thousand dollars?
Just remember this, Mr. Potter, that
this rabble you're talking about...
they do most of the working and paying
and living and dying in this community.
Well, it is too much to have
them work and pay and live and die
in a couple of decent
rooms and a bath?
Anyway, my father didn't think so.
People were human beings to him,
but to you, a warped, frustrated
old man, they're cattle.
Well, in my book, he died a much
richer man than you'll ever be.
I'm not interested in your book. I'm
talking about the Building and Loan.
I know very well what
you're talking about.
You're talking about something you can't
get your fingers on, and it's galling you.
That's what you're
talking about, I know.
Well, I, I, I've said too much.
I... You're, you're the Board here.
You do what you want with this thing.
There's j-just one thing more though.
This town needs this
measly one-horse institution
if only to have some place where people
can come without crawling to Potter.
Come on, Uncle Billy.
Sentimental hogwash. I want my motion.
Oh boy, that was telling
him, George, old boy.
You shut his big mouth.
You should have heard him.
What happened? We
heard a lot of yelling.
Well, we're being voted out of
business after twenty-five years.
Easy come, easy go.
Here it is. "Help wanted
- Female."
You still want me hang around, George?
Yeah, I'll be right down.
Hey, you'll miss your train.
You're a week late for
school already. Go on.
- What's going on in there?
- Oh, never mind. Don't worry about that.
They're putting us out
of business. So what?
I can get another job.
I'm only fifty-five.
- Fifty-six.
- Go on, go on.
Hey, look, you gave up your boat trip, now
you don't want to miss college, too, do you?
George! George!
They voted Potter down.
They want to keep it going.
- Whoopee!
- You did it, George, you did it.
But they got one condition,
only one condition.
- What's that?
- That's the best part of it.
They've appointed George here as Executive
Secretary to take his father's place.
Oh, no! But, Uncle Billy...
You can keep him on. That's all right.
As Secretary you can
hire anyone you like.
Dr. Campbell, now let's
get this thing straight.
I'm leaving. I'm leaving right now.
I'm going to school.
This is my last chance.
Uncle Billy here, he's your man.
But, George, they'll vote
with Potter otherwise.
I know, I know, he didn't go.
That's right.
Not only that, but he gave his school money
to his brother, Harry, and sent him to college.
Harry became a football star.
Made second team All-American.
Yeah, but what happened to George?
George got four years older,
waiting for Harry to come back
and take over the Building and Loan.
Oh, there are plenty of jobs around
for somebody that likes to travel.
Look at this. There...
Venezuela oil fields
- Wanted. Man with construction experience.
Here's the Yukon, oh, right here -
wanted - man with engineering experience.
There she blows.
You know what the three most
exciting sounds in the world are?
- Uh-huh. - Breakfast is served,
lunch is served, dinner...
No, no, no, no!
- Anchor chains, plane motors,
and train whistles.  - Peanut?
There's the Professor now.
- Phil Beta Kappa Bailey! All-American. -
Old George Geographic Explorer Bailey.
What? No husky dogs? No sled?
Uncle Billy, you
haven't changed a bit.
- Nobody ever changes here, you know that.
- Oh, am I glad to see you.
- Say, where's mother?
- She's home, cooking the fatted calf.
- Come on. Let's go.
- Oh, wait! Wait, wait, wait, wait a minute.
George, Uncle Billy, I
want you to meet Ruth.
- Hello.
- How do you do.
- Ruth Dakin.
- Ruth Dakin Bailey, if you don't mind.
Huh?
Well, I wired you I had a surprise.
Here she is. Meet the wife.
Well, what do you know
- wife.
Well, how do you do. Congratulations.
What am I doing? Congratulations!
They're married... why
didn't you tell somebody?
...Oh, I can't wait
to see Tilly's face.
- Did you really marry him?
- Why, yes...
What's a pretty girl like you doing
marrying this two-headed brother of mine?
Well, I tell you.
It's purely mercenary.
My father offered him a job.
Oh, he gets you and a job?
Well, Harry's cup runneth over.
Uh, George, about that
job, Ruth spoke out of turn.
I never said I'd take it.
You've been holding the bag
here for four years, and...
well, I won't let you down, George.
I would like to... Oh, wait
a minute. I forgot the bags.
I'll be right back.
It was a surprise to me. This is the
new Mrs. Bailey, my nephew's wife.
Old, old friends of the family.
- Oh, of course, I've heard him speak of you.
- And I want you to tell you,
we're going to give the biggest
party this town ever saw.
Here, have some popcorn.
George, George, George, that's
all Harry ever talks about.
Uh, uh, uh, Ruth, uh, this,
uh, what about this job?
Oh, well, my father owns
a glass factory in Buffalo.
He wants to get Harry started
in the research business.
- Well, is it a good job?
- Oh, yes, very.
- Not much money, but, uh, good future, you know.
- I know.
Harry's a genius at research.
- My father just fell in love with him.
- And you did, too.
Oh boy, oh boy, oh boy, oh boy.
I feel so good. I could
spit in Potter's eye.
I think I will. I think I will.
What did you say? Huhh?
Oh, maybe I'd better go home.
Where's my hat? Where's my...
Oh! Oh, thank you,
George, which is mine?
- The middle one.
- Oh, thank you, George, old boy, old boy.
Now, look, if you'll point me in the right
direction... would you do that, George?
- Right down here.
- Oh... Old Building and Loan pal, huh...
Now you just turn this way and
go right straight down there.
That way, huh?
My Wild Irish rose...
I'm all right. I'm all
right. +++++++++++++++++++++++
La flor mas dulce que crece...
Hola, Mami.
No es nada.
- Que te parece ella?
- Oh, est bien.
Parece que puede mantener
a Harry en lnea recta.
Lo mantendr fuera de
Bedford Falls de todos modos.
Sabas que Mary Hatch
regres ya del Colegio?
- Ah-hah. -
Regres hace 3 das.
Hmmm...
- Linda chica, Mary.
- Hmmm.
De la clase que te ayudar a
encontrar las respuestas, George.
- Hmmm...
- Oh, deja de gruir.
Hmmm.
Podras darme una buena
razon para no llamar a Mary?
- Seguro, Sam Wainwright.
- Hmmm?
- Si, Sam est loco por Mary.
- Pero, ella no est loca por l.
Bien, como lo sabes?
- Acaso, lo discuti contigo?
- No.
- Bueno entonces, como lo sabes?
- Bueno, tengo ojos, no?
Pues, ella titila como una
lucirnaga en cuanto t andas cerca.
Oh...
Y ademas, Sam Wainwright est lejos
en N. York y t aqu en Bedford Falls.
Y todo vale en la guerra y el amor.
Bueno, no conozco de la guerra.
Madre ma, puedo ver atravez tuyo
justo atras del botn del collar...
- tratando de librarte
de m, hah? - Ah-hah.
Bien, aqu est tu
sombrero, que es tu prisa.
Muy bien, Madre, Old
Building y el conpinche Loan,
creo que saldr y encontrar la chica y
le dar un apasionado beso en el cuello.
Oh, George...
Ahora si me colocas en
la direccin correcta...
esta direccin?
Buenas noches, Mrs. Bailey.
- Perdname...
- Ahora, espera un minuto.
Creo que tengo una cita.
But uh, stick around,
fellows, just in case, huh?
We'll wait for you, baby.
- Hello,
George-Porgie! - What?
- Hey, uh... What gives?
- Nothing.
- Where are you going?
- Oh, I'm... probably end up down at the library.
Georgie, don't you ever get tired
of just reading about things?
- Yes. What are you doing tonight?
- Not a thing.
Are you game, Violet?
Let's make a night of it.
Oh, I'd love it,
Georgie. What'll we do?
Let's go out in the fields and take off
our shoes, and walk through the grass.
Huh?
Then we can to up to the falls. It's
beautiful up there in the moonlight,
and there's a green pool up there,
and we can, uh, s-swim in it.
Then we can climb Mt. Bedford,
and smell the pines and watch
the sunrise against the peaks,
and we'll stay up
there the whole night,
and everybody'll be talking and
there'll be a terrific scandal...
Georgie, have you gone crazy?
Walk in the grass in my bare feet?
- Why, it's ten miles up to Mt. Bedford.
- Shhh...
- You think just because you... -
O-O-Okay, just forget about the whole thing.
What are you doing, picketing?
Hello, Mary.
I just happened to be passing by.
Yes, so I noticed.
- Have you made up your mind?
- How's that?
Have you made up your mind?
- About what?
- About coming in.
Your mother just phoned and said you
were on your way over to pay me a visit.
My mother just called you?
Well, how did she know?
- Didn't you tell her?
- I didn't tell anybody.
I just went for a walk and
happened to be passing by, idiot.
What do you... went
for a walk. That's all.
- I'll be downstairs, mother.
- All right, dear.
Well, are you coming in or aren't you?
Well, I'll come in
for a minute. But I...
I didn't tell anybody I was
coming over here, you know.
- When did you get back?
- Tuesday.
Where'd you get that dress?
- Do you like it?
- It's all right.
I thought you'd go back to New York
like Sam and Angie, and the rest of them.
Oh, oh, I worked there a
couple of vacations. But...
I don't know... l-I
guess I was homesick.
Homesick? For Bedford Falls?
Yes, and my family,
and... Oh, everything.
Would you like to sit down?
All right, for a minute.
L-I still can't understand it though. You
know I didn't tell anybody I was coming here.
Would you rather leave?
No, I don't want to be rude.
Well, then sit down.
What's this?
Some joke, huh?
Well, I see it still smells
like pine needles around here.
Thank you.
And dance by the...
What's the matter?
Oh, oh, yeah... yeah...
Well, I...
It was nice about your brother
Harry, and Ruth, isn't it?
Oh... yeah, yeah. That's all right.
Don't you like her?
Well, of course, I
like her. She's a peach.
Oh, it's just marriage in general
you're not enthusiastic about, huh?
No. Uh, marriage is all right for
Harry and Marty and Sam and you.
Mary! Mary!
Who's down there with you?
It's George Bailey, Mother.
George Bailey?! What's he want?
I don't know.
What do you want?
Me?
Not a thing. L-I just
came in to get warm.
He's making violent
love to me, Mother.
You tell him to go right back home,
and don't you leave the house, either.
Sam Wainwright promised to
call you from New York tonight.
But your mother needn't...
You know I
- I didn't come here to...
What did you come here for then?
I don't know. You tell me.
You're supposed to be the
one that has all the answers.
- You tell me.
- Why don't you go home?
That's where I'm going. I don't know
why I came here in the first place.
- Good night.
- Good night!
Mary! Mary!
- The telephone. It's Sam!
- I'll get it.
Whatever were you doing
that you couldn't hear?
Mary, he'swaiting!
Hello.
I forgot my hat.
Hee-haw! Hello, Sam, how are you?
Aw, I'm great. Gee, it's
good to hear your voice again.
Oh, well, that's awfully
sweet of you, Sam.
There's an old friend of
yours here. George Bailey.
You mean old moss-back George?
Yes. Old moss-back George.
Hee-haw! Put him on.
W-Wait just a minute.
L-I'll call him. George!
He doesn't want to speak
to George, you idiot!
He does so. He asked for him.
Geo-George! George, Sam
wants to speak to you.
- Hi, Sam.
- Well, George Bailoffski!
Hey, a fine pal you are.
What're you trying
to do? Steal my girl?
W-W-What do you mean? Nobody's
trying to steal anybody's girl.
H-Here... here's Mary.
No, no, wait a minute. Wait a
minute. I want to talk to both of you.
- Here to you.
- Tell Mary to get on the extension.
- You tell him.
- Mother's on the extension. We...
I am not!
We can both hear. Come here.
We-We're listening, Sam.
Well look, I have a big deal coming
up that's going to make us all rich.
George, you remember that
night in Martini's Bar when, eh,
you told me you read someplace about
making plastics out of soybeans?
Jelly beans?
Shut up, will you?
Do you remember out of jelly
- ...out of soybeans?
Huh? Yeah, yeah,
yeah... soybeans. Yeah.
Well, listen. Dad snapped up the idea.
And he's going to build a
factory outside of Rochester.
How do you like that?
Rochester? Well, why Rochester?
Well, why not? Can you
think of anything better?
Oh, I don't know... It's just...
Why not right here?
Y-You remember that... that
old tool and machinery works?
W-Well, you tell your father
he can get that for a song.
And all the labor he wants, too.
Half the town was thrown out
of work when they closed down.
Is that so? Well, I'll tell him.
Hey, that sounds great.
Oh, baby, I knew you'd come through.
Now here's the point,
Mary... Mary, you're in on this, too.
Now listen, have you got any money?
- Money? Yeah... well, a little.
- Well now, listen.
I want you to put every cent
you've got into our stock, you hear?
And George, I may have a job for you,
that is, unless you're still married
to that broken-down Building and Loan.
Well, this is the biggest thing since radio.
And I'm letting you in on the ground floor.
Oh, Mary... Mary...
Well, l-I'm here.
Uh, would you tell that guy I'm giving
him the chance of a lifetime, you hear?
The chance of a lifetime.
H-He says it's the
chance of a lifetime.
Now you listen to me.
I don't want any plastics. I
don't want any ground floors.
And I don't want to get married
ever to anyone. You understand that?
I want to do what I want to do.
And you're... and you're...
- Oh, Mary... Mary...
- George... George... George...
Mary... Would you? Would you...
Here they come! Here they come!
Goodbye.
First Harry. Now George.
Annie, we're just two old maids now.
You speak for yourself, Mrs. B.
If either of you two see a
stranger around here, it's me.
Hey, look! There's
somebody driving this cab.
Bert the cop sent this over.
He said to float away to
Happy Land on the bubbles.
- Oh, look at this. Old Bert. Champagne!
- Good old Bert.
By the way, where are you two
going on this here now honeymoon?
Where are we going?
Look at this. There's
the kitty, Ernie.
Here, come on, count it, Mary.
I feel like a bootlegger's wife. Look!
You know what we're going to do?
We're going to shoot the works.
A whole week in New York.
A whole week in Bermuda.
The highest hotels,
the oldest champagne,
the richest caviar, the hottest
music, and the prettiest wife!
Wow! That does it! Then what?
- Then what, honey?
- After that, who cares?
That does it, come here,
come here, come here!
Don't look now, but there's something funny
going on over there at the bank, George.
I've never really seen one, but that's
got all the earmarks of being a run.
Hey, Ernie, if you got any money
in the bank, you better hurry.
- George, let's not stop. Let's go.
- Just a minute, dear.
- Oh-oh... - Please,
let's not stop, George.
I'll be back in a minute, Mary.
Well, hello, everybody.
Mrs. Thompson, how are you?
Charlie? What's the matter
here, can't you get in?
What is this, Uncle Billy? A holiday?
George...
Come on in, everybody. That's right.
Just come on in.
Now look, why don't you all sit down?
There are a lot of seats over there.
Just make yourself at home.
George, can I see you a minute?
- Why didn't you call me?
- I just did, but they said you left.
This is a pickle,
George. This is a pickle.
All right now, what
happened? How did it start?
Well, how does a thing like this ever start?
All I know is the bank called our loan.
- When?
- About an hour ago.
- I had to hand over all our cash.
- All of it?
Every cent of it and it
still was less than we owe.
Holy mackerel!
And then I got scared, George, and
closed the doors. I... I... I...
The whole town's gone crazy.
Yes, h-hello?
George, it's Potter.
- Hello?
- George,
there is a rumor around town that
you've closed your doors. Is that true?
Oh, well, I'm very glad to hear
that. George, are you all right?
- Do you need any police?
- Police? What's for?
Well, mobs get pretty
ugly sometimes, you know.
George, I'm going all out
to help in this crisis.
I've just guaranteed the bank
sufficient funds to meet their needs.
They'll close up for
a week and then reopen.
He just took over the bank.
I may lose a fortune, but I'm
willing to guarantee your people too.
Just tell them to bring their shares over
here, and I will pay fifty cents on the dollar.
Aw, you never miss a
trick, do you, Potter?
Well, you're gonna miss this one.
If you close your doors before
six P.M., you will never reopen.
George, was it a nice wedding?
Gosh, I wanted to be there.
Yeah...
You can take this one off now.
Now, just remember that this
thing isn't as black as it appears.
I have some news for you folks.
I was just talking to old man Potter and
he's guaranteed cash payments at the bank.
The bank's going to reopen next week.
But, George, I got my money here.
Did he guarantee this place?
Well, no, Charlie. I
didn't even ask him.
- We don't need Potter over here.
- I'll take mine now.
No, but you... you... you're
thinking of this place all wrong.
As if I had the money back in a safe.
The, the money's not here.
Well, your money's in Joe's
house... that's right next to yours.
And in the Kennedy House, and Mrs.
Macklin's house, and, and a hundred others.
Why, you're lending
them the money to build,
and then, they're going to pay
it back to you as best they can.
Now what are you going
to do? Foreclose on them?
I got two hundred and
forty-two dollars in here
and two hundred and forty-two
dollars isn't going to break anybody.
Okay, Tom. All right. Here
you are. You sign this.
- You'll get your money in sixty days.
- Sixty days?
Well, now that's what you agreed
to when you bought you shares.
- Tom... Tom... Did you get your money?
- No.
Well, I did. Old man Potter'll pay fifty
cents on the dollar for every share you got.
- Fifty cents on the dollar!
- Yes, cash!
- Well, what do you say?
- Now, Tom,
you have to stick to
your original agreement.
- Now give us sixty days on this.
- Okay, Randall.
- Are you going to go to Potter's?
- Better get half than nothing.
Tom! Tom!
Randall, now wait a minute, wait...
now listen... now listen to me.
L-I beg of you not to do this thing.
If Potter gets ahold of
this Building and Loan,
there'll never be another
decent house built in this town.
He's already got charge of the
bank. He's got the bus line.
He's got the department
stores. And now he's after us.
Why? Well, it's very simple.
Because we're cutting in
on his business, that's why.
And because he wants to
keep you living in his slums
and paying the kind
of rent he decides.
Joe, you had one of those Potter houses,
didn't you? Well, have you forgotten?
Have you forgotten what he
charged for that broken-down shack?
Here, Ed. You know, you remember last
year when things weren't going so well,
you couldn't make your payments.
You didn't lose your house, did you? Do
you think Potter would have let you keep it?
Ca-Can't you understand
what's happening here?
Don't you see what's happening?
Potter isn't selling. Potter's buying.
And why? Because we're panicky
and he's not. That's why.
He's picking up some bargains.
Now, We-We can get through
this thing all right.
We-We've got to stick together, though.
We've got to have faith in each other.
But my husband hasn't worked
in over a year and I need money.
- How am I going to live until the bank opens?
- I got doctor bills to pay.
- I need cash.
- I can't feed my kids on faith.
How much do you need?
Hey! I got two thousand dollars.
Here's two thousand dollars. This'll
tide us over until the bank reopens.
All right, Tom, how much do you need?
Two hundred and forty-two dollars.
Aw, Tom, just enough to tide
you over till the bank reopens.
I'll take two hundred
and forty-two dollars.
- There you are.
- That'll close my account.
Your account's still
here. That's a loan.
Okay. All right, Ed?
- I got three hundred dollars here, George.
- Alright, now, Ed...
wh-wh-what'll it take till the
bank opens? What do you need?
- Well, l-I suppose twenty dollars.
- Twenty dollars. Now you're talking.
Fine. Thanks, Ed.
All right now, Mrs. Thompson,
how much do you want?
- But it's your own money, George.
- Never mind about that.
- How much do you want?
- I can get along with twenty, all right.
- Twenty dollars.
- And I'll sign a paper.
You don't have to sign anything.
I know you-you'll
pay it when you can.
That's okay. All right, Mrs. Davis?
- Could I have
seventeen-fifty? - Seven...
Bless your heart, of course you
can have it. You got fifty cents?
- Seven...
- We're going to make it, George.
- They'll never close us up today!
- Six, five, four,
three, two, one...
Bingo!
We made it. Close the door,
Ernie. We made it. Look.
Look, we're still in business.
We're still got two bucks left.
Well, look, let's have some
of that. Let's celebrate, huh.
G-Get some glasses, Tilly.
Well, a couple of financial wizards.
Those Rockefellers.
Get a tray for these two great
big important simoleans here.
We'll save them for seed. A toast.
A toast! A toast to Mama
Dollar and to Papa Dollar,
and if you want to keep this old
Building and Loan in business,
- you better have a family real quick.
- I wish they were rabbits.
I wish they were, too.
Okay, let's put them in
safe and see what happens.
- Folks, folks, wedding
cigars! - Oh-oh... wedding!
Holy mackerel, I'm married!
Where's Mary? Mary...
Well, poor Mary.
Look, I've got a train to
catch. Well, the train's gone.
I wonder if Ernie's still
here with his taxicab?
George, there's a call for you.
Look, will you get my wife on the phone?
She's probably over at her mother's.
- Mrs. Bailey is on the phone.
- I don't want Mrs. Bailey.
I want my wife. Mrs. Bailey!
Mrs... oh, that's my wife.
Here, I'll take it in here.
Mary! Hello. Listen,
dear. I'm sorry...
What? Come home? What home?
Three-twenty Sycamore? Well, what...
whose home is that?
The Waldorf Hotel, huh?
Hey, this is the company's posters,
and the company won't like this.
How would you like to
get a ticket next week?
- Haven't you any romance in you?
- Sure I have, but I got rid of it.
Liver pills!
Who wants to see liver
pills on their honeymoon?
What we want is romantic places, beautiful
places... places George wants to go.
- Hey, Bert. Here he comes.
- Come on, we got to get this up. He's coming.
- Who?
- The groom, idiot.
This is their honeymoon.
Come on. Get that ladder.
What are they
- ducks?
- Get that ladder up here.
- All right, all right.
- Hurry up. Hurry up. Hurry up.
- I'm hurrying.
Hiya... Geo... uh...
good evening, sir.
Entree, Monsieur.
- Entree.
- Islands of Hawaii,
Where skies of blue are calling me.
Where balmy air and golden moonlight
caress The waving palms of Waikiki.
Welcome home, Mr. Bailey.
Well, I'll be...
Mary, where did you...
I Love You Truly,
Truly, Dear.
Life with Its Shadows,
Oh, Mary...
Life with Its Tears.
Remember the night we broke
the windows in this old house?
Fade into Dreams,
- This is what I wished for.
When I Feel You Are Near,
- Darling, you're
wonderful. I Love You Truly,
Truly, Dear.
- Martini, you rented a new house?
- Rent?
- You hear what he say, Mr. Bailey?
- What's that?
I own the house.
Me, Giuseppe Martini,
I own my own house.
No more we live like pigs
in this Potter's Field.
Hurry, Marie!
Come on... Bring the baby.
This is like a dream!
I'll take the kids in the car.
Oh, thank you, Mr. Bailey.
All right, kids. Here.
Get in here.
Now get right up on the seat there.
Get the... get the dog!
You've got a goat too!
- All right. Goodbye.
- Goodbye, everybody!
All in.
Mr. And Mrs. Martini, welcome home.
Good old George. He's
always making a speech.
Hee-haw!
- Sam Wainwright!
- Oh, who cares!
Bread! That this house
may never know hunger.
Salt! That life may
always have flavor!
And wine!! That joy and
prosperity may reign forever.
Enter the Martini castle!
Look, Mr. Potter, it's
no skin off my nose.
I'm just your little rent collector.
But you can't laugh off this
Bailey Park anymore. Look at it.
Congressman Black is here to see you.
Oh, tell the congressman
to wait. Go on.
Fifteen years ago, a half-dozen
houses stuck here and there.
There's the old cemetery,
squirrels, buttercups, daisies.
I used to hunt rabbits there myself.
Look at it today.
Dozens of the prettiest
little homes you ever saw.
Ninety per cent owned by suckers
who used to pay rent to you!
Your Potter's Field, my dear Mr.
Employer, is becoming just that.
And are the local yokels making with
those David and Goliath wisecracks.
Oh, they are, are they?
Even though they know the Baileys
never made a dime out of it.
You know very well why,
the Baileys were all chumps.
Every one of these homes is worth twice
what it cost the Building and Loan to build.
- If I were you, Mr. Potter...
- Well, you are not me.
As I say, it's no skin off my nose.
But one of these days this bright young man
is going to be asking George Bailey for a job.
The Bailey family has been a
boil on my neck long enough.
- Yes, sir?
- Come in here.
We just stopped in town to take a
look at the new factory, and then
- we're going to drive on down to Florida.
- Oh...
- Why don't you have your friends join us?
- Why, sure.
Hey, why don't you kids
drive down with us, huh?
Oh, I'm afraid I
couldn't get away, Sam.
Still got the nose to
the old grindstone, eh?
Jane, I offered to let George in on the ground
floor in plastics and he turned me down cold.
- Oh, now don't rub it in.
- I'm not rubbing it in.
Well, I guess we better run along.
Awfully glad to have met you, Mary.
- Nice meeting you.
- Goodbye.
- Goodbye, George.
- So long, George.
- See you in the funny papers.
- Goodbye, Sam.
- So long, Mary.
- So long, Sam. Have fun.
Thanks for dropping around.
Florida! Hee-haw!
Hee-haw.
Thank you, sir.
Quite a cigar, Mr. Potter.
You like it? I'll send you a box.
Well, I, uh, I suppose I'll
find out sooner or later,
but just what exactly did
you want to see me about?
George, now that's just what
I like so much about you.
George, I'm an old man,
and most people hate me.
But I don't like them, either,
so that that makes it all even.
You know, just as well as I do, that I
run practically everything in this town
but the Bailey Building and Loan.
You know, also, that for a number of years I've
been trying to get control of it or kill it.
But I haven't been able to do it.
You have been stopping me.
In fact, you have beaten me, George,
and as anyone in this county can
tell you, that takes some doing.
Take during the
depression, for instance.
You and I were the only
ones that kept our heads.
You saved the Building and
Loan, I saved all the rest.
Yeah. Well, most people
say you stole all the rest.
The envious ones say
that, George, the suckers.
Now, I have stated
my side very frankly.
Now, let's look at your side.
Young man, twenty-seven, twenty-eight,
married, making say... forty a week.
- Forty-five! -
Forty-five. Forty-five.
Out of which, after
supporting your mother
and paying your bills, you're able
to keep, say ten, if you skimp.
But, George Bailey is not
a common, ordinary yokel.
He's an intelligent,
smart, ambitious young man,
who hates his job, who hates the
Building and Loan, almost as much as I do.
A young man who's been dying to get
out on his own ever since he was born.
A young man... the smartest
one of the crowd, mind you,
a young man who has to sit by
and watch his friends go places,
because he's trapped.
Yes, sir, trapped into frittering his life away
playing nursemaid to a lot of garlic-eaters.
Do I paint a correct
picture, or do I exaggerate?
Oh, what's your point, Mr. Potter?
- My point? My point is, I want to hire you.
- Hire me?
I want you to manage my
affairs, run my properties.
George, I'll start you out at
twenty thousand dollars a year.
Twenty thous... twenty
thousand dollars a year?
You wouldn't mind living
in the nicest house in town,
buying your wife a
lot of fine clothes,
a couple of business trips to New York
a year, maybe once in a while Europe.
You wouldn't mind
that, would you, George?
Would I?
Y-You're not talking to somebody
else around here, are you?
You know, th-this is me, you
remember me? George Bailey.
Oh, yes, George Bailey.
Whose ship has just come in,
provided he has enough
brains to climb aboard.
Holy mackerel!
Well, how about the Building and Loan?
Oh, confound it, man!
Are you afraid of success?
I'm offering you a three-year contract at
twenty thousand dollars a year, starting today.
Is it a deal, or isn't it?
Well, Mr. Potter, I...
I... I know I ought to jump at
the chance but I... I just, uh,
l-I wonder if-if it would be possible for you
to give me twenty-four hours to think it over?
Sure, sure, sure.
You go on home and talk
about it to your wife.
- I'd like to do that.
- Yeah.
In the meantime, I'll
draw up the papers.
- All right, sir.
- Okay, George?
Okay, Mr. Potter.
No, no, no, no. Wait a
minute here. Wait a minute.
I don't need twenty-four hours.
I, I don't have to talk to anybody.
I know right now, and
the answer is no! No!
Doggone it!
You sit around here and
you spin your little webs
and you think the whole world
revolves around you and your money.
Well, it doesn't, Mr. Potter.
In the... in the whole vast
configuration of things,
I'd say you were nothing
but a scurvy little spider.
You... and that goes for you, too.
And it goes for you, too.
If you wouldn't mind living
in the nicest house in town.
Buying your wife a
lot of fine clothes.
Going to New York on a business
trip a couple of times a year.
Maybe to Europe once in a while.
I know what I'm going to do tomorrow
and the next day and next
year and the hear after that.
I'm shaking the dust of this crummy little
town off my feet, and I'm going to see the world
and then I'm going to build things.
I'm going to build air fields.
I'm going to build skyscrapers
a hundred stories high.
I'm going to build
a bridge a mile long.
What is it you want,
Mary? What? Y-You want the moon?
If you do, just say the word,
I'll throw a lasso around it
and pulls her down for you.
Buffalo Gals, won't
you come out tonight,
Won't you come out tonight,
Won't you come out tonight.
Buffalo Gals, won't
you come out tonight,
And...
- Hi.
Mary Hatch!
Wh-Why in the world did you
ever marry a guy like me?
To keep from being an old maid.
You could have married Sam
Wainwright and anybody else in town.
I didn't want to marry
anybody else in town.
I want my baby to look like you.
You didn't even have a honeymoon.
I promised you... your what?
My baby.
You... You-You-You-You-You-You-You...
Mary, you're on the nest?
George Bailey lassoes stork.
Lassoes the stork!
What do you...
You mean...
you-you-you...
What-what-what is
it, a boy or a girl?
Uh-hm.
Now, you've probably already guessed
that George never leaves Bedford Falls.
No!
Mary had her baby, a boy.
Then she had another one, a girl.
Day after day she worked away remaking
the old Granville house into a home.
Night after night, George
came back late from the office.
Potter was bearing down hard.
Then came a war.
Ma Bailey and Mrs. Hatch
joined the Red Cross and sewed.
Mary had two more babies but
still found time to run the U.S.O.
Sam Wainwright made a fortune
in plastic hoods for planes.
Potter became head of the draft board.
One-A...
one-A... one-A
Gower and Uncle Billy sold war bonds.
Bert the cop was wounded in
North Africa, got the Silver Star.
Ernie, the taxi-driver,
parachuted into France.
Marty helped capture
the Remagen Bridge.
Harry, Harry Bailey topped them all.
A Navy flier, he shot
down fifteen planes.
Two of them as they were about to
crash into a transport full of soldiers.
- Yes, but George...
- George?
Four-F on account of his ear, George
fought the battle of Bedford Falls.
Hold on, hold on, hold on now.
Don't you know there's a war on?
Air raid warden...
paper drives... scrap
drives... rubber drives...
Like everybody else, on
V-E day he wept and prayed.
On V-J day, he wept and prayed again.
Joseph, now show him
what happened today.
Yes, sir.
This morning, day before Christmas,
about ten A.M., Bedford Falls Time.
Hi, Ernie, look at that.
Gonna snow again.
What do you mean it's gonna
snow? Look at the headlines.
I know, I know, George.
And it's marvelous.
Commander Harry Bailey!
Mr. Gower, look at this.
The second page. Now
look, this is for you.
This is for you. That's for you.
- Thanks.
- See you again.
Be sure you spell the name right.
Hello, Billy, how are you?
Extra! Extra! Read all about it!
George! George! It's Harry now
on long distance from Washington.
- Harry! What do you know about that!
- He reversed the charges. It's okay, isn't it?
Reverse the charges...
of course it's for a hero.
Harry...
Oh, you old seven
times of a son of a gun.
Congratulations!
How's mother standing it?
She did?
What do you know...
Mother had lunch with
the President's wife.
Wait till Martha hears about this.
- What did they have to eat? -
Wha-What did they have to eat?
H-H-Harry, you should see what
they're cooking up in the town for you.
Oh, they are?
The Navy's going to fly
mother home this afternoon.
In a plane?
What? Uncle Billy?
- Has Uncle Billy come in yet?
- No, he stopped at the bank first.
No, he's not here right
now, Harry. But look...
- George... ...tell me about it.
...George, tha-that man's here again.
- What man? -
B-B-Bank... examiner.
Oh, oh. Uh, uh,
Harry, talk to Eustace
for a minute, will you?
I'll be right back. Well...
- Harry...
- Good morning, sir.
Carter, bank examiner.
- Mr. Carter, Merry Christmas.
- Merry Christmas.
We're all excited around here.
My brother just got the
Congressional Medal of Honor.
The president just decorated him.
Well, I guess they do those things.
Well, I trust you had a good year.
Good year?
Uh, well, between you and
me, Mr. Carter, we're broke.
Yeah, very funny.
Uh, w-well... Now, come
right in here, Mr. Carter.
Oh, I shouldn't wonder when you okay reverse
charges on personal long distance calls.
George, shall we hang up?
No, no. He wants to talk to
Uncle Billy. You just hold on.
Now, if you'll cooperate, I'd
like to finish with you by tonight.
I want to spend Christmas
in Elmira with my family.
I don't blame you at all, Mr. Carter.
Just step right in
here. We'll fix you up.
December twenty-fourth...
Eight thousand.
Merry Christmas, Mr. Potter...
Well, good morning, Mr. Potter?
What's the news?
Oh, well, well, well. Harry
Bailey wins Congressional Medal.
That couldn't be one
of the Bailey boys?
You just can't keep those Baileys
down, now can you, Mr. Potter.
How does slacker
George feel about that?
Very jealous. Very jealous.
He only lost three
buttons off his vest.
Of course, slacker George would have
gotten two of these medals if he had gone.
Bad ear.
Yes. After all, Potter, some people
like George had to stay at home.
Not every heel was
in Germany and Japan.
- Oh, good morning, Mr. Bailey.
- Good morning, Horace.
- I guess you forgot something.
- Huh?
- You forgot something.
- What?
- Well, aren't you going to make a deposit?
- Oh, sure, sure I am.
Well, then it's usually customary
to bring the money with you.
Huh? Oh, shucks...
Well, I knew I had...
- How about that finger there?
- Hmm? Well, I...
Bailey...
Take me back there. Hurry up.
Come on, look sharp.
Take me back.
Just make yourself at home, Mr.
Carter. I'll get those books for you.
Oh, hello, Vi.
George, can I see you for a second?
Why, of course you can.
Come on in the office here.
Uncle Billy, talk to Harry.
He's on the telephone.
Hurry, Uncle Billy, hurry.
Long distance, Washington.
Hey, here's Harry on the phone.
Harry, your nephew, remember?
Here he is. Hurry up.
Hello... hello.
Y-Y-Yes, Harry.
Yes... everything...
everything's fine.
I should have my head examined.
Eight thousand dollars.
It's got to be somewhere.
Here you are.
Character?
If I had any character, I'd...
It takes a lot of character to leave
your home town and start all over again.
No, George, don't...
- Now here, now you're broke, aren't you?
- I know, but...
What do you want to do,
hock your furs and that hat?
Want to walk to New York?
You know, they charge for
meals and rent up there
just the same as they
do in Bedford Falls.
- Yeah, sure.
- It's a loan.
That's my business. Building and Loan.
Besides, you'll get a job.
Good luck to you.
I'm glad I know you, George Bailey.
Say hello to New York for me.
Yeah, yeah... sure, I will.
Now let's hear from
you once in a while.
Hmm.
- Merry Christmas, Violet.
- Merry Christmas, George.
- Mr. Bailey.
- Oh, Mr. Carter,
I'm sorry. I'll be right with you.
- Uncle Billy in?
- Yeah, he's in his office.
Unc... What's going on?
The bank examiner's here, and I...
- He's here?
- Yeah, yeah.
He wants the accounts payable...
- What's the matter with you?
- Come here.
- Eustace.
- Yeah?
Come here a minute.
Did you see Uncle Billy
with any cash last night?
He had it on his desk counting
it before he closed up.
Now look, did you buy anything?
- Nothing. Not even a stick of gum.
- All right, all right.
Now, we'll go over every step
you took since you left the house.
All right. This way.
And did you put the
envelope in your pocket?
Yeah... maybe, maybe, maybe...
Maybe-Maybe! I don't want any maybe.
We've got to find that money!
- I'm no good to you, George. I...
- Uncle Billy, do you...
Listen to me. Do you have
any secret place hiding place?
Listen to me, listen
to me! Think! Think!
I can't think anymore, George.
I can't think anymore. It hurts...
Where's that money, you
silly, stupid old fool?!
Where's that money?
Do you realize what this means?
It means bankruptcy
and scandal, and prison!
That's what it means.
One of us is going to jail!
Well, it's not gonna be me.
Hello, darling.
Hello daddy, hello daddy.
How do you like it?
We're going to put...
Bless you!
Did you bring the wreath?
- Yes, Daddy, did you bring the Christmas wreath?
- What wreath?
Oh, that's the Merry Christmas
Wreath for the window.
No. I left it at the office.
- Is it snowing?
- Yeah, just started.
- Where's your coat and hat?
- Left them at the office.
- What's the matter?
- Nothing's the matter. Everything's all right.
Go on, Pete, you're a big boy.
You can put the star up.
Way up at the top.
That's it.
All right.
Fill in that little
bare spot right there.
That's it.
Isn't it wonderful about Harry?
We're famous, George.
I'll bet I had fifty calls today
about the parade, the banquet.
Your mother's so excited, she...
Must she keep playing that?
I have to practice it for
the party tonight, Daddy.
Mommy says we can stay up till
midnight and sing Christmas carols.
Can you sing, Daddy?
Better hurry and shave.
The families will be here soon.
Families! I... I don't
want the families over here.
Come on out in the kitchen
with me while I finish dinner.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
Have a hectic day?
Oh, yeah. Another big
red-letter day for the Bailey's.
Daddy, the Brown's next door
have a new car. You should see it.
Well, what's the matter with our
car? Isn't it good enough for you?
Yes, Daddy.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
Excuse you for what?
I burped!
All right, darling, you're excused.
Now go upstairs and see
what little Zuzu wants.
Zuzu. W-What's the matter with Zuzu?
Oh, she's got a cold. She's in bed.
Caught it coming home from school.
They gave her a flower for a prize
and she didn't want to crush it
so she didn't button up her coat.
- What is it, a sore throat or what?
- Just a cold.
- The doctor says it's nothing serious.
- The doctor?
- Was the doctor here?
- Yes, I called him right away.
- He says it's nothing to worry about.
- Is she running a temperature?
- What is it? - Just a
teensy one, ninety-nine, six.
- She'll be all right.
- Gosh, it's this old house.
I don't... I don't know why
we don't all have pneumonia.
This drafty old barn! Might as
well be living in a refrigerator.
Why did we have to live here in the first place
and stay around this measly, crummy old town?
George, what's wrong?
Wrong? Everything's wrong.
You call this a happy family?
Why did we have to
have all these kids?
Dad, how do you spell 'frankincense'?
I don't know. Why, ask your mother.
- Where're you going?
- Going up to see Zuzu.
He told me to write
a play for tomorrow.
F-R-A-N-K-l-N...
Hi, Daddy.
- Well, what happened to you?
- I won a flower.
Wait now. W-Where do
you think you're going?
Want to give my flower a drink.
All right, all right,
here, give Daddy the flower.
I'll give it a drink. All right, here.
- Look, Daddy... paste it.
- Yeah, all right...
Now, I'll paste this together.
Now, there it is, good as new.
All right, give the flower a drink.
- Now, will you do something for me?
- What?
Will you try to get some sleep?
I'm not sleepy. I want
to look at my flower.
I know, I know, but
you just go to sleep
and then you can dream about
it, and it'll be a whole garden.
- It will?
- Uh-huh.
- Telephone!
- I'll get it.
Hello.
Yes, this is Mrs. Bailey.
Oh, thank you, Mrs. Welch.
I'm sure she'll be all right.
The doctor says that she ought to be out
of bed in time to have her Christmas dinner.
- Is that Zuzu's teacher?
- Yes.
Let me speak to her.
Hello. Hello, Mrs. Welch?
This is George Bailey.
I'm Zuzu's father.
Say, what kind of a
teacher are you anyway?
What do you mean sending her
home like that, half naked?
Do you realize she'll probably end
up with pneumonia on account of you?
- George!
- Is this the sort of thing
we pay taxes for
- to have teachers... to have teachers like you?
Stupid, silly, careless people who send
our kids home without any clothes on?
You know, maybe my kids
aren't the best-dressed kids,
and maybe they don't
have any decent clothes...
Aw, that stupid...
He-Hello, Mrs. Welch.
L-l-I want to apologize.
Hel-lo... hello...
- She's hung up. -
L-l-I'll hang her up.
Now, who do you think you are?
What is that?
Hello? Who is this?
Oh, Mr. Welch?
Okay, that's fine, Mr. Welch.
Gives me a chance to tell you
what I really think of your wife.
- George...
- Will you get out and let me handle this?
Hello?
Hello? What? Oh, you will, huh?
Okay, Mr. Welch. Any time
you think you're man enough.
Hello... any...
Oh...
Daddy, how do you spell "Hallelujah?"
How should I know? What do
you think I am, a dictionary?
Tommy, stop that! Stop it!
Janie, haven't you leaned that silly tune
yet? You've played it over and over again.
Now stop it! Stop it!
I'm sorry, Mary.
Janie, I'm sorry.
I didn't mean...
You go on and practice.
Pete, I owe you an apology, too.
I'm sorry.
What do you want to know?
Nothing, Daddy.
What's the matter with everybody?
Janie, go on. I told you to practice.
- Now, go on, play.
- Oh, Daddy...
George, why must you
torture the children?
Why don't you...
Mary...
Bedford
two-four-seven, please.
- Is Daddy in trouble?
- Yes, Pete.
- Shall I pray for him?
- Yes, Janie, pray very hard.
- Me, too?
- You, too, Tommy.
Hello, Uncle Billy?
I'm in trouble, Mr. Potter.
I need help.
Through some sort of an accident my
company's short in their accounts.
The bank examiner's got there today.
I've got to raise eight
thousand dollars immediately.
Oh, so that's what the reporters
wanted to talk to you about?
- The reporters?
- Yes,
they called me up from
your Building and Loan.
Oh, there's a man over there
from the D.A.'s office, too.
He's looking for you.
Please help me, Mr. Potter.
Help me, won't you, please?
Can't you see what
it means to my family?
I'll pay any sort of a bonus
on the loan, any interest
if you still want the
Building and Loan. I'm...
George, could it possibly be there's
a slight discrepancy in the books?
No, sir. There's nothing
wrong with the books.
I've just misplaced
eight thousand dollars.
I can't find it anywhere.
You misplaced eight thousand dollars?
Yes, sir.
Have you notified the police?
No, sir. L-I didn't
want the publicity.
Harry's homecoming tomorrow...
They're gonna believe that one.
What've you been doing, George?
Playing the market with
the company's money?
No, sir, no, sir. I haven't.
What is it, a woman then?
You know, it's all over town that
you've been giving money to Violet Bick.
- What!
- Not that it makes any difference to me,
but why did you come to me?
Why don't you go to Sam Wainwright
and ask him for the money?
I can't get ahold of
him. He's in Europe.
Well, what about all
your other friends?
They don't have that
kind of money, Mr. Potter.
You know that. You're the only
one in town that can help me.
I see.
I've suddenly become quite important.
Wha-What kind of security
would I have, George?
- Have you got any stocks?
- No, sir.
Bonds? Real estate?
Collateral of any kind?
I have some life insurance, a
fifteen thousand dollar policy.
Yes... how much is your equity in it?
- Five hundred dollars.
- Five hundred dollars!
And you ask me to lend
you eight thousand.
Look at you.
You used to be so cocky!
You were going to go out
and conquer the world.
You once called me a
warped, frustrated old man.
What are you but a warped
frustrated young man?
A miserable little clerk crawling in here
on your hands and knees and begging for help.
No securities, no stocks, no bonds,
nothing but a miserable little five hundred
dollar equity in a life insurance policy.
You're worth more dead than alive.
Why don't you go to the
riff-raff you love so much
ask them to let you
have eight thousand?
You know why?
Because they'd run you
out of town on a rail.
But I tell you what I'm
going to do for you, George.
Since the state
examiner is still here,
as a stock holder of
the Building and Loan,
I'm going to swear out a
warrant for your arrest.
Misappropriation of funds,
manipulation, malfeasance...
All right, George, go ahead, George.
You can't hide in a
little town like this.
Bill? This is Potter.
Joe! Merry Christmas!
- Glad you come.
- Thank you.
- How about some of that good spaghetti?
- We got everything.
God...
Oh, God...
Dear Father in Heaven,
I'm not a praying man,
but if you're up there,
and you can hear me, show me the way.
I'm at the end of my rope. I...
Show me the way, God.
Are you all right, George?
Want someone to take you home?
Why you drink so much, my friend?
Please go home, Mr. Bailey.
This is Christmas Eve.
Bailey? Which Bailey?
This is Mr. George Bailey.
And the next time you talk to my
wife like that, you'll get worse.
She cried for an hour.
It isn't enough she slaves
teaching your stupid kids
how to read and write, and
you have to bawl her out, eh.
You get out of here, Mr. Welch!
Now wait. I want to pay for my drink.
Never mind the money.
You get out of here quick.
- All right.
- You hit my best friend. Get out!
You all right, George?
Who was that?
He gone. No worry.
His name is Welch. He no
come in to my place no more.
Oh, Welch. That's
what I get for praying.
The last time he come in
here. You hear that, Nick?
Yes, you bet.
Where's my insurance policy? Oh, here.
- Oh, no, please, no go out this way, Mr. Bailey.
- I'm all right.
No, no, you no feel so
good. Sit down and rest.
- I'm all right.
- Please no go away. Please!
What do you think you're doing?
Now look what you did.
My great-grandfather
planted this tree.
Hey, you! Hey, you!
Come back here, you drunken fool!
Get this car out of here!
Hey, what's the matter with
you? Look where you're going!
Help!
Help! Help! Help!
Help! Help!
Help!
Help! Help! Help! Help!
Help! Help! Help!
I didn't have time to get
some stylish underwear.
My wife gave me this
on my last birthday.
I passed away in it.
Oh, Tom Sawyer's drying out, too.
You should read the new book
Mark Twain's writing now.
How did you happen to fall in?
I didn't fall in. I
jumped in to save George.
You what? To... to save me?
Well, I did, didn't I? You didn't
go through with it, did you?
- Go through with what?
- Suicide.
Well, it's against the law
to commit suicide around here.
Yeah, it's against the
law where I come from, too.
- Where do you come from?
- Heaven.
I had to act quickly.
That's why I jumped in.
I knew if I were drowning
you'd try to save me.
And you see, you did, and
that's how I saved you.
Very funny.
Your lip's bleeding, George.
Yeah, I got a bust in the jaw in
answer to a prayer a little bit ago.
Oh, no, no, no, George, I'm
the answer to your prayer.
That's why I was sent down here.
How do you know my name?
Oh, I know all about you. I've
watched you grow up from a little boy.
- What are you, a mind reader or something?
- Oh, no.
- Well, who are you then?
- Clarence Odbody, A-S-2.
Odbody... A-S-2.
Wh-Wh-What's that A-S-2?
Angel Second Class.
Cheerio, my good man.
Oh, brother...
I wonder what Martini
put in those drinks?
Hey, what's... with you...
wh-wh-what-did you
say just a minute ago?
Why'd you want to save me?
That's what I was sent down
for. I'm your guardian angel.
I wouldn't be a bit surprised.
Ridiculous of you to think
of killing yourself for money.
- Eight thousand dollars.
- Yeah, I'll say. Just things like that.
Now how do you know that?
I told you. I'm your guardian angel.
I know everything about you.
Well, you look about like
the kind of an angel I'd get.
Sort of a fallen angel, aren't you?
What happened to your wings?
I haven't won my wings yet. That's
why I'm an angel second class.
I don't know whether I like it very much being
seen around with an angel without any wings.
Oh, l-I've got to earn them
and you'll help me, won't you?
- Sure, sure. How?
- By letting me help you.
Only one way you can help me.
Y-You don't happen to have
eight thousand bucks on you?
Oh, no, no. We don't
use money in heaven.
Oh, that's right, I keep forgetting.
Comes in pretty handy down here, bub.
Oh, tut, tut, tut.
I found it out a little late.
I'm worth more dead than alive.
Now look, you mustn't talk like that.
I won't get my wings with that attitude.
You just don't know
all that you've done.
If it hadn't been for you...
Yeah, if it hadn't been for me,
everybody'd be a lot better off.
My wife, and my kids, and my friends.
And my... Look, little fellow, why, you
go off and haunt somebody else, will you?
No, no, you don't
understand. I've got my job.
Aw, shut up, will you?
Hmmm, this isn't gonna be so easy.
Yeah! So you still think killing yourself
would make everyone feel happier, eh?
Oh, I don't know. I
guess you're right.
I suppose it would have been better
if I'd never been born at all.
- What'd you say?
- I said I wish I'd never been born.
Oh, you mustn't say things like that.
You...
Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
That's an idea.
What do you think?
Yeah, that'll do it.
All right.
You've got your wish.
You've never been born.
You don't have to make
all that fuss about it.
What did you say?
You've never been
born. You don't exist.
You haven't a care in the world.
No worries, no obligations, no
eight thousand dollars to get,
no Potter looking for
you with the sheriff.
- Say something else in that ear.
- Sure. You can hear out of it.
Well, that's the doggonedest thing.
I haven't heard anything out
of that ear since I was a kid.
Must have been that
jump in that cold water.
Your lip's stopped
bleeding, too, George.
What do you know about that?
What's happened?
It's stopped snowing out, hasn't it?
Well, I, uh... What's happened here?
What I need is a couple
of good stiff drinks.
How about you, angel,
you want a drink?
Come on, soon as these
clothes of ours are dry...
Those are dry.
What do you know about that?
Stove's hotter than I thought.
Now, come on, get your clothes on, and
we'll stroll up to my car and get...
Oh, I'm sorry. I'll stroll, you fly.
I can't fly. I haven't got my wings.
You haven't got your
wings. Yeah, that's right.
What's the matter?
Well, this is where I left
my car and it isn't here.
You have no car.
Well, I had a car and it was right
here. I guess somebody moved it.
- Good evening.
- Oh, say... Hey...
wh-where's my car.
- I beg your pardon?
- My car, my car.
I'm the fellow that owns the
car that ran into your tree.
What tree? What do
you mean, what tree?
This tree. Here. I ran into it.
Cut a big gash in
the side of it there.
You must mean two other trees.
You had me worried.
One of the oldest
trees in Pottersville.
Pottersville. Why,
you mean Bedford Falls.
I mean Pottersville.
Don't you think I know where I live?
What's the matter with you?
Oh, I don't know. Either
I'm off my nut, or he is.
...or you are.
It isn't me!
Well, maybe I left the car up at
Martini's. Well, come on, Gabriel.
- Clarence!
- Clarence! Clarence!
That's all right. Go on in.
Martini is a friend of mine.
There's a place to sit down, sit down.
Oh, hello, Nick. Hey, where's Martini?
- You want a Martini?
- No, no, Martini.
- Your boss. Where is he?
- Look, I'm the boss.
You want a drink or don't you?
Okay, all right. Double
bourbon, will you? Quick, huh.
Okay.
What's yours?
I was just thinking.
Uh... It's been so long since I...
Look, Mister, I'm standing here
waiting for you to make up your mind.
That's a good man.
I was just thinking, uh,
of a flaming rum punch.
No, it's not cold enough for
that. Not nearly cold enough.
Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
I got it.
Mulled wine, heavy on the
cinnamon and light on the cloves.
Off with you, me lad, and be lively!
Hey, look, Mister, we serve hard drinks
in here for men who want to get drunk fast.
And we don't need any characters around to
give the joint atmosphere. Is that clear?
Or do I have to slip you
my left for a convincer?
What's he talking about?
Nick, Nick, just give him
the same as mine. He's okay.
Okay.
What's the matter with him?
I never saw Nick act like that before.
You'll see a lot of
strange things from now on.
Oh, yeah.
Hey, li-li-little
fellow, you worry me.
- You know, y-y-you got
someplace to sleep? - No.
You don't, huh?
- Well, y-y-you
got any money? - No.
No wonder you jumped in the river.
I jumped in the river to save
you so I could get my wings.
- Oh, that's
right. - Oh-oh.
- Somebody's just made it.
- Made what?
Every time you hear a bell ring, it means
that some angel's just got his wings.
Look, I think maybe you better not
mention getting your wings around here.
Why? Don't they believe in angels?
A... Yeah, they believe in angels.
Oh, oh! Why should they be
surprised when they see one?
Aw, he never grew up. He's...
How old are you, anyway, Clarence?
Two hundred and
ninety-three, uh, next May.
That does it!
Out you two pixies go, through
the door or out the window.
Look, Nick, what's wrong?
And that's another thing. Where
do you come off calling me Nick?
Well, Nick, that's your name.
What's that got to do with it? I
don't know you from Adam's off ox.
Hey! Hey, you, rummy
there! Come here! Come here!
Didn't I tell you never to come
panhandling around here, huh?
Mr. Gower!
What... what is he...
Mr. Gower! This is George Bailey!
- Don't you know me?
- No. No.
Throw 'em out. Throw 'em out!
Mr. Gower... Hey, what is...
Hey, Nick, Nick... Isn't
that Mr. Gower, the druggist?
You know, that's another
reason for me not to like you.
That rum head spent twenty years
in jail for poisoning a kid.
If you know him, you must
be a jailbird yourself.
Uh, would you show these
gentlemen to the door?
Sure. This way, gentlemen.
Stay out! Stay out!
Hey! Get me!
I'm giving out wings!
You see, George, you were not there
to stop Gower from putting
that poison into the capsule...
What do you mean I wasn't there?
I remember distinctly. What the...
hey, what's going on around here?
Why, this ought to be Martini's place.
Look, who are you?
I told you, George.
I'm your guardian angel.
Yeah, yeah, I know. You told me that.
What else are you? What are you?
- You are hypnotist?
- No, of course not.
Well, then why am I seeing
all these strange things?
Don't you understand, George?
It's because you were not born.
Then if I wasn't born, who am I?
You're nobody. You have no identity.
Oh, what do you mean, no
identity? My name's George Bailey.
There is no George Bailey.
You have no papers, no cards, no driver's
license, no 4-F card, no insurance policy.
They're not there, either.
- What?
- Zuzu's petals.
You've been given a
great gift, George...
a chance to see what the world
would be like without you.
Now wait a minute here.
Wait a minute here.
Aw, this is some sort of a
funny dream I'm having here.
So long, Mister, l-I'm going home.
- Home? What home?
- Now shut up! Cut it out!
You're... You're... You're
crazy. That's what I think.
You're... You're screwy and
you're driving me crazy, too!
I'm seeing things here.
I'm going home and
see my wife and family.
You understand that?
And I'm going home alone!
How am I doing, Joseph? Thanks.
No, I didn't have a drink!
Hey, hey.
- Where did the Building and Loan move to?
- The building and what?
The Bailey Building and
Loan. It was up there.
They went out of business years ago.
That guy is a liar!
I know everything's shot in this town.
- I know...
- Hey, Violet.
Hey, listen, that's Violet Bick!
- I know. I know.
- I know that girl.
Take a walk. Beat it.
Hey, Ernie, Ernie...
Ernie, take me home.
I've gone off my nut!
- Where do you live?
- Aw, now, doggone it,
Ernie, don't you start
pulling that stuff.
You know where I live.
Three-twenty Sycamore.
- Now hurry up. - Okay.
Three-twenty Sycamore?
- Yeah, yeah, hurry up. Zuzu's sick.
- All right. All right.
Look here, Ernie,
straighten me out here.
Look, l-I've got some
bad liquor or something.
I want you to listen to me.
Now, you are Ernie Bishop,
and you live in Bailey Park with your
wife and kid? That's right, isn't it?
You seen my wife?
Seen your wife! I've been to
your house a hundred times.
Look, bud, what's the idea?
I live in a shack in Potter's Field and my wife
ran away three years ago and took the kid...
And I ain't never seen
you before in my life, see?
Okay. Just step on
it. Just get me home.
- Is this the place?
- Of course, it's the place.
Well, this house ain't been
lived in for twenty years.
What's up, Ernie?
I don't know, but we'd better
keep our eye on this guy.
He's bats.
Mary! Mary!
Tommy! Pete! Janie!
Zuzu! Where are you?
They're not here, George.
You have no children.
Where are they? What
have you done with them?
All right, put up your
hands. No fast moves.
Come on out here, both of you.
Bert! Thank heaven, you're here.
- Stand back!
- Bert, what's happened to this house?
Wh-Where's Mary? Where's my kids?
Watch him, Bert.
- Come on, come on.
- Bert, Ernie!
What's the matter with you two guys?
You-You-You were here
on my wedding night.
You, both of you, stood out there on the
porch and sung to us, don't you remember?
- Think I'd better be going.
- Look,
now why don't you be a good kid
and we'll take you into a doctor.
- Everything's gonna be all right. Now...
- Bert, now listen to me.
Ernie, will you take me
over to my mother's house?
Bert! Listen! It's that fellow there.
He says he's an angel.
He's tried to hypnotize me.
I hate to do this, fella, but...
Run, George! Run, George!
Help! Joseph, help!
- Oh, shut up!
- Help, oh, Joseph, Joseph!
Where'd he go? Where'd he
go? I had him right here.
I need a drink.
Well, which way'd they
go? Help me find 'em.
Well?
Mother.
Mother? What do you want?
Mother, this is, this is George.
I... I thought sure you'd remember me.
George who?
If you're looking for a
room, there's no vacancy.
Oh, Mother, listen. Please help me.
Something terrible's happened to me.
L-l-I don't know what it is.
Something's happened to everybody.
Please let me come in.
- Keep me here until I get over it.
- Get over what?
I don't take in strangers unless
they're sent here by somebody I know.
What? Look, I know everybody you know.
What do you... Your
brother-in-law, Uncle Billy.
- You know him?
- Well, sure I do.
- When'd you see him last?
- Today over at his house.
That's a lie.
He's been in the insane asylum
ever since he lost his business.
And if you ask me,
that's where you belong.
Strange, isn't it?
Each man's life touches
so many other lives
and when he isn't around he
leaves an awful hole, doesn't he?
I've heard of things like this.
You've got me in some kind
of a spell, or something.
Well, I'm going to get out
of it. I'll get out of it.
I know how, too. I...
The last man I talked to before all this
stuff started happening to me was Martini.
You know where he lives?
Sure I know where he lives.
He lives in Bailey Park.
Are you sure this is Bailey Park?
Oh, I'm not sure of anything anymore.
All I know is this
should be Bailey Park.
But where are the houses?
You weren't here to build them.
Your brother, Harry Bailey,
broke through the ice and was
drowned at the age of nine.
That's a lie. Harry
Bailey went to war!
He got the Congressional
Medal of Honor!
He saved the lives of
every man on that transport.
Every man on that transport died.
Harry wasn't there to save them,
because you weren't there to save Harry.
You see, George, you
really had a wonderful life.
Don't you see what a mistake
it would be to throw it away?
- Clarence...
- Yes, George?
- Where's Mary?
- Oh, well, I... I... I can't do...
I don't know how you
know these things,
- but tell me, where is she?
- I...
If you know where she is,
tell me where my wife is.
I'm not supposed to tell.
Please, Clarence,
tell me where she is.
- You're not going to like it, George.
- Where is she?
She's an old maid. She never married.
Where's Mary, where is she?
- She is...
- Where is she?
She's just about to
close up the library!
Aw, there must be some easier
way for me to get my wings.
Mary!
Mary, Mary, Mary...
Mary, it's George.
Don't you know me?
What's happened to us?
- I don't know you, let me go!
- Mary, please!
Oh, don't do this to me.
Please, Mary, help me.
Where's our kids? I need you, Mary!
Help me, Mary! Mary...
Let me go!
- Mary, don't run away!
- That man, stop him!
Tom! Ed!
Charlie! That's my wife!
- Mary!
- Oh, no, you don't!
- Somebody call the police!
- Hit him with a bottle!
He needs a straight jacket.
Mary! Clarence!
Get out of here!
- Clarence!
- Where are you?
Oh, it's you!
Stand back!
Clarence!
Clarence! Clarence!
Help me, Clarence.
Get me back.
Get me back. I don't
care what happens to me.
Get me back to my wife and kids.
Help me, Clarence, please.
Please! I want to live again.
I want to live again.
Please, God, let me live again.
Hey, George.
George!
You all right. Hey, what's the matter?
Now get out of here, Bert or
I'll hit you again! Get out!
What the Sam Hill you,
you yelling for, George!
You... George?
Bert, do you know me?
Know you? Hum, are you kidding'?
I've been looking all over
town, trying to find you.
I saw your car piled into that tree
down there, and I thought maybe you...
Hey, your mouth's bleeding.
Are you sure you're all right?
What did you...
My mouth's bleeding,
Bert! My mouth's bleed...
Zuzu's petals,
Zuzu's... There they are!
Bert! What do you know about that?
Merry Christmas!
Well, Merry Christmas!
Mary!
Yaa!
Hello, Bedford Falls!
- Merry Christmas!
Merry Christmas, George!
Merry Christmas, movie house!
Merry Christmas, Emporium!
Merry Christmas, you wonderful
old Building and Loan!
Hey! Merry Christmas, Mr. Potter!
Happy New Year to you... in jail.
Go on home. They're waiting for you.
Mary!
Well, hello, Mr. Bank
Examiner. How are you?
- Mr. Bailey, there's a deficit.
- I know. Eight thousand dollars.
George, I've got a little paper here.
I'll bet it's a warrant for
my arrest. Isn't it wonderful?
I'm going to jail.
Merry Christmas! Reporters?
Wh-Where's Mary?
Mary! Oh, look at this
wonderful old drafty house.
Mary! Mary! Mary!
Have you... Have you seen my wife?
- Merry Christmas, Daddy!
Kids! Pete!
Oh!
Kids! Janie! Janie! Tommy!
Oh, let me look at you.
Oh, I could eat you up.
- Where is your mother?
- She went looking for you with Uncle Billy.
- Daddy!
- Zuzu! Zuzu!
My little gingersnap! How do you feel?
- Fine! Not a smitch of temperature.
- Not a smitch of tempe...
Hallelujah!
- George! George!
- Mary! Mary!
George, darling! Where have you been?
- Oh, George, George, George.
- Mary! Let me touch you.
Let me touch you. Oh, you're real!
Oh, George... George.
You have no idea what happened to me.
You have no idea what happened.
Well, well, come on, George, come on
downstairs, quick. They're on their way.
- All right.
- Come on!
Come on in here now.
Now, you stand right over here, by the tree.
Right there, and don't move, don't move.
What's happening? Who's gonna come?
I hear 'em coming now,
George, it's a miracle!
- It's a miracle!
- Who's coming?
Who's gonna come, Daddy?
- Who, Daddy?
- I don't know.
Come in, Uncle Billy.
Everybody! In here!
Isn't it wonderful? So many faces!
Mary did it, George! Mary did it!
She told some people you
were in trouble and then,
they scattered all over
town collecting money.
They didn't ask any questions
- just said: "If George is in trouble, count me in...
What is this, George?
Another run on the bank?
Here you are, George, Merry Christmas.
The line forms on the right.
Merry Christmas! God bless you.
- Oh, Mr. Martini!
- Merry Christmas!
Step right up here.
I busted the jukebox, too!
Mr. Gower!
I made the rounds of
all my charge accounts.
- Violet Bick!  - I'm not going to go,
George. I changed my mind.
I've been saving this money for a
divorce, if ever I get a husband.
There you are, George. I got
the faculty all up out of bed.
And here's something
for you to play with.
I wouldn't have a roof over my
head if it wasn't for you, George.
Just a minute. Just a minute.
Quiet, everybody. Quiet, quiet.
- I just got this. It's from London.
- Oh.
Mr. Gower cabled you need cash. Stop.
My office instructed to advance you up
to twenty-five thousand dollars. Stop.
Hee-haw and Merry
Christmas. Sam Wainwright.
Mr. Martini. How about some wine?
Hark, the Herald angels sing
Glory to the new-born king.
Peace on earth, and mercy mild,
God and sinners reconciled.
Joyful all ye nations rise,
Join the triumph of the skies,
With angelic hosts proclaim
Christ is born in Bethlehem,
Harry Bailey.
George, old son of a gun.
- Harry! Harry!
- Looks like I got here too late.
Mary, I got him here from the
airport as quickly as I could.
The fool flew all the
way up here in a blizzard.
Harry, how about your
banquet in New York?
Oh, I left right in the middle of
it as soon as I got Mary's telegram.
Good idea, Ernie, a toast...
to my big brother George.
The richest man in town!
Should auld acquaintance be forgot
And never brought to mind,
Should auld acquaintance
Be forgot, and days of Auld Lang Syne.
What's that?
That's a Christmas present
from a very dear friend of mine.
Look, Daddy.
Teacher says every time a bell
rings, an angel gets his wings.
That's right. That's right.
Atta boy, Clarence.
For Auld Land Syne, my dear.
For Auld Land Syne
We'll take cup of kindness yet,
For Auld Lang Syne