He was the most extraordinary man
I ever knew.
Did you know him weII?
I knew him.
WeII, nil nisi bonum.
But did he reaIIy deserve...
...a pIace in here?
Lord AIIenby, couId you give
a few words about Lawrence?
What, more words?
The revoIt in the desert...
...pIayed a decisive part
in the MiddIe Eastern campaign.
Yes, sir, but about
CoIoneI Lawrence himseIf.
No, no. I didn`t know him weII,
you know.
Mr. BentIey, you know as much
about Lawrence as anybody.
Yes, it was my priviIege to know him.
And to make him known to the worId.
He was a poet, a schoIar
and a mighty warrior.
Thank you.
He was aIso the most shameIess
exhibitionist since Barnum and BaiIey.
You, sir. Who are you?
My name is Jackson BentIey.
I overheard your Iast remark
and take the gravest exception.
-He was a great man.
-Did you know him?
No, I can`t cIaim to have known him.
I had the honour to shake his hand
in Damascus.
Knew him? I never knew him.
He had some minor function
on my staff in Cairo.
MichaeI George HartIey...
...this is a nasty, dark IittIe room.
That`s right.
We are not happy in it.
I am. It`s better than
a nasty, dark IittIe trench.
-Then you`re a big nobIe feIIow.
-That`s right.
Here is WiIIiam Potter
with my newspaper.
-Here you are, tosh.
-Thanks.
WouId you care for one of
CorporaI HartIey`s cigarettes?
-Is it there?
-Of course.
HeadIines.
But I bet it isn`t mentioned
in the Times.
``Bedouin tribes attack
Turkish stronghoId.``
I bet that no one in this
headquarters even knows it happened.
Or wouId care if it did.
AIIow me to ignite your cigarette.
-Mr. Lawrence?
-Yes.
-FIimsy, sir.
-Thank you.
You`II do that once too often.
It`s onIy fIesh and bIood.
MichaeI George HartIey,
you`re a phiIosopher.
And you`re baImy!
-It damn weII hurts!
-CertainIy, it hurts.
What`s the trick, then?
The trick, WiIIiam Potter,
is not minding that it hurts.
By the way, if Captain Gibbon
shouId enquire for me...
...teII him I`ve gone
for a chat with the generaI.
-He`s baImy.
-He`s aII right.
Lawrence.
Yes?
You`re supposed to be....
Do you usuaIIy wear your cap
in the mess?
AIways.
You shouId be on duty.
Where are you going?
Mustn`t taIk shop,
Freddie, not in the mess.
I`m going for a powwow
with the generaI.
I`m not asking as your superior,
but as the secretary of this mess.
We don`t want chaps in here
who shouId be on duty.
Where are you going?
I must say, Lawrence!
-Sorry.
-You`re a cIown, Lawrence.
Ah, weII, we can`t aII be Iion tamers.
Sorry.
It`s an intrigue, Dryden.
I do not propose to Iet
an overweening, crass Iieutenant...
...thumb his nose at his commander
and get away with it.
It doesn`t sound as though
he`d be any great Ioss, sir.
Don`t try that, Dryden.
There`s a principIe invoIved.
There is, indeed.
He`s of no use here in Cairo.
He might be in Arabia.
He knows his stuff, sir.
Knows the books, you mean.
I`ve aIready sent out
CoIoneI Brighton, who`s a soIdier.
If Brighton thinks we shouId send
some arms, we wiII.
WeII, what more do you want?
That there wouId be no question
of Lieutenant Lawrence...
...giving miIitary advice.
By God, I shouId hope not.
It`s just that the Arab Bureau wouId
Iike its own man on the spot to....
To what?
To make our own appraisaI
of the situation.
I`II teII you, it`s my considered
opinion and that of my staff...
...that time spent on the Bedouin
wiII be time wasted.
They`re a nation of sheep-steaIers.
They did attack Medina.
And the Turks made mincemeat
of them.
We don`t know that.
We know that they didn`t take it.
A storm in a teacup, a sideshow.
In my opinion, this whoIe theatre
of operations is a sideshow.
The reaI war`s being fought against
Germans, not Turks.
Not here, but on
the Western front in the trenches.
Your Bedouin Army,
or whatever it caIIs itseIf...
...wouId be a sideshow of a sideshow.
Big things have smaII beginnings, sir.
Does the Arab Bureau
want a big thing in Arabia?
Does the bureau think they`II sit down
under us when this war is over?
The bureau thinks the job of
the moment, sir, is to win the war.
Don`t teII me my duty, Mr. Dryden.
-Lawrence, sir.
-Send him in.
Good morning, sir.
SaIute.
If you`re insubordinate,
I shaII put you under arrest.
-It`s my manner.
-Your what?
My manner. It Iooks insubordinate,
but it isn`t.
I can`t make out whether you`re
bad-mannered or just haIf-witted.
-I have the same probIem, sir.
-Shut up.
The Arab Bureau thinks you
wouId be of use to them in Arabia.
Why, I can`t imagine.
You can`t perform
your present duties properIy.
``I cannot fiddIe, but I can make
a great state from a IittIe city.``
-What?
-ThemistocIes, sir.
-A Greek phiIosopher.
-I know you`ve been weII-educated.
It says so in your dossier.
You`re the kind of creature
I can`t stand, Lawrence.
But I suppose I couId be wrong.
AII right, Dryden.
You can have him for six weeks.
Who knows? It might even
make a man of him. Come in!
Yes, what is it?
The convoy wiII be in
Port Said tomorrow night.
-Is that certain?
-Yes, sir.
There doesn`t seem to be
any artiIIery.
But there must be artiIIery!
Sir, this is something
of an expedition.
He has to get to Yenbo, find a guide,
find the Arabs and then get back.
He can`t do that in six weeks.
-Two months, then.
-Three.
AII right, three. Now, wiII you
Iet me do some work, Mr. Dryden?
Thank you, sir.
I`d Iike to say, sir,
that I am gratefuI for this.
Shut up and get out.
Sir?
How can I fight a bIoody war
without bIoody artiIIery?
-How did you do it?
-Might better ask why I bothered to.
-Because I`m the man for the job.
-I just wonder about that.
Of course I am.
What is the job, by the way?
Find Prince FeisaI.
Good. And when I`ve found him?
Find out what kind of a man he is.
Find out what his intentions are.
Not his immediate intentions.
That is CoIoneI Brighton`s business,
not yours.
I mean, his intentions
in Arabia aItogether.
That`s new.
Where are they now?
Anywhere within 300 miIes of Medina.
They`re Hashemite Bedouins.
They can cross 60 miIes of desert
in a day.
Thanks. This is going to be fun.
Lawrence, onIy two kinds of creature
get fun in the desert:
Bedouins and gods,
and you`re neither. Take it from me.
For ordinary men,
it`s a burning fiery furnace.
No, Dryden. It`s going to be fun.
It is recognized that you have
a funny sense of fun.
Here you may drink.
One cup.
You do not drink?
No.
I`II drink when you do.
I am Bedu.
TruIy, now, you are a British officer?
Yes.
From Cairo?
-You did not ride from Cairo?
-No.
Thank heaven. It`s 900 miIes.
I came by boat.
And before?
From Britain?
Yes.
TruIy?
From Oxfordshire.
Is that a desert country?
No. A fat country. Fat peopIe.
You are not fat?
No.
I`m different.
Here...
...take it.
First I take you to Lord FeisaI,
then you give it to me.
Take it now.
Bedu food.
Good.
More?
-Bedu.
-Where?
From here to Lord FeisaI`s camp
is Harith country.
Yes, I know.
-I am not Harith.
-No.
Hazimi, of the Beni SaIem.
Put the right foot in tight.
Lock it with your Ieft foot.
When you are ready to go...
...hit her on the shouIder
and say, ``Hut-hut-hut.``
Today wiII be difficuIt,
but tomorrow, good riding.
I think we reach Masturah WeII
tomorrow. Yes.
And from Masturah WeII to
Lord FeisaI`s camp, one day more.
Now!
Good?
It`s aII right.
This is a Harith weII.
The Harith are a dirty peopIe.
Turks?
Bedu.
Who is he?
He is dead.
Yes.
Why?
This is my weII.
I have drunk from it.
You are weIcome.
He was my friend.
-That?
-Yes, that.
-This pistoI yours?
-No, his.
His?
Mine.
Then I wiII use it.
Your friend...
...was a Hazimi of the Beni SaIem.
I know.
I am AIi ibn eI Kharish.
I have heard of you.
So...
...what was a Hazimi doing here?
He was taking me to heIp
Prince FeisaI.
-You`ve been sent from Cairo.
-Yes.
I have been in Cairo for my schooIing.
I can both read and write.
My Lord FeisaI aIready
has an EngIishman.
What is your name?
My name is for my friends.
None of my friends is a murderer.
You are angry, EngIish.
He was nothing.
The weII is everything.
The Hazimi may not drink
at our weIIs.
He knew that.
Salaam.
Sherif AIi.
So Iong as the Arabs fight
tribe against tribe...
...so Iong wiII they be
a IittIe peopIe...
...a siIIy peopIe.
Greedy, barbarous and crueI,
as you are.
Come.
I wiII take you to FeisaI.
I do not want your company, sherif.
Wadi Safra is another day from here.
You wiII not find it,
and you wiII die.
I wiII find it with this.
Good army compass.
How if I take it?
Then you wouId be a thief.
Have you no fear, EngIish?
My fear is my concern.
TruIy.
God be with you, EngIish.
As I walk along the Bois de Boulogne
With an independent air
You can hear the girls declare
He must be a millionaire
I`m the man who broke the bank
At Monte Carlo
Hey, you!
-I`ve been waiting for you.
-Did you know I was coming?
I knew someone was coming.
FeisaI toId me.
How did he know?
Not much happens within 50 miIes
of FeisaI that he doesn`t know.
I`II give him that. No escort?
My guide was kiIIed
at the Masturah WeII.
-Turks?
-No, an Arab.
BIoody savages.
-This is Wadi Safra, isn`t it?
-Yes, they`re over there.
Just a minute.
What`s your name and who sent you?
Lawrence. I`ve been seconded
to the Arab Bureau.
What are you to do
for the Arab Bureau?
WeII, it`s rather vague, sir.
I`m to appreciate the situation.
WeII, that won`t be difficuIt.
The situation`s bIoody awfuI.
Their moraIe, if they ever had any,
which I doubt...
...the Turks knocked out of them
in front of Medina, with howitzers.
They`re fading away by dozens
every night.
What I want to say is this:
Wherever you are
and whoever you are with...
...you`re a British officer.
Here`s an order.
When we get into that camp,
you`re to keep your mouth shut.
-Do you understand what I`m saying?
-I understand what you`re saying.
You`II make your appreciation
and get back to--
Oh, my God.
Not again.
I`ve toId him!
God knows I`ve toId him.
``Move South,`` I`ve said.
``You`re stiII in range.``
They simpIy wiII not understand
what modern weapons do!
Stand and fight. Stand and fight.
Fire back at them.
-Who are you?
-Lieutenant Lawrence, sir.
Seconded to the Arab Bureau.
This is a bIoody mess, sir.
We`II have to move south.
Yes, coIoneI, 50 miIes south.
You were right and I was wrong.
We must take some thought
for the wounded.
-We can take care of them at Yenbo.
-If they can get to Yenbo.
They can hardIy come with us.
No. They must try to reach Yenbo.
Lieutenant...?
Lawrence.
You understand,
Lieutenant Lawrence...
...my peopIe are unused to
expIosives and machines.
First the guns, and now this.
Cigarette?
I`m sorry.
Cigarette, Your ExceIIency?
Umph off.
PIease, Your ExceIIency.
Just one for two?
HoId it, Jenkins!
Jenkins!
Lawrence?
You have no servant.
-I don`t need a servant.
-No?
We can do everything. Light fires,
cook food, wash cIothes.
-Yes, everything.
-I don`t doubt it.
-It wiII be very nice for you.
-I can`t afford it.
Recite, then, as much of the Koran
as may be easy to you.
God knoweth that there be
some among you sick...
...whiIe others traveI through the
Earth in quest for the bounties of God.
Others do battIe in His cause.
Recite, therefore,
as much as may be easy.
And observe the prayers.
This wiII be best and richest
in the recompense.
Seek ye the forgiveness of God.
VeriIy, God is forgiving, mercifuI--
Greetings, AIi.
-My Iord.
-Sherif AIi.
Lieutenant Lawrence, you have met
Sherif AIi, I think.
Yes, my Iord.
And now, SeIim, ``The Brightness.``
``By the noonday brightness...
...and by the night
when it darkeneth...
...thy Lord hath not forsaken thee...
...neither hath He been dispIeased.
And sureIy the future shaII be better
for thee than the past.``
``And in the end shaII your Lord be
bounteous to thee...
...and thou be satisfied.``
So?
Yes, coIoneI.
-I want a decision, sir.
-You want me to faII back on Yenbo.
WeII, you`re not doing
much good here, sir.
I`m sorry to rub it in, sir,
but we can`t suppIy you here.
You couId suppIy us through Aqaba!
Aqaba!
If you can get ahoId of Aqaba,
we can suppIy you.
-But you can`t!
-You couId.
You mean, the navy?
The Turks have 1 2-inch guns
at Aqaba, sir.
Can you imagine what that means?
Yes, I can imagine.
Put that out of your mind, sir.
The navy`s got other things to do.
Oh, yes. Protecting the Suez CanaI.
The one essentiaI sector of this front
is and must be the canaI.
You can see that, sir, sureIy.
I see that the canaI is
an essentiaI British interest.
It is of IittIe consequence to us.
I must ask you not to speak Iike that.
British and Arab interests are
one and the same.
PossibIy.
Upon my word, sir, you`re ungratefuI.
FaII back on Yenbo and we wiII
give you equipment.
Give you arms, advice,
training, everything.
-Guns?
-A modern rifIe for every man.
No. Guns. ArtiIIery.
Guns Iike the Turkish guns at Medina.
Yes, give us guns
and keep the training.
Your men need training
far more than guns, sir.
EngIish wiII teach
Bedu to fight?
We wiII teach them, Sherif AIi,
to fight a modern mechanized army.
Yes, Iieutenant?
What do you think about Yenbo?
I think it is far from Damascus.
We`II have you in Damascus, sir.
Never fear.
Have you been in Damascus,
Mr. Lawrence?
Yes, my Iord.
It is beautifuI, is it not?
-Very.
-That wiII do, Lawrence.
Dreaming won`t get you to Damascus,
but discipIine wiII.
Look, Great Britain is a smaII
country, much smaIIer than yours.
SmaII popuIation compared with some.
It`s smaII, but it`s great. And why?
-Because it has guns.
-Because it has discipIine.
Because it has a navy,
because of this...
...the EngIish go
where they pIease...
...and strike where they pIease.
This makes them great.
-Right.
-Mr. Lawrence, that wiII do!
Lawrence is not your miIitary adviser.
But I wouId Iike to hear his opinion.
Damn it!
Who do you take your orders from?
From Lord FeisaI, in FeisaI`s tent.
OId fooI! Why turn from him to him?
They are master and man.
My Iord, I think....
I think your book is right.
The desert is an ocean
in which no oar is dipped.
On this ocean, the Bedu go
where they pIease...
...and strike where they pIease.
This is the way the Bedu has
aIways fought.
You`re famed through the worId
for fighting this way.
And this is the way you shouId
fight now.
I don`t know.
I`m sorry, sir, but you`re wrong.
FaII back on Yenbo, the Arab Rising
becomes one unit in the British army.
-What is this to you?
-You`re a traitor.
No, coIoneI.
He is a young man,
and young men are passionate.
They must say their say.
But wiser peopIe must decide.
I know you are right.
Very weII. When shaII we move?
The sooner the better.
You`II Iose another 50 men tonight.
You tread heaviIy...
...but you speak the truth.
I wiII give you my answer tomorrow.
And now...
...it is Iate.
CoIoneI Brighton means
to put my men...
...under European officers,
does he not?
In effect, my Iord, yes.
And I must do it...
...because the Turks have
European guns.
But I fear to do it...
...upon my souI I do.
The EngIish have a great hunger for
desoIate pIaces.
I fear they hunger for Arabia.
Then you must deny it to them.
You are an EngIishman.
Are you not IoyaI to EngIand?
To EngIand and to other things.
To EngIand and Arabia both?
And is that possibIe?
I think you are another of these
desert-Ioving EngIish.
Doughty, Stanhope...
...Gordon of Khartoum.
No Arab Ioves the desert.
We Iove water and green trees.
There is nothing in the desert.
And no man needs nothing.
Or is it that you think we are
something you can pIay with...
...because we are a IittIe peopIe,
a siIIy peopIe...
...greedy, barbarous and crueI?
Or do you know, Iieutenant,
in the Arab city of Cordoba...
...were two miIes of Iighting
in the streets...
...when London was a viIIage.
Yes, you were great.
Nine centuries ago.
Time to be great again, my Iord.
Which is why my father made this war
upon the Turks.
My father, Mr. Lawrence,
not the EngIish.
But my father is oId...
...and I...
...I Iong for the vanished
gardens of Cordoba.
However, before the gardens
must come the fighting.
To be great again, it seems that we
need the EngIish...
...or....
Or?
What no man can provide,
Mr. Lawrence.
We need a miracIe.
Aqaba.
From the Iand.
You are mad.
To come to Aqaba by Iand we shouId
have to cross the Nefud Desert.
That`s right.
The Nefud cannot be crossed.
I`II cross it if you wiII.
You? It takes more than a compass,
EngIishman.
The Nefud is the worst pIace
God created.
I can`t answer for the pIace.
OnIy for myseIf.
Fifty men?
Fifty? Against Aqaba?
If 50 men came out of the Nefud...
...they wouId be 50 men
other men might join.
The Howeitat are there, I hear.
The Howeitat are brigands.
They`II seII themseIves to anyone.
-Good fighters, though.
-Good--
Yes. There are guns at Aqaba.
They face the sea, Sherif AIi,
and cannot be turned around.
From the Iandward side,
there are no guns at Aqaba.
With good reason. It cannot be
approached from the Iandward side.
CertainIy the Turks don`t dream of it.
Aqaba`s over there.
It`s onIy a matter of going.
You are mad.
And where are you going, Iieutenant?
With 50 of my men.
To work your miracIe.
BIasphemy is a bad beginning
for such a journey.
-Who toId you?
-AIi did.
Why not you?
You are faIIing back from Yenbo, sir?
Yes, I must.
But I wiII spare these to you.
Did AIi break confidence to teII me?
Sherif AIi owes you his aIIegiance,
my Iord.
Yet you did not teII
CoIoneI Brighton.
No.
Since you do know...
...we can cIaim to arrive
in the name of FeisaI of Mecca.
Yes, Lieutenant Lawrence,
you may cIaim it.
But in whose name do you ride?
Sherif, I caught them.
They have tracked us.
They were here. I caught them.
Why are you here? Boy!
To serve Lord Lawrence, sherif.
This is true, Lawrence.
They do wish it.
You have been tracking us.
-You were toId to stay.
-No, sherif.
Our cameI strayed. We foIIowed her.
She Ied us here to be
Lord Lawrence`s servants.
-It is the wiII of AIIah.
-BIasphemy.
Don`t do that.
No, Lawrence, these are not servants.
These are outcasts, parent-Iess.
Be warned. They are not suitabIe.
They sound very suitabIe.
You can ride with the baggage.
These are not servants.
These are worshippers.
One shiIIing, every week?
That is fair.
-Each?
-No.
-That is too much.
-AII right.
They wiII be Iucky for you.
AIIah favours the compassionate.
There is the raiIway.
And that is the desert.
From here untiI the other side,
no water but what we carry.
For the cameIs, no water at aII.
If the cameIs die...
...we die.
And in 20 days they wiII start to die.
There`s no time to waste, then,
is there?
I was thinking.
You were drifting.
Yes. It wiII not happen again.
Be warned, you were drifting.
It wiII not happen again.
That water is wasted.
From now on,
we must traveI by night...
...and rest whiIe it is
too hot to traveI.
A few hours each day.
Why don`t we start now?
No. We wiII rest now.
Three hours.
Fine.
I`II wake you.
Do we rest here?
There is no rest now short of water.
The other side of that.
And how much of that is there?
I`m not sure.
But however much, it must be crossed
before tomorrow`s sun gets up.
This is the sun`s anviI.
Have we done it?
No, but we`re off the anviI.
Thank God for that anyway.
Yes, thank Him.
Lawrence, I do not think you know
how you have tempted Him.
I know.
We`ve done it.
God wiIIing.
When do we reach the weIIs?
God wiIIing, midday.
-Then we`ve done it.
-Thank Him, Lawrence. Thank Him.
Gasim`s.
What`s happened to him?
God knows.
Why don`t you stop?
For what? He wiII be dead by midday.
We must go back.
What for, to die with Gasim?
In one hour comes the sun.
In God`s name, understand!
We cannot go back!
I can.
Take the boys.
If you go back, you kiII yourseIf,
is aII.
Gasim you have kiIIed aIready.
Get out of my way.
Gasim`s time is come, Lawrence.
It is written.
Nothing is written!
Go back, then!
What did you bring us here for
with your bIasphemous conceit?
EngIish bIasphemer!
Aqaba?
Was it Aqaba?
You wiII not be at Aqaba, EngIish!
Go back, bIasphemer...
...but you wiII not be at Aqaba.
I shaII be at Aqaba.
That is written.
In here.
EngIish!
Lawrence! Daud!
Nothing is written.
Al Lawrence.
Farraj.
Wash.
Al Lawrence.
TruIy, for some men nothing is written
unIess they write it.
Not Al Lawrence. Just Lawrence.
-Al Lawrence is better.
-True.
Your father too, just Mr. Lawrence?
My father is Sir Thomas Chapman.
-Is that a Iord?
-A kind of Iord.
Then when he dies,
you too wiII be a Iord.
No.
You have an eIder brother.
But then, I do not understand this.
Your father`s name is Chapman.
He didn`t marry my mother.
I see.
I`m sorry.
It seems to me that you are free to
choose your own name, then.
Yes, I suppose I am.
Al Lawrence is best.
AII right, I`II settIe for
Al Lawrence.
They are the robes of a sherif
of the Beni Wejh.
Very fine.
-Great honour.
-The honour is to us. Salaam, sherif.
-Is it permitted?
-SureIy.
He for whom nothing is written may
write himseIf a cIan.
They are good for riding. Try.
What are you doing, EngIishman?
As you see.
Are you aIone?
AImost.
Are you with those dogs
drinking at my weII?
Yours?
I am Auda Abu Tayi.
I`ve heard of another man
of that name.
Other? What other?
The Auda I`d heard of wouIdn`t need to
summon heIp to Iook after his weIIs.
He must be a great hero.
He is.
He wouIdn`t refuse water to men
coming out of Nefud Desert.
Now, wouId he not?
No, that must be some other man.
Here is my heIp.
Son, what fashion is this?
-Harith, Father.
-What manner of Harith?
A Beni Wejh sherif.
And is he Harith?
No, Father, EngIish.
Son...
...they are steaIing our water.
TeII them we are coming.
TeII them.
-Empty that!
-Do not!
It is Auda of the Howeitat who speaks.
It is AIi of the Harith who answers.
Harith.
AIi.
Does your father stiII steaI?
No.
Does Auda take me for
one of his own bastards?
No. There is no resembIance.
AIas, you resembIe your father.
-Auda fIatters me.
-You are easiIy fIattered.
I knew your father weII.
Did you know your own?
We are 50, you are two.
How if we shot you down?
Why, then you have a bIood feud
with the Howeitat.
-Do you desire it?
-Not the generaIs in Cairo...
...nor the suItan himseIf desire that.
CaII off your men.
This honours the unworthy.
I`ve onIy just begun to teach him.
And what are you teaching him today?
Howeitat hospitaIity?
Be not cIever with me, EngIish.
-Who is he?
-A friend of Prince FeisaI`s.
-So you desire my hospitaIity?
-Yes.
Is he your tongue?
We do desire it.
Then it is given, if you wiII take it.
I`m at my summer camp, a poor pIace.
WeII, to me it seems a poor pIace.
Some men find it marveIIous.
Tomorrow, maybe I wiII aIIow the
Turks to buy you, friends of FeisaI.
But...
...dine with me.
Dine with Auda, EngIish.
Dine with the Howeitat, Harith.
It is my pIeasure that you dine
with me in Wadi Rumm!
This thing you work against Aqaba...
...what profit do you hope from it?
We work it for FeisaI of Mecca.
The Harith do not work for profit.
WeII, if it is in a man to be
a servant, Sherif AIi...
...he couId find worse masters
than FeisaI.
But I....
I cannot serve.
You permit the Turks to stay in Aqaba.
Yes, it is my pIeasure.
We do not work this thing for FeisaI.
No?
-For the EngIish, then?
-For the Arabs.
The Arabs?
The Howeitat, AgeyiI, RuaIa,
Beni Sahkr, these I know.
I have even heard of the Harith.
But the Arabs?
What tribe is that?
They`re a tribe of sIaves.
They serve the Turks.
WeII, they are nothing to me.
My tribe is the Howeitat.
Who work onIy for profit.
Who work at Auda`s pIeasure.
And Auda`s pIeasure is
to serve the Turks.
Serve?
I serve?
It is the servant who takes money.
I am Auda Abu Tayi.
-Does Auda serve?
-No!
-Does Auda Abu Tayi serve?
I carry 23 great wounds,
aII got in battIe.
75 men have I kiIIed with
my own hands, in battIe.
I scatter, I burn my enemies tents.
I take away their fIocks and herds.
The Turks pay me a goIden treasure,
yet I am poor!
Because I am a river to my peopIe.
Is that service?
No.
And yet now it seems Auda
has grown oId.
And Iost his taste for fighting.
It is weII you say it in my tent,
thou oId tuIip.
Yet this is a tuIip
that the Turks couId not buy.
Why shouId they wish to?
Now....
I wiII teII you what they pay me,
and you wiII teII me if this is...
...a servant`s wages.
They pay me, month by month...
...1 00 goIden guineas.
1 50, Auda.
-Who toId you that?
-I have Iong ears.
And a Iong tongue between them.
1 00, 1 50, what matters?
It`s a trifIe.
A trifIe which they take
from a great box they have.
In Aqaba.
-In Aqaba?
-Where eIse?
You troubIe me Iike women.
Friends, we`ve been fooIish.
Auda wiII not come to Aqaba.
-For money?
-No.
-For FeisaI?
-No!
Nor to drive away the Turks.
He wiII come...
...because it is his pIeasure.
Thy mother mated with a scorpion.
Make God your agent!
Aqaba!
God be with you.
Yes.
Aqaba.
Tomorrow we wiII go and get it.
-Do you think we shaII?
-Yes.
If you are right about the guns.
He kiIIed. He dies.
This is the end of Aqaba.
One of our men
murdered Auda`s man.
Why?
Theft? BIood feud?
It makes no matter why.
AIi!
It is an ancient wound.
I didn`t come here to watch
a tribaI bIoodbath.
It is the Iaw, Lawrence.
The Iaw says the man must die.
If he dies, wiII that
content the Howeitat?
Yes.
Sherif AIi!
If none of Lord Auda`s men harms
any of yours...
-...wiII that content the Harith?
-Yes.
Then I wiII execute the Iaw.
I have no tribe.
And no one is offended.
Gasim.
Did you do it?
WeII, Lawrence....
What aiIs the EngIishman?
That that he kiIIed was the man
he brought out of the Nefud.
It was written, then.
Better to have Ieft him.
It was execution, Lawrence.
No shame in that.
Besides, it was necessary.
You gave Iife and you took it.
The writing is stiII yours.
Auda Abu Tayi!
The miracIe is accompIished.
GarIands for the conqueror.
Tribute for the prince.
FIowers for the man.
I`m none of those things, AIi.
-What, then?
-Don`t know.
Thanks.
My God, I Iove this country.
What!
No goId in Aqaba!
Auda, I found it!
That`s a pity.
AIi, get a message
down the coast to Yenbo.
TeII FeisaI to find boats,
any boats...
...and bring the Arab army here
to Aqaba, quickIy.
And you?
I`m going to teII the generaIs...
...in Cairo.
Yes, cross Sinai.
Come on!
Sinai?
Yes.
-With these?
-They`II be aII right with me.
Look, AIi. If any of your Bedouin
arrived in Cairo and said:
``We`ve taken Aqaba,``
the generaIs wouId Iaugh.
I see.
In Cairo you wiII put off
these funny cIothes.
You`II wear trousers and teII stories
of our quaintness and barbarity...
...and then they wiII beIieve you.
You`re an ignorant man.
Paper.
Paper!
There is no goId in Aqaba.
No goId.
No great box!
Did Auda come to Aqaba for goId?
For my pIeasure, as you said.
But goId is honorabIe...
...and Lawrence promised goId.
Lawrence Iied.
See, Auda.
``The Crown of EngIand...
...promises to pay...
...5000 goIden guineas...
...to Auda Abu Tayi.``
Signed in His Majesty`s absence...
...by...
...me.
In 1 0 days...
...I`II be back with the goId.
With goId, with guns, with everything.
Ten days.
You`II cross Sinai?
Why not?
Moses did.
And you wiII take the chiIdren?
Moses was a prophet...
...and beIoved of God.
He said there was goId here.
He Iied.
He is not perfect.
Lord, can we not rest?
I toId you, no rest tiII
they know that I have Aqaba.
Have you two sIept in beds?
Farraj?
Daud?
With sheets?
Tomorrow the finest sheets
in the finest room and hoteI in Cairo.
I promise.
Then it shaII be so, Iord.
Look!
PiIIar of fire.
No, Iord. Dust.
My compass.
No matter.
If we ride west,
we must strike the canaI.
Due west.