-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-
I only ever met one man
I wouldn't want to fight.
- I can't stop that.
- Get out of here, you useless tit!
When I met him, he was already
the best cut man in the business.
Started training and managing in the
'60s, but he never lost his gift.
- Let me have a look at him.
- He's fine.
He ain't if you don't stop this
bleeding. l'II give you one round.
- Seconds up. Let's go.
- What do we do?
You let him hit you.
Sometimes there's
just nothing you can do.
Cut's too wide,
too close to the bone,
maybe you got a severed vein
or you just can'tget
the coagulant deep enough.
There are all kinds of combinations
you come up against down
in the different layers of meat.
And Frankie
knew howto work every one.
People love violence.
They'll slow down at a car wreck
to check for bodies.
Same people claim to love boxing,
they got no idea what it is.
Boxing is about respect.
Getting it for yourself
and taking it away
from the other guy.
- l'll warm up the car.
- Mr. Dunn?
- I owe you money?
- No, sir.
- I know your mama?
- I don't rightly know, sir.
- Then what is it you want?
- I was on the undercard.
- I won my fight. Maggie Fitzgerald.
- What's up?
- Did you happen to see it?
- Nope.
I did pretty good. Thought you
might be interested in training me.
- I don'ttrain girls.
- Maybe you should.
People see me fight
say I'm prettytough.
Girlie, tough ain't enough!
It's a mistake.
Car should be able to back up,
Frankie.
Just push, will you?
- What did Hogan want?
- Offered us a title shot.
- About time.
- I turned him down flat.
Two or three more fights
and you'll be ready.
Been two or three more fights
for a long time now, Frankie.
You get one shot at the title,
you lose it, it may not come again.
Now, two orthree more fights
and we'll be ready.
Whatever you say.
Frankie liked to say
that boxing is an unnatural act,
that everything
in boxing is backwards.
Sometimes, best way
to deliver a punch is step back.
Do Your best, Lord, protect Kathy.
Annie too.
Other than that
you know what I want,
there's no use me repeating myself.
But step back too far,
you ain't fighting at all.
- Father, that was a great sermon!
- What's confusing you this week?
The same old one.
God, three God thing.
Most people figure out by
kindergarten it's about faith.
Is it like Snap, Crackle and Pop
all rolled up in one big box?
You're standing outside my church
comparing God to Rice Krispies?
You come to mess only to wind me up.
It won't happen this morning.
- I'm confused.
- No.
- Yes, I'm.
- There's one God.
- Anything else? Because I'm busy.
- What about the Holy Ghost?
- He's an expression of God's love.
- And Jesus?
- Son of God. Don't play stupid!
- Does that make him a demigod?
There are no demigods,
you fucking pagan!
- Did you write your daughter?
- Absolutely.
You're lying to a priest. Take a day
off, don't come to mass tomorrow.
They'd say the most important thing
a fighter can have is heart.
Frankie'd say: "Show me a fighter
who's nothing but heart
and l'll show you
a man waiting for a beating!"
I think I only ever met one fighter
who was all heart.
My name's Dangerous Dillard
Fightin' Flippo Bam-Bam Barch
out of Broward County, Texas.
Danger showed up
couple of years back.
He'd come visiting L.A. with Ervel,
his mama's new boyfriend.
Apparently Ervel got lost
and ended up back in Texas.
Danger looked for him for about
a week before he introduced himself.
You know,
I've got nothing against niggers.
- That's nice to hear.
- Lotsa people where I come from does
but my mama taught me not to cause
hurt to no man, niggers or not.
You got a nice mama.
Anything else I can do for you?
Just one of those questions you ask,
but Danger wanted to answer.
I'd like to become the
Welterweight Champion ofthe world.
And I challenge the Motor City Cobra,
Thomas "Hit Man" Hearns
to fight me for the Welterweight
Championship of the whole world!
You ain't even ranked! You gotta have
at least one fight to be ranked!
- l'll fight any man, anytime!
- You a bad man, huh?
- Go a round with me.
- Shawrelle.
Leave him alone.
Danger, go on back to training.
Will do, Mister Scrap.
Them some nice tights, Danger.
- I'II give you that ass-whuppin'.
- Those pants look pretty on you.
Shawrelle Berry had a left hook
that would move a tank,
but he had a heart
the size of a split pea.
Frankie bought the Hit Pit
from BobbyMalone 17 years ago.
Bobby wanted to move to Florida
and Frankie wanted some security.
Bobby died while he was packing.
Frankie found out
most gyms lose money.
I told you I didn't want
Danger working out here anymore.
- He ain't hurting nothing.
- He's hurting me.
Breaking my heart watching him punch
the air like it's gonna punch back.
How many times have I got
to tell you that bleach is bleach?
You don't have to buy
the expensive stuff.
- It smells better.
- Bleach smells like bleach!
Nice fight. People are talking.
- What kind of language is that?
- What do you want?
You got a fighter
not talking to another manager.
- Not talking to another manager?
- And not just any manager...
...Mickey Mack.
- You came in here to tell me
that Big Willie
is not talking to Mickey Mack.
- Not a word. Neither one of them.
- I'm trying to read here.
If you think that's more important.
- Who's your new girl?
- What?
If she keeps hitting it like that
she gonna break her wrists.
You're wasting your time,
I told you I don't train girls.
- Thought you might change your mind.
- Dozens oftrainers train girls.
- You won't have trouble finding one.
- You'll do fine, boss.
I'm not your boss
and don'tyou be calling me that.
- You ready to work?
- Anytime.
If I stop calling you boss,
will you train me?
Then I might as well
keep calling you it.
She came from Southwestern Missouri,
the hills outside the scratch-ass
Ozark town of Theodosia,
set in the trees somewhere
between nowhere and goodbye.
She grew up knowing one thing:
she was trash.
It's for my dog.
She'd come 1800 miles, but Theodosia
was stil ljust over the hill.
- Working the bag, boss.
- Not your boss.
And that bag's working you!
- Give her her money back.
- You sure?
- How much did she pay?
- Six months.
- No, I'll give it back.
- Don't be a smart ass!
Woman thinks I'll throw away
six months' worth of dues
just to get rid of her, she's out of
her mind. But don't encourage her.
And what's Danger doing out there?
What's he looking at?
- Looks like a bottle of water.
- He paid his dues?
Boy can't afford pants,
want him to pay dues?
Get out of my office!
Can't think of it as a bag.
I'm not a trainer, but I can
show you this, if you'd like.
Appreciate any help I can get.
You want to think of it as a man.
He's constantly moving.
He's moving towards you, around you,
away from you. All right?
Don't hit him when he's coming
towards you or he'll push you back,
he'll smotheryour punches,
take your balance, right?
Watch him carefully, keep rotating
and keep your head moving
and keep one shoulder back so
you're ready to fire a powershot.
Go ahead, good. Keep rotating,
keep moving. That's it.
Keep that chin tucked in.
- Like that?
- Keep moving. Give it a few shots.
Tuck that chin in.
You get this down, we'll put you
on the speed bag.
You do have a speed bag.
l'll borrow it,
till I can buy my own.
- All right. You go home now.
- l'll walk out with you?
I am home. Want to see?
Would it bother you much
if I worked a little longer?
Just pull the door closed
when you leave.
lf there's magic in boxing
it's the magic of fighting battles
beyond endurance,
beyond cracked ribs, ruptured
kidneys and detached retinas.
It's the magic of risking everything
fora dream that nobody sees butyou.
I think I found somebody
you can beat.
- I don't fight women.
- It's perfect. You know why?
You could fight to him
and then you could kiss to him.
- Then fight one more time.
- That's like poetry!
- It's like poetry.
- You been reading and shit.
That's a girl, man?
Look at her little titties.
They're like mosquito bites!
- That's barely even a mouthful.
- Saw your last fight, Shawrelle.
Spent so much time face down,
I thought the canvas had titties!
Canvas has titties!
Look at me! I'm Shawrelle!
Just humping the canvas,
humping the floor.
Come on, bro. The floor
having titties, that's funny!
Shut up! Whatyou laughing at?
Hold the bag!
When they start making
those tights for men, Flippy?
That's enough for today.
- l'll give you a rubdown.
- I can't.
My middle one's got a piano lesson.
I told Grace I'd drive her.
- Something wrong with Grace's car?
- She hates that car.
Wants the old one back,
but the dealer already got a buyer.
- I should talk to the dealer.
- I'd appreciate that.
The man's a rubdown whore
and today he doesn't want one?
You ever do anywork around here?
Not my job I'd worry about,
if I was you.
Little girl seems to be coming along.
It's almost like
somebody's been helping her.
She might just be a natural.
Looks like she's got something.
She's got my speed bag,
that's what she's got!
I wonder how she got that!
- I need that speed bag back.
- That bag?
- This bag?
- People will think I'm training you.
- Is that such a bad thing, boss?
- Yes, it is.
Every time you touch it,
you're losing my business out here.
I gotta agree,
I am embarrassing myself.
I can't just lend it to anybody.
You seem like a nice girl.
Can I give you some advice?
- I'd appreciate that.
- You'll find a trainer
that will want to train a girl.
It's the latest freak show out there!
But they'll be wasting your time
because you're too old.
I don't feel that old.
Neither do I, but you don't see me
fighting 21-year-olds, do you?
Takes about four years
to train a fighter.
- How old are you?
- 31 until my next birthday.
You wouldn't start training to be
a ballerina at 31, would you?
- Already been working for 3 years.
- And you can't hit a speed bag?
- What kind of training is that?
- I've never had any, boss.
I hate to say it, but it shows.
Somebody's got to be honest with you.
I hate to be the one
to tell you the truth.
Sorry for using your bag, Mr. Dunn.
- You're not gonna cry now, are you?
- No, sir.
- Keep the goddamn thing.
- No, you need it.
No, take the bag. I haven't seen it
in 20 years anyway.
I've had three since then.
Just enjoy it, will you?
- I'll borrow it till I buy my own.
- Don't lose it.
I know, Hogan. Your guy's the champ,
so we don't split fifties.
But if I don't see forty percent...
Call me back when it's 60-40
or don't call me back at all.
- Is something wrong?
- Sorry to come like this.
- You don't like people dropping in.
- You're not people, Willie.
- You're welcome anytime. Come on in.
- Thank you for getting the car back.
Paying an extra 1000 dollars
for your own car is not a favor.
- Grace cried when she saw it.
- Really?
I also needed to talk with you
about business.
I justtalked with Hogan,
we're all set for September.
- Everything but the split.
- I gotta leave you, Frankie.
- The title is just two fights away.
- It ain't that.
It's like you said, I got one shot.
lf I win, I gotta make
as much as I can, while I can.
I need somebody in the action
who can make things happen.
And I gotta make the change
before the fight.
Only way this guy say he'd take me
is if he took me to the title.
So I get you the title fight
and this guy takes you there?
Only way he'd do it.
I'm sorry, Frankie.
I know how long
you've been waiting on a title.
Mickey Mack's a business man.
He can't teach you nothing.
You already taught me
everything I need to know.
There's some things that people
just don't want to hear.
And I challenge the Motor City Cobra,
Thomas "Hit Man" Hearns
to fight me for the Welterweight
Championship of the whole world!
I'm wearing these mitts for a reason.
Just working on my footwork,
Mist' Scrap.
Danger, you throw a punch
or get the hell out ofthis gym.
While you thinking about that punch,
I'll be right back.
I'm thinking how I'm gonna
hit it hard for you, Mist' Scrap!
No one had the heart to tell Danger
that Hearns had retired years ago.
I heard about Willie.
That's cold, man, that's dead cold.
It wouldn't be so bad
if you weren't so damn old.
At least I can see through both eyes.
Didn't do you a lot of good though,
did it?
I've got the gym. Don't need
to be training fighters at my age.
- Willie tell you why?
- Mickey's got the connections.
It ain't about connections.
It's about you not believing in him.
I stuck with him for eight years.
How's that for not believing in him?
You could've got him a title fight
two years ago, he knew that.
I'm amazed he stayed around
this long.
Getting there and taking home
the belt are two different things.
What was I supposed to do? Put him
in over his head, not protect him?
You were protecting him
from the championship!
- Now it makes sense.
- Whatabout you, Scrap?
What did your manager do? You were
a good fighter, better than Willie.
He get you a title fight or did
he bust you out banging your head
against other people's fists,
until you lost your eye?
I had my shot. I went out swinging
and no man can say I didn't.
I remember. Excuse me
if I didn't want my fighter
spending the second half ofhis life
cleaning up other people's spit.
Right, you're the smart one.
You're the one learning Greek.
- It's Gaelic.
- You protected yourself
out of a championship fight.
How do you say that in Gaelic?
Boxing is an unnatural act.
'Cause everything in it
is backwards.
You want to move to the left,
you don't step left,
you push on the right toe.
To move right,
you use your left toe.
Instead of running from the pain,
like a sane person would do,
you step into it.
So Big Willie comes back.
Oh, my God!
He hits the champ with a right hand
and the champ is down.
The Refis into the count
and Big Willie Jones
is the new champion ofthe world!
It's unbelievable!
There you have it, folks,
a new champion!
Everything in boxing is backwards.
- Wanta cheeseburger?
- You bought me a cheeseburger?
I never seen you buy anybody
a cheeseburger.
I couldn't eat it and I ordered it.
You want it?
I guess the planet
can go back to spinning!
- You watch the fight?
- Yeah, I watched it.
Willie did good.
- That's what you got to say?
- He won, didn't he? He did good.
I see you been working on yourself,
learning to open up. Good work.
- You watch it?
- Yeah, I got HBO.
How can you afford HBO?
How long have I been telling you
to save your money?
Since I fought Louis "Typhoon"
Johnson in Tupelo, Mississippi.
- That true?
- Manager ran off
and left you and me to hitch home,
don't you remember nothing?
I remember walking halfway,
thinking I was gonna be lynched.
I remember you leaving me pissing
behind that gas station.
I gota ride. The guy took off
before I hardly closed the door.
I had to walk back two miles.
Your conscience got
the better of you, that's what.
- What's that?
- It's her birthday.
You're not breathing right,
that's why you're panting.
So, it's your birthday, huh?
- How old does that make you?
- I'm 32, Mr. Dunn.
I'm here celebrating the fact that
I spent another year waitressing
which is what I've been doing
since 13. And according to you
I'll be 37 before
I can even throw a decent punch
which after working this speed bag
for a month and getting nowhere
I now realize may be
God's simple truth. Other truth is
my brother's in prison,
my sister cheats on welfare
by pretending one ofher babies
is still alive, my dad is dead
and my mama weighs 312 pounds.
If I was thinking straight
I'd go back home,
find a used trailer,
buy a deep fryer and some Oreos.
Problem is, this is the only thing
I ever felt good doing.
If I'm too old for this,
then I got nothing.
- That enough truth to suit you?
- This your speed bag?
Put yours behind the counter.
Wish I could say I wore it out.
Hold it.
Il'll show you a few things
and then we'll get you a trainer.
- No, sorry.
- You're in a position to negotiate?
Yes, sir. Because I know if you train
me right, I'm going to be a champ.
- I seen you looking at me.
- Out of pity.
Don't you say that if it ain't true!
I want a trainer. I don't want
charity, and I don't want favors!
lf you're not interested,
then I got more celebrating to do.
What the hell are you doing?
- If I'm going to take you on...
- You won't never regret it.
- Listen to me. If I take you on...
- I promise l'll work so hard.
- This is a mistake already.
- I'm listening, boss.
If I take you on, you don't say
anything, you don't question me.
You don't ask "Why?". You don't say
anything except "Yes, Frankie".
And I'm going to try to forget
the fact that you're a girl.
- It's all I ask.
- Don't cry if you get hurt.
- All right.
- We got a deal.
No, not quite.
I'll teach you how to fight
then we'll get you a manager
and I'm off down the road.
- I hate to argue with you...
- That's how we're doing it.
I teach you and you go off
and make a million dollars.
I don't care. Get your teeth
knocked out, I don't care.
I don't want to hear about it,
that's the only way I'll do it.
One of the things I've noticed
is you never move your feet.
You've got to move your feet,
that's the best thing l'll teach you.
Here's what you do.
Bend your knees a little bit.
Get in an athletic position. Look
like you're going to hit something.
- Move them how, boss?
- Hit the bag.
- What'd I do wrong?
- You did two things wrong.
One is you asked a question and
two is you asked another question.
What I want you to do
it's not about hitting it hard,
it's how good you hit it.
So, watch me.
You can count with me if you want. On
a one count, I hit through the bag.
- Can you show me that again?
- Just say "one", please.
Just say "one". That's good.
Then I move over to my right foot.
My weight is shifting to my right foot.
Then I hit it with the back of my
hand, like I'm using an ice pick.
Then I come over,
I shift to my left foot
and I hit it with my right hand.
Ice pick movement again
and I come over on my right foot,
and hit it right.
Don't watch anything but my feet.
Keep on training.
You show them how to stand, keep
their legs under their shoulders.
To make a fighter, you got
to strip them down to bare wood.
Rest when you're dead. Come here.
You can't just tell them
to forget everything you know
because you got to make them
forget it in their bones.
Make them so tired they only
listen to you, only hear your voice,
only do what you say
and nothing else.
Move your feetaround.
Show them how to keep their balance
and take it away from the other guy.
How to generate momentum
off your right toe
and how to flex your knees
when you fire a jab.
How to fight backing up, so the other
guy doesn't want to come after you.
Then you got to show them all
over again. Over and over and over.
Till they think
they were born that way.
Okay. That's enough for today.
Good work.
Think I'm ready for a fight, boss?
Come here.
- You're not breathing.
- Hate to disagree with you.
Every time you get under pressure,
you're holding your breath.
- Stop doing that.
- Okay.
But other than that, I'm doing good,
right? I mean, for a girl.
I don't train girls.
- Think I'm ready for a fight?
- We'll get a manager.
I'd like to but you've been
keeping me too busy.
- Got any family, boss?
- What?
You been spending all this time with
me. I didn't know if you had any.
- I've got a daughter, Katy.
- That's family.
- We're not exactly close.
- How much she weigh?
Trouble in my family
comes by the pound.
Not very big.
Used to be very athletic
I don't know if she kept it up.
So, what do you think?
I ready for a fight?
Come here for a minute, will you?
I need to see you
in the back for a minute.
Sally is a good manager,
has a couple of Golden Gloves boys.
- Looking for a girl, Sally?
- Looking for a good one.
Well, see, there you go.
Nice working with you, girlie.
- What'd you want?
- Nothing.
I been watching you work,
you got a hell of a left.
You want to give this a try,
see if it's a fit?
I think you're ready for a fight.
What am I doing wrong? Every time
I get inside, she's on me.
- You're doing great. Keep punching.
- I ain't doing great. I'm losing.
You're wearing herdown.
- Nice night, ain't it?
- Jesus Christ!
That's Lonnie Washington's girl.
Hell of a fighter. 11-0.
Keep your left up.
Lonnie's got a lot of good fighters.
He's got Joey Adagio,
lightweight champ?
Your left!
Wouldn't have been my choice
for a first fight,
but Sally's a good manager.
He must think she can take her.
Keep your left up!
You think she can hear you
from back here?
If Maggie loses, it wouldn't
mean anything to Sally.
Might even help him.
Lonnie's girl gets another win,
Lonnie might let Sally's lightweight
fight Joey Adagio for the title.
Sally's trying to set a fight
with Adagio?
What do I know? I just come
because I enjoy the fights.
Break!
- Come here.
- Getover here!
You're dropping your left hand.
Quit dropping your left hand.
- You mind if I talk to my fighter?
- You're doing a hell of a job.
Is this the way
you advise your lightweight?
- Dunn, what are you doing?
- I'm talking. What are you doing?
- Is this your fighter?
- It's my fighter!
- It ain't fitting very well.
- Fine. You take her.
- She can't fight worth a shit!
- What's going on?
I was late. Sally was subbing for me.
Is this your fighter?
- Yes. This is my fighter.
- You got ten seconds.
I keep holding my left up, then I
throw a punch and it keeps dropping.
- Let it drop.
- That'd be a lot easier.
She thinks she knows you. Every time
you drop itshe comes over the top.
You wait for her, see?
That's all she's thinking about.
- She cocks that big right hand...
- I hear you, boss.
Step to the side and come over
with a big good night hook!
- Got it right here.
- Fight or I'm calling it.
The body knows what fighters don't,
how to protect itself.
A neck can only twist so far.
Twist it just a hair more
and the body says:
"l'll take it from here,
because you don't know
what you're doing."
See the way she did that?
Sugar Ray would do that.
Girl's gotsugar.
"Lie down, rest and we'II talk about
this when you regain your senses."
lt's called the knockout mechanism.
You forgot the rule.
Now, what is the rule?
- Keep my left up?
- To protect yourself at all times.
- What is the rule?
- Protect myself at all times.
You gave me away.
How was that protecting me?
- It wasn't.
- It's okay.
- I'll work on my left, boss.
- Drink your water.
- Other than that, how'd I do?
- You did fine.
- You going to leave me again?
- Never.
That place you work, do they have
homemade lemon meringue pie?
- Sure.
- Not with the canned filling crap?
Big can, yea size.
Says "homemade" on the label.
- I want you to take the weekend off.
- It's only Thursday.
- You going to argue with me?
- Know better than to do that.
All fighters
are pig-headed some way or other.
Some part ofthem always thinks they
know better than you about something.
Can you spare a few minutes
for the lmmaculate Conception?
Truth is, even if they're wrong,
even if that one thing
is going to be the ruin ofthem,
if you can beat that last bit
out of them...
...then they ain't fighters at all.
- Thought I said I'd see you Monday.
- You sure did, boss.
- That was last night.
You said not to argue with you!
Damn woman won't do a thing
I tell her!
- You want my advice?
- What?
- Where are your shoes?
- I'm airing out myfeet.
- You got big holes in your socks.
- They're not that big.
Didn't I give you money
for some new ones?
These are my sleeping socks.
My feet like a little air at night.
How come you're wearing them
in the daytime?
Because my daytime socks
got too many holes in them.
If I give you some more money,
you buy some new socks.
I'd be tempted,
but I couldn't say for sure.
Might find its way to the track!
It's over!
Didn't take Maggie long
to hit her stride.
- I got the breathing thing down.
- No, you ain't breathing,
because you're knocking them out
in the first round.
- I thought that was the point.
- The point is to get good.
Can't get good if you keep knocking
them out in the first round.
How am I going to get you fights?
Nobody wants to see
their fighter embarrassed.
- Why am I still doing four-rounders?
- You hadn't the lungs for 6 rounds.
I do if I keep knocking them out
in the first round.
Frankie made her fight
one more four-rounder
just to let her know who was boss!
Maggie left no doubt about it.
Her first six-rounder
didn't go quite as smooth.
Maggie didn't knock her out
till the end of the first round.
After that, no manager wanted
to put his fighter in with Maggie.
Frankie had to go into his pocket
to get her decent fights,
sweetening the purse
by paying managers on the side.
That only worked for so long, then
Frankie did something he hated doing.
He took a chance.
He moved her up in class.
That could've been a mistake.
Break! Step back! Time!
Give us two seconds, will you?
- Your nose is broken.
- Fix it!
- I can't.
- You can fix it.
- I can't. I've gotto call it.
- I've seen what you can do, fix it!
I can snap it back into place,
but I can't stop the bleeding.
- The ring doctor's going to call it.
- Stop the blood, I can beat her.
Bite down on this.
- Inhale.
- What?
Breathe in!
In 20 seconds this turns into a
geyser and sprays the front raw.
20 seconds, that's all you've got.
Now get going.
Go to your corner!
Mo Cuishle.
- Whatcha reading?
- What's she saying?
- Wants to know what you're reading.
- It's Yeats. Keep your head back.
Why don't you talk a little Yeats to
her? Show her whata treat that is.
- When they going to get to her?
- I'm okay, Frankie.
- What'd you learn tonight?
- Always protect myself.
- What's the rule?
I'll be right here.
- How you doing?
- Me? I'm not the one who's hurt.
- Broken nose don't hurt that much.
- Why are you telling me that?
No reason.
But some wounds are too deep
or too close to the bone.
No matter how hard you work at it,
you just can't stop the bleeding.
- Did you write your daughter?
- Every week.
I've no idea
why you come to church.
After her 12th straight knockout,
Frankie got a couple of good offers.
The first was to fight
Billie "The Blue Bear" Osterman
for the WBA welterweight title.
Billie was a former prostitute
out of East Berlin.
Had a reputation for being
the dirtiest fighter in the ranks.
Didn't seem to matter to her that
those things could kill a person.
And the crowds loved her.
He turned it down
without even telling her.
The next was to fight the British
champ, a girl Billie just beat.
Not interested.
He turned that down, too.
That's a lot of money, boss.
You're making money.
What are you still working here for?
- It's a title match, right?
- Are you British?
It's a title you can't take away.
She's got nothing to lose.
- You got nothing to win.
- Might still be a good fight.
I just brought you up
to welterweight.
Too good to fight these contenders,
you'd rather fight a bullshit champ?
Didn't notice
I was fighting any contenders.
You can get yourself
another manager any time you want.
If you'd learn to protect
your face a little better
I wouldn't have
to turn down this money.
My face out there so much it's a
miracle I ain't been knocked out yet!
You can't work here anymore tonight.
I made us a reservation.
You might want to shower.
Here you go. Here you go.
- What's this?
- I know what you're wishing for.
Go on, blow!
33 ain't so old.
I was still fighting at 39.
Fought for 23 years.
- How's it going, Scrap?
- Doing good, Mickey.
- What will you have?
- Coffee.
- You two not speaking?
- Don't hardly know him.
I met Frankie
right after my 37th birthday.
He was picking up cut work.
He used to patch me up
when I thought it was impossible.
- Good man to have in your corner.
- Yes, he is.
He stayed with me
through my last fight in San Berdu.
My manager was off
getting drunk somewhere,
it was just Frankie and me.
I was taking a hellacious beating.
Everybody's got a particular number
offights in them.
Nobody tells you what that number is.
Mine was a 109.
I just didn't want to admit it.
Fourth round this cut opens up.
Blood starts pouring into my eye.
They should've stopped the fight,
but I was a black man in San Berdu,
blood was what I was there for.
Round after round, I kept
getting Frankie to patch me up.
He's talking about throwing in
the towel,
but he ain't my manager,
he can't throw in nothing.
Round after round,
he's arguing with me.
I'm laughing because
it's getting more to him than to me.
I go 15 rounds lose by decision.
Next morning I lose the eye.
In 23 years
he's never said a thing about it.
Doesn't have to. I can see it in
his face every time he looks at me.
Somehow Frankie thinks
he should've stopped that fight,
should've saved my eye.
Spends his life wishing he could
take back that 109th fight.
I wanted to go to 110.
Thing is,
if you want to get to the title
maybe he's not the one
to take you there.
You tell Mr. Mack
we'd be here tonight?
- Eat your cupcake.
- No, I got it.
It's the rule.
Always protect yourself.
People never take theirown advice.
If she was going to leave Frankie,
better she did it to him then.
Mr. Mickey Mack?
I'm Maggie Fitzgerald.
I hear you're a real good manager.
Doing good things for Big Willie.
But I thought you should know
I ain't never leaving Mr. Dunn,
so you don't need to make
any more excuses to bump into me.
Sorry for interrupting your dinner.
Maggie always did like
taking them out in the first round.
The letters always came back
marked the same way,
"Return to Sender".
I will make you some coffee.
- What are you doing with your money?
- Saving it.
You save enough of it, you ought
to get yourself a little house.
- Cash, no mortgage.
- It'll take me a while.
It might be a stretch, but you got
to get yourself a place of your own.
Go around wasting iton things that
don't matter and what do you got?
You understand? Pretty soon, you
wait long enough, you got nothing.
Okay, soon as I get the money.
I made a lot of mistakes, I'm trying
to keep you from doing the same.
- I know, boss.
- I'm not going to live forever.
- What is it?
- A tape on that girl in England.
If you're going to go for the title,
we got some moves to...
Get the hell down!
You know how old I am?
You're welcome, darling.
Now let me put this in the machine.
What machine?
- Don't have a TV, huh?
- No.
- Ten minutes, luv.
- Thank you.
- Man says he loves me.
- I bet he's not the first to say it.
First since my daddy.
- I win, you think he'll propose?
- You win, I'll propose.
I've got you a gift here.
- They gave you somebody else's.
- No. This is it.
- What does it mean?
- It's something in Gaelic.
Real silk thread.
From the United States of America
the challenger Maggie Fitzgerald!
"Mo Cuishle".
Did you see what was on her robe?
She wasn't the main attraction.
She was on the undercard
of a middleweight title fight.
But ask someone who was there,
they couldn't tell you
who else fought that night.
She's tough.
I can't get close enough to hit her.
- You know why that is?
- Why?
She's a better fighter than you are.
She's younger, stronger
and more experienced.
What are you going to do about it?
I could ask someone.
Good.
You find out, you let me know.
Whatever it meant, the name stuck.
Maggie fought in Edinburgh
and Paris, Brussels and Amsterdam.
It was always "Mo cuishle".
Seems there're lrish people
everywhere, or people who want to be.
By the time
they came back to the States,
Maggie was in a whole new league.
After that they got another offer
to fight for the title.
What's the split?
- 60-40.
- Good.
We'll take 60 and you take 40,
being as that Maggie's the draw.
- That little girl?
- You think I'm wrong, really?
You think people are saying
they want to see some scrabby Kraut
beat up on Miss What's-her-name?
You find someone who says that
and we'll take the40.
They're at 60-40
but they'll come up to 50-50.
How's that girl doing?
She's got a concussion
and a broken eardrum.
- She be all right?
- And if she isn't?
Maybe I should send her something.
You could send her your check,
I'm sure she'd take it.
That little house we talked about?
I bought it.
- Well, smart girl.
- For my mama.
It's a mile from where she lives.
No mortgage, just like you said.
- You're a good daughter.
- She doesn't know about it yet.
I was hoping maybe we could stay
an extra day, drive over there?
- I know she wants to meet you.
- Yeah. We could do that.
Oh, my God! Mama, come on out here.
Mary M's here.
- This is the Johnson's old house.
- Not anymore.
It's all yours, mama.
For you and Mardell and the kids!
- You bought this for me?
- All yours, free and clear!
- Darling...
- There's no fridge, no stove.
They'll be here before you move in.
- How much money did this cost you?
- You never mind that.
- You shouldn't a done this.
- You need a decent place.
You shouldn't a done it!
You should've asked me first!
Government's gonna find out about it,
they'll stop my welfare.
- They ain't.
- You're fine, you're working,
but I can't live without my welfare!
- I send you money.
What about my medicine?
Medicaid going to cut me off.
- How I'm gonna get my medicine?
- I'll send you more money.
Hope you don't expect J.D. to move
in here with us. He's getting out.
Why didn'tyou
just give me the money?
Why'd you have to buy me a house?
Didn't have to, mama. But it's yours.
You want the money? Sell it.
You didn't mean nothing hurtful,
but you don't think things through.
- That's true, Mama.
- I'll try and keep the house.
I just worry about
all those expenses.
I'll send you some more money.
That man hitting you?
It's from the fight.
I'm a fighter, Mama.
Find a man, Mary M.
Live proper.
People hear about what you're doing
and they laugh.
Hurts me to tell you,
but they laugh atyou.
You ever own a dog?
Nope. Closest I ever came
was a middleweight from Barstow!
My daddy had a German Shepherd, Axel.
Axel's hindquarters were so bad
he had to drag himself
room to room by his front legs.
Me and Mardell'd bust up laughing
scoot across the kitchen floor.
Daddy was so sick by then,
he couldn't hardly stand himself.
But one morning he got up
and carried Axel to his rig
and the two of them went off
into the woods, singing and howling.
Wasn't till he got home
that night, alone,
that I saw the shovel
in the back of the truck.
Sure miss watching
the two of them together.
I got nobody but you, Frankie.
Well, you've got me.
At least, that is until
we find you a good manager.
Can we stop just up here?
This place has
the best lemon pie around.
None of that canned filling crap!
Now I can die and go to Heaven!
I used to come here with Daddy.
I wonder if a place like this
is for sale.
I got a little bit of savings.
- What the hell's Danger looking at?
- Another bottle of water.
Want to come to Vegas with us?
Watch you suffer
over the nickel slots.
- My hart can't take it.
- She's got a title shot.
The Blue Bear. Million dollars,
split right down the center.
I could use a good second. Can't
find one, I thought I'd ask you.
Why would I want to do that?
Because you're a half-blind old fool
who never got there himself.
you might like to feel what's like
to be in a ring on a title match.
Excuse me for feeling sorry for you.
No, you pick up somebody
there in Vegas.
- Somebody with young hands!
- You're not going to cry, are you?
- I've already got one girl.
- I leave this place for one day,
got any idea what it would look
like when I come back?
- Kind of like it looks right now.
- Go to hell!
Tell Maggie don't come back
without a belt!
Will do!
I got a question,
but I feel real stupid asking it.
No such thing
as a stupid question there, Danger.
How'd you get all the ice in here
through this little tiny hole?
I been thinking on it,
can't figure it out.
- Why don't I show you, Danger?
- You could show me?
Also, I was kind of thinking
I might be ready for a fight.
- I got the tickets. You ready?
- We're flying?
- Would you rather drive?
- You're asking me?
Would you rather fly
or would you rather drive?
- I finally get to decide something?
- That's what I'm saying.
Fly there, drive back.
That's the stupidest thing I've ever
heard. How are we going to do that?
You said it was up to me.
- Give them hell there, Danger.
- The toilet's overflowing.
Flippy, come here for a minute.
Dumb-ass!
Could be sitting up at The Mirage,
drinking mai tais,
looking at naked women!
Come on now, Flip.
Whatare you doing? Let him go.
I've gotcha now.
- We don't need no corner trainer.
- How'd I do, Mr. Scrap?
You did good, Danger.
You my man, you rock!
Come on, Flip. You ain't done.
You ain't even fight good yet.
Anybody can lose one fight, son.
You'll come back from this,
you'II be champion of the world.
No, I won't, Mr. Scrap.
- I should've known.
- We don't need this honky!
- Let me help you.
- Untie the Velcro for me.
Don't take the gloves off, man.
You ain't even used them, Danger.
- Mind if I borrow these?
- I thought your name was "Danger"!
I see. Now I get to fight
a retard and a old man.
Call ESPN, 'cause
you can't write this shit!
110.
Get a job, punk!
Win this one
and l'll tell you what it means.
I got you some pipers.
Jab her right it the tits,
until they turn blue and fall off.
Ladies and gentlemen, this is the
feature presentation of the evening.
In this corner,
the challenger, Maggie Fitzgerald,
in the red corner.
In the blue corner,
the WBA Welterweight
champion ofthe world,
Billie "The Blue Bear".
Fitzgerald is pushing the Blue Bear
around the ring, coming on strong.
Challenger darts in, lands a
combination to the head and the body.
A right hook stunts the champ.
Break it up!
Do that one more time, it'll cost you
a point, do you hear me?
Fight.
I'm going to take away one point.
One point deduction off the blue corner.
Ref, open your eyes!
The first round is in the books
on this championship match.
- Looking good.
- Pull that crap one more time,
you're disqualified.
- It's going to be all right.
- Got no doubt, boss.
Watch yourself,
stay away from this dame.
Go to the neutral corner!
Stay there, bitch!
Fitzgerald continues to pummel the
Blue Bear, the East German Champion.
Eyes are blurring.
- How many eyes do you need?
- One's enough.
What do I do about the Bear?
Do you know that step into
the outside and hook into the liver?
I been doing that.
She's made of steel.
Don't go to the liver this time,
hit her right up under her skinny ass.
Right in the sciatic nerve. Keep
digging it in there, digging it in.
- Keep sticking her.
- What about the Ref?
Keep yourself between the Ref and
the Bear and everything will be fine.
This is you.
You keep it going. You keep it up.
Get the doctor!
Come on. Breathe.
That's it. Breathe. Good.
Concentrate on me. Breathe. Good.
How you feeling, darling?
Growing a beard, boss?
Yeah, I thought it might help me
with the ladies.
Can't say it does.
- Does it hurt much?
- Don't hurt at all.
Where's Frankie?
He's out there
talking to the doctors.
Probably telling them
how to do their job.
They're telling him
I'm a C1 and C2 complete.
My spinal cord's so broke
they'll never be able to fix it.
Going to be frozen like this
the rest of my life.
I asked them to tell him. I don't
know how he's going to take it.
Did you see the fight?
Course I did.
You had her cold, Maggie.
I shouldn't a dropped my hands.
I shouldn't a turned.
Always protect myself,
how many times he tell me that?
Does like to repeat himself.
Will you tell him I'm real sorry?
No. I won't do no such thing, Maggie.
Damnedest thing.
So, what's the plan?
I know you got one, so you might
as well tell me what it is.
It's your fault
she's lying in there like that.
You kept after me until I trained
her. I know I shouldn't have done it.
Her being a girl and all.
Everything kept telling me not to.
Everything but you.
I'm going to get you out of here.
These doctors don't know squat.
Otherwise why would they
be living out here in the desert?
As soon as you're able to be moved
we'll find someplace where
they've actually studied medicine.
You just rest there. I'm on it.
Frankie must've called
every hospital in America
looking for somebody who'd tell him
they could fix her.
He came close twice
till they checked her over,
said there was nothing to be done.
Took two months till
she was stable enough to move.
- They got nurses for that.
- They're amateurs.
She developed skin ulcers because
she couldn't change positions.
They made the six-hour trip
by ambulance.
Fly there, drive back.
The rehab center Frankie found
was a nice place.
They took care of Maggie. She would
not have complained if they hadn't.
Took several hours every day
to get her ready for the wheelchair.
Since she couldn't breathe on her
own, her respirators were always on.
Oxygen was pumped into her
24 hours a day.
Maggie's mama called to say
they were all coming for a visit.
She waited by the window every day
for the next two weeks.
Frankie finally tracked them down
learned they'd checked
into their hotel six days earlier.
Kept leaving messages
which were never returned.
You don't have
to hang around all day.
I like it here. I don't mind.
If you weren't here, I'd come here
anyway to read my books.
Mama will be here soon,
share some of the burden.
It's no burden.
Here, read this.
That's enough. That's terrible!
l'll tell you in English
what you were saying.
Itsays: "I will arise
and go now and go to Innisfree.
And a small cabin build there,
of clay and wattles made.
And I shall have some peace there,
for peace comes dropping slow.
Dropping from the veils of the
morning,
to where the crickets sings."
Not bad, huh?
- You going to build a cabin, boss?
- Me?
You know, when you quit all this.
You mean boxing? No, l'll never quit.
Like the stink too much, I guess.
I could see you there, real easy,
with your books and lemon pie.
How about you?
Would you like to go live in a cabin?
I could learn how to bake.
Well, then, maybe I'll start looking.
I'm Frankie Dunn.
I met you back out in Missouri.
- Where's my little girl?
- You ought to go back and change.
She doesn't know you've been here
a week visiting Woody and Mickey.
We got business with my sister.
Why don't you just tell us where she is?
You must be J.D. the business guy.
There's some rides you missed.
- I'll tell her you couldn't make it.
- I drove here to visit my child.
You're suggesting I'm not a good
mother? Mary can't go nowhere
if we could have taken her
to Disneyland we would have.
- Margaret Fitzgerald?
- Right down here. 301.
I saw myself breathing!
My body was going up and down.
I thought,
"Why didn't somebody tell me?"
Your hear needs washing.
It's kind of greasy.
- It's just some kind of legal thing.
- What is it?
- How we all doing here?
- We ain't got a lot oftime.
Mr. Johnson is charging us a lot of
money to make sure this is legal.
Leave that
and l'll read it to her later.
You part of our family?
Stay the hell out ofthis.
- Read it to me, Mama.
- It's just something legal...
...to protect your money.
- You don't have to worry.
The Boxing Commission's paying
for all this, everything.
What if they don't? Mr. Johnson
says they can take my house.
Assign your assets to your mother
and no one will touch them.
No doctors, no funeral expenses.
Nothing.
Why don't you leave it
and l'll read it to her later on...
This isn't your business.
All right. I'll be out in the hall.
You been a good daughter, Mary M.
You sign that paper,
it'll take care of your family,
the way your daddy
would have wanted you to.
How do you make your mark?
- Can you hold a pen?
- She gotta do it with her teeth.
- You gotta put it in her mouth.
- Here you go, honey.
- Did you see the fight, Mama?
- You know how I feel about that.
I did pretty good.
You lost, Mary M. Ain't yourfault,
the way I heard it, but you lost.
Don't want to lose
the rest of what you got left.
- What happened to you?
- What's that supposed to mean?
You take Mardell and J.D.
and get home.
Before I tell that lawyer that you
were so worried about your welfare
you never signed those house papers
like you were supposed to.
So any time I feel like it
I can sell that house
from your fat,
lazy, hillbilly asses!
And if you ever come back,
that's exactly what I'll do.
Maybe someone ought to count to ten!
Don't smell real pretty,
does it, Doc?
We might have to lose it, Maggie.
They took my leg, boss.
It's gonna be all right. You hear?
I always hear your voice, boss.
You need anything?
I need to know
what "Mo Cuishle" means.
You didn't win,
I don't have to tell you.
You're the meanest man I ever met,
no wonder no one loves you!
You remind me of my daddy.
Well, he must have been
a very intelligent, handsome man!
You ain't gonna make me
talk no more Yeats, are you?
I was looking at this catalog
from City College.
I thought I'd get you a wheelchair,
maybe the kind that operates
by blowing through a straw.
I thought maybe you'd like
to go back to school.
I got a favor to ask you, boss.
Anything you want.
Remember what my daddy did for Axel?
Don't even think about that.
I can't be like this, Frankie.
Not after what I've done,
I have seen the world.
People chanted my name.
Not my name,
some damn name you gave me,
but they were chanting for me.
I was in magazines.
You think I ever dreamed
that'd happen?
I was born at two pounds,
one-and-a-half ounces.
Daddy used to tell me
I fought to get into this world
and I'd fight my way out.
That's all I want to do, Frankie.
I just don't want to fight you
to do it.
I got what I needed.
I got itall.
Don't let them
keep taking itaway from me.
Don't let me lie here till I can't
hear those people chanting no more.
I can't.
Please, don't ask me.
I'm asking.
In the middle of the night,
Maggie had found her own solution.
She had bit her tongue.
Look at me.
Nearly bled to death
before they stitched her up.
She came around and ripped them out
before Frankie even got there.
They stitched her up again,
padded the tongue
so she couldn't bite.
You can't do it, you know that.
I do, Father.
You don't know how thick she is,
how hard it was to train her.
Other fighters would do
exactly what you say to them
and she'd ask,
"why this" and "why that"
and do it her own way, anyway.
How she fought for the title...
Wasn't by anything...
it wasn't by listening to me.
But now she wants to die
and I just want to keep her with me.
And I swear to God, Father,
it's committing a sin by doing it.
By keeping her alive,
I'm killing her.
Do you know what I mean?
How do I get around that?
You don't. You step aside, Frankie.
You leave it with God.
She's not asking for God's help.
She's asking for mine.
I've seen you at mass
almost every day for 23 years.
A man who comes to church this much
can't forgive himself for something.
Whatever sins you're carrying,
they're nothing compared to this.
Forget about God or Heaven and Hell.
If you do this thing, you'll be lost
somewhere so deep,
you'll never find yourself again.
I think I did it already.
We're keeping her sedated
so she won't try that again.
I went to see Maggie this morning.
- You must have been somewhere else.
- Yeah.
You got a fight I don't know about?
lt wasn't your fault.
I was wrong to say that.
You're damn right.
I found you a fighter and you made
her the best fighter she could be.
And I killed her.
Don't say that.
Maggie walked through that door
with nothing but guts,
no chance in the world
of being what she needed to be.
A year and a half later, she fights
for the championship of the world.
You did that.
People die every day, Frankie,
mopping floors, washing dishes.
You know what their last thought is?
I never got my shot.
Because of you, Maggie got her shot.
If she dies today, you know
what her last thought will be?
"I think I did all right."
I know I could rest with that.
I'll get a cup of coffee.
All right.
I'm gonna disconnect
your air machine
then you're gonna go to sleep.
Then I'll give you a shot
and you'll stay asleep.
Mo Cuishle
means "my darling, my blood".
He gave her a single shot.
It was enough adrenaline
to do the job a few times over.
He didn't want her
going through this again.
Then he walked out.
I don't think he had anything left.
I went back to the gym.
Waited, figuring
he'd turn up sooner or later.
And that's when a ghost
came through the door.
I got to thinking what you said,
Mist' Scrap.
What was that, Danger?
Anybody can lose one fight.
That's the truth. Put your gloves on.
You missed a lot of training.
Will do, Mist' Scrap. Sure thing.
Frankie never came back at all.
Frankie didn't leave a note
and nobody knew where he went.
I'd hoped he'd gone to find you
and ask you one more time
to forgive him.
But maybe he didn't have
anything left in his heart.
I just hope he found someplace
where he could find a little peace.
A place set
in the cedars and oak trees.
Somewhere between
nowhere and good-bye.
But that's probably wishful thinking.
No matter where he is
I thought you should know what
kind of man your father really was.
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-