www.seedr.co.il - come visit to stream
your torrents with subtitles search
Prisoners of the Sun - Part 1
Just think... Tomorrow we'll
see old Cuthbert again.
Hmmm, yes.
Why so glum? Things are looking up.
I guess so, but I can't help feeling
we're being watched.
Aah, enjoy yourself. Look around you!
Amazing!
Look at that!
Look! A Llama!
Careful, Señor!
Why? Such a nice Llama!
Kitchy, kitchy, kitchy!
Thundering typhoons!
C'mon, Captain, it's time to
get back to the hotel!
When Llama angry, Senor, he always do that.
Filthy animal!
Blistering barnacle of a brute.
Those things shouldn't be allowed!
There's the inspector...
Huh!
Thomson & Thomson?
Interpol has sent us to
back up the inspector
on this this delicate mission.
Precisely...
And where's the "Pachacamac"?
Out there.
Beside the little tug,
with the the red funnel.
Let's have a look at this.
Ah! There she is.
Thundering typhoons!
Infectious disease on board!
It will be impossible to search
the ship until the port health
authorities have released her.
Hm! Another convenient coincidence?
Those doctors are taking forever.
Captain, just what is this "guano" stuff?
Guano?
Er, um!
How shall I put it?
Well, there's a sample of it!
Capitain! Look! A new flag...
Quarantined!
We wouldn't be able to board her
for days... maybe weeks!
You can't do this, Tintin.
It might be cholera...
the plague... yellow fever...!
I think they know we're on to them.
and I'll bet every man on that ship
is as healthy as you and me.
Well, what about the sharks, then?
Nuts to the sharks!
OK, stop, this is close enough!
Be a good boy, Snowy!
Good luck, lad!
Que pasa ahi abajo?
Que ha pasado, Chiquito?
No, es nada,
debe de ser el gato.
He's going back to his cabin.
Excuse me.
A little further to the west.
Professor Calculus!
Professor, wake up!
Professor!
The mummy's bracelet...!
Si...!, the bracelet of Rascar Capac.
What do you want with poor Calculus?
Your friend has donned the sacred
bracelet of the Incas...
That is sacrilege!.
The punishment for that is death!.
- Alonzo!
- No!
You there! Stop!
Devil! You'll pay for this!
Iconoclasts!
Pirates!
Guano gatherers! Murderers!
Let's get out of here!
Professor's Calculus' life is
in danger, Captain!.
We've got to get help.
You alert the police!
I'll stay here and watch the ship.
Whew! At last!
Come on... come on!
- Si...
- Thundering typhoons!
Get me the Chief Inspector!
- He's asleep, Senor.
- Then wake him!
This is urgent!
Blistering blundered! He hung up.
Somebody's coming ashore.
Blue Blistering Barnacles!
I can't stand here all night!
Are you going to answer it?
Certainly not! I'm asleep!
You can't be asleep,
You're talking to me!
You know very well that
I talk in my sleep...
Lazy bones! Next time it's your turn!
Thomson!?
And about time, too!
Great snakes!
They're carrying somebody ashore!
It's got to be the Professor...
Tintin...!Tintin...! Tintin...!
No use shouting ourselves hoarse.
Tintin's gone.
Let's try to pick up his tracks...
It's like looking for a
needle in a haystack...
To be precise, we look like needles in a...
Ah... aah... isn't this the
Professors' pendulum?
Without a shadow of a lout...
er, shadow of a doubt.
Over here.
Look at these footprints...
several men with Llamas.
- Question is, which way did they go?
- I know.
Nothing simpler.
Cuthbert's pendulum?!
Spot on!
And this utensil is going to
lead us directly to its owner.
Dowsing is a question of
having the right touch.
See? The pendulum is pointing south.
Then south we must go.
If you don't mind, I'm heading north.
- Suit yourself.
- I'd better go and investigate...
That is to say, we better
go and investigate...
And keep your eyes open...!
Never you mind, they're open...
To be precise they're...
Excuse me, son. Have you seen a
young lad with a little white dog?
Yes, indeed and I know him well.
Tintin!?
Snowy!
What about Cuthbert?
We haven't got a moment to lose.
I overheard the kidnappers
say they were heading for Jauga.
If we hurry, we just might
catch up with them by train..
What a mob!
This train is going to be crammed.
Have a good trip, Señores.
Ow!... Thundering typhoons!
That's odd! There's not another
soul in this carriage.
We're alone... strange.
We must be pretty high up.
We've been climbing steadily for hours...
Hello... We're slowing down!
We must be coming to a station...
What!?
Oh! No!
Captain! Our section has been unhooked.
What?
Blistering Barnacles!
- Quick. Jump!.
- Jump?
Snowy, Snowy... come on!
We're going too fast!
A river.
This is our only chance, Snowy.
Snowy?
Oh, good boy!
We can thank our lucky stars we got out!
I wonder what's become of the Captain?
I wonder what's become of Tintin?
Hey! Stop!
Thank goodness you're save!
Such an unfortunate accident...
That was no accident!
We must get to Jauga as fast
as possible.
Well, not much help from the police...
he seemed to be afraid
to even talk to us.
Let's split up and question
some of the locals.
Right.
His name is Calculus. A short man...
with a little beard... wearing glasses?
No say...
- About this high?
- No say...
- Had a little beard.
- No say.
- With spectacles.
No say... no say... no say...
"No say! No say!"
Blistering barnacles!
They all seem to be afraid.
One last try... that young orange seller.
The bullies!
Aren't you ashamed bullying
a child like that?
Why...? You...!
Go for it, Pedro!
Young swine. You little rat!
Stand still, smart guy...!
Yeoww...!
Wait, you little...!
Good boy, Snowy!
Well, I'm no further ahead.
- Pssst... Senor?
- What?... Who...
Please be quiet, Senor!
Pretend to tie your shoelace.
I know where you can find
the man you're looking for.
Tomorrow at dawn come
to the bridge of the Inca.
You go now! It is dangerous
for me to be here!
I just hope it's not a trap.
You listen, Senor!
I see you help Indian boy.
You are brave. But you not go
and search for your friend.
Look! I don't know who you are.
But I'll tell you, I would never
abandon a friend.
That is foolish!
But take this...
it may save your life...
So where is this guide of yours?
Psst... psst...
It's the little orange seller.
So it was you?
No make noise.
If Indians see us...
they kill us.
You come now!
You wait here!
I don't like this.
Thundering Typhoons!
Not another pair of
perambulating fire-pumps!
Llamas very gentle, Senor
You not be afraid.
Afraid? Me?
Eyeoww!
You miserable iconoclast!
No hit, Señor!
- When Llama angry...
- I know!
"He always do that. "
Blistering barnacles!
You know... we don't even know your name?
Zorrino, Senor.
Well, Zorrino... you can tell me now,
where is our friend?
He's taken to the Inca.
The inca? I thought the last
of the Incas died 400 years ago?
Many things you not know.
Where is this Inca, then?
The temple of the sun, Senor.
Your friend is the prisoner of Sun God.
Temple of the sun? Sun God?
There is "Chulpa", Señor.
We spend the night there.
Good night, Captain!
Make sure you wake me for my watch.
I will. Sleep well, you two...
Good night Zorrino...
Good night, Senor Tintin.
Amazing! An Inca plant in bloom...!
Excuse me, Señor Inca!
Have you a Licence for that gun...?
Licence?
Licence...?!
Sacrilege! Sacrilege!
The fire of heaven will strike you down!
Good heavens!
They let me sleep on.
Captain?
Zorrino?
Great snakes! Where could they be?
Captain!
What have you found, Snowy?
What's going on?
Cut the cords and get me out
of this before I go crazy!
Hurry!
Billions of blue
blistering barnacles!
Got it!
This miserable reptile has spent the
night waltzing along my spine!
Well, whoever they are they got
our Llamas, our supplies, our guns
and they got Zorrino!
But there's one thing they missed...
Zorrino's hat.
Snowy! Snowy, here boy!
It's up to you now, Snowy...
Find Zorrino, Snowy! Find him!
Come on! After him!
Hey! Not so fast, you mountain goat!
There they are!
They'll pass directly below us!
If we take a short cut down the
cliff we can surprise them!
Snowy... you stay here!
More likely
we'll break our necks.
Better find another way, Captain...
This is very steep...!
Blistering typhoons!
Don't move!
Captain!
Que pasa?
You tell us, where is your friend?
No say!
Tell us or die!
Well... What do you know!
He's right behind you!
- You! No joke!
- No joke!
Hands up!
I'll take that.
Untie Zorrino, Captain.
I'll keep an eye on them.
Good to see you, little one.
Thank you, my friends.
Look out!
Hooray!
Thundering typhoons!
And anyone who crosses our
path again is a dead duck!
You... just... wait!
Thank you for saving me, Senor Tintin!
We wouldn't abandon you, Zorrino.
But where is Snowy?
Snowy!
I have news of your friend, Señores.
Professor Calculus?
I hear Indians talking. They're only
about a half day ahead of us.
Maybe we catch them soon if we hurry.
That's good news, Zorrino.
Let's get going!
You sure we can't do it...
without these
cushion-footed ruminants?
Oh, no, Señor!
Llamas is very helpful.
Very gentle, Senor...
You try to be friends, you see...
Blistering barnacles!
Fast Forward to Part 2
for the conclusion...
Prisoners of the Sun - Part 2
Okay, Snowy! We're coming.
We're coming!
- Snowy!
- A condor has taken him.
He'll be eaten alive.
Maybe I can scare it off...
There! Snowy's safe for the time being.
But I gotta work fast!
What are you going to do?
I'm gonna get Snowy down from there...
Be careful!
Snowy...!
I hope he's okay?
Snowy!
Well, hello to you too.
Is he okay...?
Now hold still!
Heads up!
Blistering typoons!
The condor's back!
Look out, Tintin!
Hey! No, no!
Hang on, Snowy!
Tintin, Tintin!
Are you okay?
Blistering barnacles!
Hmm... how peculiar.
The pendulum says that
they are somewhere... high up.
Ha... cheeh!... Blistering barnacles!
Ouch! Blue blistering barnacles!
Aagh...!
...how it could kill you...
- Yes...
- Quite!
Alright... Snowy, leave me alone!
We'll have to try and cross here.
It's our only chance!
Give me the rope, Zorrino.
Here goes.
Now... who's first?
I go first to show rope very strong.
He's got guts that boy.
Thundering typhoons!
You need a cool head for this!
Oops! My hat!
For heaven's sake, Captain!
Forget your hat...
Not on your life!
This hat means a lot to me...!
Okay, come on!
Our turn, Snowy!
Hang on, Snowy! We're nearly there!
Aaah...!
Tintin?!... Tintin...!
Tintin not dead, is he, Captain?
My poor Zorrino, Tintin is gone.
We'll never see him again... ever!
Hey...! Captain! Zorrino...!
That voice! I must be dreaming!
It can't be!
Captain!
I'm behind the waterfall!
Throw me a rope!
Hang on, Tintin!
Here it comes.
Got it!
- Come on in!
- In there?
Yes, in here... you have to see this!
Don't worry, it's only a thin
curtain of water.
If you say so...
Blistering barnacles!
Remarkable, isn't it?
Where are we?
Incredible!
Come on, Zorrino...!
- Zorrino!
- Tintin!
What do you think, Captain?
I would say we've stumbled into some long-
forgotten entrance to
the temple of the sun...
It'll be dark as the belly
of a whale in there.
No... I had a look...
the rock is some sort of phosphorous mineral
that actually gives off light!
I've got a hunch
we're not far from Professor Calculus.
Huh! Oh-oh...
Looks like a dead end!
I think Snowy's found something.
Where are you going?
Good boy, Snowy!
Wow...!
Inca Mummies!
This must be some kind of tomb...!
If I'm not mistaken, Snowy, this looks
like it could be a secret doorway.
Tintin?
Blistering barnacles!
Give me a hand!
Now! Where the devil are...?!
- Who's that?
- Look, Captain!
Help me give this slab a push!
Right! I sure don't feel like
hanging about in here!
I don't think I like the company.
One, two, three... heave..!
It moved! And again!
One, two, three...!
Sacrilege! Seize them!
Sea gherkins!
Ectoplasms! Poltroons! Terrorists!
Don't cry, Zorrino...
We'll get out of this, you'll see.
Oh.. The medallion!
...but take this medallion...
it may save your life...
I wonder... here, Zorrino...
Take good care of this,
it might come in handy.
Strangers... you have
violated the sacred temple.
You must pay for this sacrilege
with your lives.
Do you really think we'd let ourselves
get massacred just like that?
You tin-hatted tyrant!
Noble Prince of the Sun,
we have never sought to commit sacrilege.
We were simply looking
for our friend, Professor Calculus.
Your friend dared to wear the
sacred bracelet of Rascar Capac.
He too will be put to death.
Blistering barnacles!
You've no right to kill him!
It's murder. Pure and simple!
But it is not we who will put you to death.
It is the sun itself.
It's rays will set alight your pyre.
As for this young Indian who betrayed us...
he will be sacrificed at once
on the altar of the Sun God...
Billions of Blistering blue barnacles! Don't
you dare touch a hair on this boy's head!
Zorrino, the medallion.
Where did you steal that,
little viper?
I not steal, Prince of the Sun.
He... he gave me this medallion.
I beg leave to speak. It is I,
noble Prince of the Sun...
who gave the sacred token
to the young stranger.
You, Huascar?
A high priest of the Sun God...
You gave this talisman to our enemy?
I did so, because he showed great
courage in defense of one of our race.
He is not an enemy, O Noble Prince.
Good, Huascar, your action
will save the young Indian.
But the two strangers must
be sacrified to the sun.
However, I will grant them one favor.
They may choose the day and the hour
when the rays of the sacred sun
will light their pyre,
within the next 30 days.
Let the strangers be taken away
and confine them till tomorrow.
The Prince of the Sun has spoken...!
Well... We're up to our necks this time!
Huh...!
Thundering typhoons!
Where did you find this newspaper?
Have you forgotten? You told me
to keep it to light a fire.
Won't be needing it now.
There'll be fire alright.
Now where are they?
The pendulum says they're very low.
Hmmm... now that's interesting.
What's the date today? The 15th?
Yes, if it makes any difference!
The tomorrow's the 16th!
Eureka! We're saved.
Thundering typhoon!
What's the matter with you?
I can't tell you now.
But we'll be alright!
The most important thing
for you to do is trust me
and do exactly as I say...
You'll understand later.
Well, strangers...
have you decided on the day
and the hour of your death?
Yes, Noble Prince of the Sun.
This very afternoon at precisely 4 O'clock.
Today is my friend the Captain's
birthday and I...
Have you gone crazy? You know it isn't...
Captain... you promised to trust me.
Guards...! Take them away!
The ceremony will take place
at the appointed hour.
You were so keen to see us
roasting on this barbecue!
So... here we are...
Trust me, Captain.
Captain! There! Calculus!
After all the time we've
spent searching for him!
Now we'll have all eternity
with him in the ever-after.
Why, Captain...
what a delightful surprise!
How are you?
Ohh... just dandy, Cuthbert.
And you too, my dear Tintin!
But tell me... what is all this performance?
Where are we?
We're with the Incas.
Ahh...! The cinema! Good!
You must congratulate the director for me!
What a clever
historical reconstruction!
Look at those extras... so natural.
Who would believe they're acting?
Let the sacrifice begin!
No! You can't! You can't!
What are we doing here?
According to the pendulum
they must be in a hot spot.
O Pachacamac,
Lord of the day!
Strike now with thine avenging rays!
O Magnificent Sun!
Do not heed your son's prayers!
Show all those present
that our death is not your desire.
Silence, dog!
How dare you call on the Sun!
O sublime Pachacamac!
If this sacrifice is not thy will...
hide thy shining face from us!
Poor Tintin! He's lost his mind.
Blistering Barnacles! What's happening?
An eclipse!
Haha! An eclipse!
No reason to panic, Captain.
It's only an eclipse, that's all...
Mercy! Mercy! I implore you!
Make the sun show his light again.
I will grant whatever you desire.
My desire is that the curse of
Rascar Capac be lifted
from the 7 explorers
who came to your temple.
They came seeking only knowledge
of what they believe was
a long forgotten culture.
So be it! You have my word!
O Sun,
Lord of the day!
Show mercy, I pray thee!
Pity thy children!
And show thy light once more!
By Rascar Camac... the Sun obeys him!
Quickly! Set them free!
Your newspaper saved us, Captain.
Life is magnificent!
Now what?
It says they're
getting bumped about.
These wax images enabled
me to maintain my spell
over the men for whom you plead.
But what about the crystal balls?
What were they for?
They contain a mystic liquid
obtained from Coco which...
plunged the victims into a deep sleep...
the perfect state for enchantment.
Goodbye, Zorrino.
Your place is here now.
Farewell, Tintin, my friend.
Before you leave, Noble strangers!
I too have a favour to ask of you.
I know what you're about to say,
Noble Prince of the Sun!
And you need have no fears about that!
I will never reveal to anyone the
whereabouts of the Temple of the Sun.
Me too! I swear it!
May... my beard be barbecued if
I breathe so much as a word!
Likewise! I swear I will never
again act in another film,
however glittering
the Hollywood contract!
Adios, Señores.
And may the sun shine upon you!
Hang on a sec! Don't leave just yet!
Nothing against you, personally,
but that pays a very old debt...
Let's go home, Captain.
The End...
-= www.OpenSubtitles.org =-